The Impostor

I

As the old man, after shoving the package into the safe, piled the money in on top of it, he was conscious of being watched. At the moment, you could have heard a lizard move. With a lizard’s rapidity, he turned. There was no one. Save for himself—for the safe, the chairs, the books, the immense table—the large, high-ceiled room was vacant.

For a moment he hesitated. Then, at once going to the table, he touched a button, sat down, and began to write.

898 West Eighty-ninth Street, New York,
4th November, 1915

I, George Gorgias Vulper, declare this to be my last will and testament.

I direct—

At the door came a knock, and a withered servant, his face inextricably wrinkled, appeared. Vulper looked up.

“Archibald, telephone to Doctor Dix. Ask him to come here at once.”

“Yes, sir.”

Before the servant could go, Vulper again was at it.

I give, devise, and bequeath to my son, Michael Vulper, the copyright of my work entitled “Commentaries on the Sutras of Patanjali.” I give, devise, and bequeath to my nephew, Arthur Glendenning, the sum of one dollar, free from inheritance tax and executors’ fees. I give, devise, and bequeath to the director and curators of the British Museum, London, my manuscript entitled “Alpha and Omega.” I give, devise, and bequeath to Shri Shankira my best wishes here and hereafter. The rest and residue of my property, of whatever kind, nature, and description, and wheresoever situated, of which I die seized and possessed, I give, devise, and bequeath to my ward, Camille Marcy, and to her heirs, executors, and assigns forever. I appoint the Amsterdam Trust Company—

The hurrying pen tripped and made a blot. Before Vulper could dry it, there was another knock, and a man with eyeglasses and a professional beard came in.

Vulper nodded at him.

“Dix, I want you to witness my will—you and Archibald. Will you look at it?”

The physician took the paper, glanced at it, and asked:

“Where is the manuscript?”

Vulper motioned at the safe.

“In that package under the junk.”

Dix moved over and looked in.

“There seems to be no end to that junk. You ought to—”

“Only ten thousand,” Vulper interrupted. “If it looks big, it’s because it’s all in twenty-dollar bills. I intended it for Mike, but I’ve changed my mind.”

“Yes, he told me. He was in my office today.”

“What about?”

“Several things. And you leave him a copyright!” Dix, examining the will again, exclaimed. “That’s very paternal. I doubt if it will stand.”

“Mike won’t contest it. Besides, he’s nobody’s fool. He’ll get along.”

Dix rattled the paper.

“It’s a pity, though, about his appearance. It would handicap any one else. But really, now, this nonsense about Shri! If the facts were known, you’d be judged incompetent and the will thrown out.”

Vulper took it in.

“You’re probably right. I’ll do it over and omit that.”

“And you leave everything to Miss Marcy?”

“I can’t do otherwise. It came to me from her father.”

“Well, it’s none of my business. But that manuscript, now. If it were read in court, it would queer your will. It’s all like Shri—the result of auditory and ocular hallucinations.”

Vulper nodded.

“To you—yes. You’re a physician—therefore, a materialist. You believe, as brutes do, only in the reality of things. And yet, as a physician, you ought to recognize the potentialities of the pineal gland. They have taken me to strange places; they have shown me strange things. I can no more prove it to you than I can dazzle a blind man. but the fact that I can see things which to you are invisible should be as comprehensible as that a composer can hear combinations of sounds to which you are deaf.”

“Oh, as for that, if I wanted to, I could see things myself. With morphine, apparitions can be scientifically produced. Only we don’t call them apparitions; we call them manifestations of morbid activity in certain clusters of the brain cells.” The physician paused and added: “That reminds me. Are you still taking chloral? You are? I told you not to. It’s a stupid thing to take at any age, but at yours it’s fatal.”

Vulper smiled. He was old and he looked it, but his face displayed that strength which is possessed only by those who know neither greed nor envy, neither hope nor fear. In strength such as that, there is infinite indulgence, equal unconcern; and that his smile expressed.

“If you’re trying to alarm me, you’ll hardly succeed. Only the unevolved fear death. What they should fear is life.”

Dix, who had been standing, sat down.

“Mr. Vulper, you have nothing to complain of. Life has treated you very well.”

“Hasn’t it, now? It’s been a wonderful experience. I didn’t have a dollar. I haven’t earned one since, and yet I have a quarter of a million, for which, now that my manuscript is done, I have no longer the slightest need.”

“Yes, you told me. Miss Marcy’s father divided his property between you and his daughter and made you her guardian.”

“And in so doing, afforded me the leisure to write that manuscript. It was more than decent of him—particularly as he had no other reason than that I saw things concerning him, things that affected him vitally, things that at first he could not credit, but that—”

“Things of the same order as Shri?” the physician, with professional intolerance, got in.

Vulper sat back on his hobby.

“Totally different. I can understand, though, that you don’t believe in him. Yet I showed you his letter.”

“A letter—yes. One that any crank might have sent you. It mentioned some book or other and warned you of the author’s fate.”

Vulper raised a hand.

“This country is full of cranks. I doubt if one of them ever heard of the book, or of Delormel who wrote it. The book, entitled ‘La Période Solaire’—‘The Solar Period’—was published in France. There, the law requires that of every book published, two copies shall be deposited in the National Library. The arrangements in that institution were such that no book had ever been stolen from it. Two copies of this book were deposited there. In twenty-four hours, they had vanished. In twenty-four hours, not a copy of the book was obtainable anywhere, and the man who wrote it was killed.”

Dix sniffed.

“By Shri?”

“Or some other Brahman.”

“But why?”

“Because the book revealed secrets that the esoteric sections of the Upanishads contain and which only the Brahman hierarchy may approach.”

“If you want to put it in that way, yes. Only he did it in the same manner in which I secured the data for my manuscript—out of the fourth dimension.”

Dix, plucking at his beard, said, and severely enough:

“The fourth dimension is a mathematical dream.”

Serenely the old man nodded.

“To the mathematician, perhaps. But not to the occultist. To him it is an actual plane on which he functions at will. That is what Swedenborg did, what Delormel did, what I have done. In the fourth dimension, I saw the past and the future. My manuscript contains them both. I say, Dix! You’re thinking I ought to be locked up.”

So neat and sure was the thrust that before it the physician backed.

“No, not that exactly. But I was thinking that if any other man told me what you have, I’d stand ready to sign his commitment.”

“Which reminds me. It’s my will I want you to sign, or, rather, to witness. I told you Mike wouldn’t contest it. That’s because I took a look ahead today and I couldn’t see any contest. But then I couldn’t see any will either, and because of that, and of other things, I’m in a hurry to make one. What is it, Archibald?”

Noiselessly the withered servant had entered.

“Doctor Dix’s secretary has telephoned. Mrs. Gehm is dying.”

Dix picked up his hat. With one hand, the old man stayed him; the other he pressed to his head.

“Mrs. Gehm? I’ve got her. Her name belies her, though. She’s a fat woman in a wig. She’d die of a motor accident in a thunderstorm.” He dropped his hands and added: “This is November. Assuming that the lady remains in New York, she has still five or six months to the good.”

Dix laughed; he couldn’t help it. The portrait of his patient had been exact.

“All the same,” he said, “I’ll have to go. I’ll be back, though, shortly.”

“Thank you. Please do,” replied Vulper, who scribbled on the will and tore it in two.

Meanwhile, in the drawing-room on the floor below, Camille Marcy, in breeches and boots, a man’s coat and a derby, was being talked at by Glendenning, Vulper’s nephew, a superior young man who did something in the insurance line and whose long face gave him the thoroughbred air of a horse.

Camille lacked that distinction. A nice, candid-looking girl of sweet-and-twenty, with good eyes, good features, a very good nose, and fair hair—which was docked—she had the appearance of having no nonsense, or at any rate very little of it, about her.

The room, comfortably and long since summarily furnished with articles selected haphazard by an occultist in a hurry, was ugly, but not depressing, for its ugliness was attenuated by this girl, whom Glendenning was asking to marry him.

Like getting up in the morning or having dinner, it was a habit of his. Camille had money of her own, enough for two—enough even in New York, where living costs everybody a little more than he has got—and Glendenning, who lived in a boarding house and had nothing except what he made, saw no reason why she should not honorably support him. He quite counted on it.

But Camille had no more idea of taking him than she had of jumping out of the window. Again and again she had told him so. Again and again he had whinnied and returned to the charge. Now, as he was prancing at her again, Mike Vulper looked in.

In the doorway, his figure showed straight and supple, but his face was sinister. It suggested a mask clapped there by nature in derision. Quasimodo must have had just such another. He was hideous.

Many are without suspecting it, but he had no illusions. Formerly felons were branded on the face; like their chains, it was part of the penalty. And it may be that, because of some forgotten sin committed in an unremembered life, this mask was his punishment. Otherwise he was free—apparently, that is, for actually he was chained. Hoops stronger than steel bound him to Camille. He loved her. Fancy a worm in love with a star! But fancy, too, common sense on the part of the worm, and the latter will know that the star is out of reach. Mike needed no one to tell him that. A mirror can be very instructive.

Now, as he entered the room, Glendenning turned, scowled, and, precisely as if he were eating ice, addressed him.

“And how is my cousin today?”

In the same voice, in the same tone, in the same manner, with a power of mimicry that was disconcerting, instantly Mike repeated the question. It was as if Glendenning had asked it twice.

Camille laughed and showed her teeth, which were well worth showing.

“Mike, you ought to be on the stage.”

Glendenning’s scowl deepened.

“Yes, as Romeo.”

Without heat, Mike took it up.

“Perhaps I may. I may surprise you yet, Glendenning.”

As he spoke, he moved to the girl, dropped his voice, whispered at her.

At that Glendenning fairly neighed.

“Ha! It won’t be with your manners, then! Good night, Camille.”

Camille nodded and turned to Mike. When they had both been younger, his face had frightened her. Latterly she had become accustomed to it as one does become accustomed to anything. In the interim, she had been in Europe, and he in this country. It was only since the war that they had been under this roof, which belonged to his father, her guardian.

“I wish you were blind,” he told her, when Glendenning had gone. “If you were, you would marry me. As it is, I’m off.”

Camille, who had been standing, sat down.

“Where to, Mike?”

From a pocket, he took a paper and, in taking it, took also another, which fell at her feet. The first, which was partially engraved, had on it particulars concerning him; also his photograph. He displayed it.

“This is a passport. With it, I had intended to go to France and join the Foreign Legion. But yesterday my father changed his mind about something, and since then I have changed mine.” He stooped and recovered the fallen paper, at which, as he did so, she looked.

“What is that? A Medical Record? Mike! You’re not going to be a physician, are you? A physician in the family is so reassuring. Just like a fire escape.”

He shook his head.

“That’s just a thing I happened on in Dix’s office. He wants it back. No, I’m going away to join a friend of mine.”

“Who? What is his name?”

For a second he hesitated.

“Victor Revell.”

The girl considered him.

“I never heard you speak of him before.”

Mike fumbled in his waistcoat.

“You never heard me speak of anything but you, Camille. You won’t any more. Now, before I go, will you do me a favor?”

“A dozen.”

Into her hand he put a silver coin, at which she stared and exclaimed:

“Why, it’s a five-franc piece! What in the world—”

Mike nodded at her.

“It’s what gamblers call a luck piece. I want you to keep it for me. Promise that you will.”

“I promise. But you must do something for me. You must write.”

He took her hand.

“I have every intention of doing so. May I kiss you goodbye?”

She nodded, but she closed her eyes. When she opened them, he was in the hall.

In the hall was the stair. He went on and up. At the top was darkness. It engulfed him.

In this life, Camille was never to see his face again—except once, long later, when she thought she did. Yet in that, as will appear, she was perhaps mistaken.

II

Camille got up and looked at the clock, which marked seven. Usually at that hour she dined, having dressed beforehand. But on this evening, after returning from a run with a chum, Kate Delafield, she had been waylaid by the cook, then by Glendenning, finally by Mike, and she had had no time to change.

She was none the less hungry and she went back into the dining room, which, situated in an extension, was in a measure separated from the rest of the house. There the lights were on, the table was set. On a sideboard was bread, fruit, a salad, a decanter of claret, a brace of cold partridges; also, an evening paper.

Camille rang and took up the paper, which told of the misery that is the garment of Europe and of the gayety that is the parure of New York. The moderate irony of it missed her. But then one gets satiated with horrors, and, telling herself she was glad that Mike had changed his mind about going abroad, she rang again.

Then, as no one came, she put the food on the table, sat down, and began to eat. The partridge was good, and though, ordinarily, she would have preferred something hot, she was too hungry to care. The salad, too, might have been worse—and better, for in the preparation of the dressing, there had been a noticeable absence of brains. But that, too, she let pass and, while eating it, wondered whether Mr. Vulper was coming down and, in that case, whether he would have more to tell her about Shri.

That creature interested her enormously. She did not in the least believe in him, but the things he did, or was credited with doing, delighted her. He could be in two places at once, and if you happened on him where he had no business to be—in, for instance, Mr. Vulper’s study at the head of the stairs—he would break like a bubble and vanish.

Gymnastics of that high order appealed to her as unsurpassed by anything she had ever read.

“But how can he be so wickedly lovely?” she had at dinner, only the day before, asked of Mr. Vulper, who had referred her to his “Sutras of Patanjali”—which, when she had first heard of them, she had thought must be something from the chemists, but which, she had since become skeptically aware, taught of union with the supersensible; taught of the supernormal powers which that union confers; taught, too, how the advanced pupil may exteriorize himself from the body, project himself through space, materialize partially or wholly, appear and disappear at will.

“But why should this duck of a darling want to play flying trapese with himself like that?” she had also asked, and had been told that among the apes and peacocks of the apricot temples at Benares, there are priests whose duty it is to guard the arcana of their immemorial lore.

“Such things,” the old man continued, “are not for everybody—at all events not for nobodies who talk about nothing—yet, while they can be safely divulged to scholars, it is just that that Shri is trying to prevent. Well, my dear, perhaps he may, perhaps he may,” Vulper, with philosophic fatalism, had added.

Camille, at the time, had decided that he was as mad as a hatter, as mad as two hatters, as mad as Lincoln and Bennett, but none the less the most adorable old dear in the world. And now, as she hacked at one of the partridges, she wondered whether he would be coming down with more tales of Shri’s high jinks.

Behind her something moved. She half turned and, catching a side view of Archibald, exclaimed at him:

“I rang and rang! This salad is—”

“Beg pardon, mem. Mr. Mike wanted a taxi, and just now I had to let Doctor Dix in. Would you wish some soup, mem? There’s a filet of sole and—”

“For Heaven’s sake! I can’t eat backward! Get me some coffee. Isn’t Mr. Vulper coming down?”

“I’ll see, mem.”

He turned and went, and the girl took up again the paper, in which she found a fashion article that, like the salad, lacked brains. Before she had finished, Archibald was again behind her.

“Well?” she asked, without looking up.

After a moment, getting no other answer than the inarticulate sound that some people make when eating, she turned and saw that the servant looked like a ghost with a stomach ache. Quite white, he was opening and closing his mouth. Calmly she surveyed him.

“What is the matter with you?”

Archibald swallowed.

“It’s Mr. Vulper, mem.”

“Well, what about him?”

He swallowed again.

“Oh, mem, I don’t rightly know. But Doctor Dix, he—”

Camille was on her feet so quickly that she overturned the chair. She ran through the drawing-room, out into the hall, and up the stairs to the study at the head of them. There, in a chair, one arm pendant, his head hanging over it, the old man lay. Bending over him was Dix. As Camille entered, the physician straightened, looked at her.

“Cardiac paralysis,” he announced.

Camille’s hands had gone to her throat. In her riding costume, she always looked like a handsome boy. Now she looked like a thoroughly frightened one. From her eyes two round tears leaped like beads. Ever since she could remember, the dead man had been good to her. Though no relative whatever, he had been father and mother to this girl who now, in all the world, had no one—except a trust company, which is without a soul.

A sense of desolation, immense, unescapable, swept over her. She had so taken him for granted! The fact that he was old had never troubled her. It was natural for him to be old. She could not remember that he had ever been anything else. And now he had gone. The memory of little negligences to him came and hurt her. But behind it, behind everything, was the consciousness, selfish, yet human, that she was alone.

Dix, who had moved from the chair to the table and who had in his hand a paper, was talking at her, though about what she did not know. But gradually she realized that what he was saying concerned a will. As if she cared! But he was showing it to her—a sheet of paper, torn in two, half covered with the dead man’s writing, across which was crawled, “Shri Shankira.”

Utterly unstrung, at sight of that, for a second she stared, then she screamed.

For that one second, before her had passed a vision of apes, of peacocks, of apricot temples, and of some priest of Siva, recovering there from a catalepsy, self-induced, during which his entity, exteriorized, had crossed the seas, gibbered at Vulper, and—

It was then that she screamed.

“He killed him?”

Dix, tossing the paper aside, turned sharply to her.

“What do you mean?”

But now, though still unstrung, the girl’s common sense was asserting itself.

“I thought you meant that Shri had done it.”

“I meant nothing of the kind,” Dix impatiently retorted. “This Shri business he wrote himself. Only an hour ago, I warned him, and for the twentieth time, that at his age chloral was fatal. It was that that did it. I can’t be sorry enough. Apart from which, he had intended to leave you everything. Now it will all go to Mike, and you’ll be put in the street. Where is Mike?”

“Mike? He’s gone.”

Dix, moving from the table, looked in at the open safe, looked closer, fumbled it with his eyes, plucked at his beard, and turned.

“There was a pile of money there and a package. They’ve disappeared.”

That disappearance he momentarily considered. Then he dismissed it.

“Bah! He may have thrown them out of the window. He was quite capable of it.”

But there were other things to be attended to, and, seeing that the girl, for the time being at least, was totally unstrung, he went back to the table and rang.

III

“Don’t say you won’t change your mind,” Glendenning, with his equine air, was protesting at Camille, whose being put into the street was, of course, entirely figurative.

After the funeral and the rush of reporters who, from the inexperienced girl, had pulled more than they had expected—the will unsigned and destroyed, the sudden demise, the missing manuscript, the missing money, the missing heir, out of all of which they made very good copy—after that, the public administrator had stepped in, and notices had appeared announcing that “the People of the State of New York, by the grace of God free and independent, sent greeting to Michael Vulper, whose residence could not, after diligent inquiry, be ascertained, and citing him” and so forth and so forth.

But the greeting of the free and independent people had been ignored; so also had the citation. On the verbiage of both, Mike had appeared to be obscurely, but disdainfully turning his back. Yet, everything being possible, it may have been that neither had reached him; precisely as it may also have been that he was otherwise engaged.

Meanwhile, around the corner, on Riverside Drive, Camille had taken an apartment, furnished it after a fashion of her own, which was partly New York and partly Peking, put herself and the servants into it, and later had gone with Kate Delafield to Aiken.

There various young men had said the same thing to her. But as, from long practice, they had one and all acquired the art of making any subject uninteresting, their conversation had not affected her heart, her dreams, her golf, her runs, or her return. It had been January when she had gone South. Now it was April.

“No,” Glendenning repeated. “Don’t say it. Changing the mind is cleanly and therefore hygienic. My departed uncle had a room that he used for no other purpose.”

Camille, seated in a hand-painted chair, looked out at the moon and at the river, then at the Chinese lamps, at the draped and grand piano, at the portières, on which silver dragons roamed, and finally at this superior young man, who was also seated.

Between her chair and his, there was a space, which mentally she surveyed. It amounted, she judged, to about thirty-six inches. But in those inches there were miles, thousands of them. If he had been talking from a kloof of inner Africa, he could not have been farther away.

None the less, he represented to her that curious thing which is called a link. He connected her with the past, with the old man whom she had loved, with his son, whom she had liked. And, moreover, he and she now had—at any rate, he claimed that they had—interests in common; interests, that is, in the final disposition of the decedent’s estate, concerning which he had long since retained a fat shyster named Tatum, to whom he negligently referred as his counsel.

“You don’t, perhaps, care for me yet—” he was saying.

“And that,” Camille wickedly cut in, “is such an advantage. I could have no disillusions.”

“On the other hand,” Glendenning, smoothing his white tie, continued, “you know that I do care for you.”

Camille laughed.

“You are so persuasive! Poor Mike wasn’t in it with you.”

“Why poor? He has only to show up to step into a fortune,” retorted Glendenning, who earnestly hoped that Mike would do nothing of the kind; for, if he omitted to, then, after the legal delays, that fortune he, as next of kin, would inherit.

Camille looked down at a floor pillow at her feet, kicked it aside, stood up, and made a pass with her hands.

“I can’t account for it, and the fact that I can’t torments me. It seems as if it were my fault. When he said he was going away, I should have made him say where. Instead of which, I asked him to write. He never has. Yet he must be somewhere.”

Glendenning nodded.

“In the fourth dimension.”

Camille turned on him.

“I’ll thank you not to jest on a subject that to Mr. Vulper was an article of faith!”

With entire ease, Glendenning tacked.

“Excuse me. I meant in the grave, for there he is, unless”—“he is in prison,” he was about to add, but instead he said—“unless he went blind.” Again Camille turned on him.

“I must be blind, too. I don’t see what you are driving at.”

“Then I’ll tell you. The death of the author of a book of commentaries on the sutras of—of some jellyfish of a Hindu spook; the death of an occultist who had devoted twenty years of his life to a manuscript which departed when he did; the death of a recluse who for no obvious reason inherited half of your father’s estate—the death of an individual so unusual does not take place without comment. For forty-eight hours afterward, the papers dripped with his name, with the missing money, the missing manuscript, the missing heir. Mike must have read of it, unless, as I say, he went blind. Even so, unless in going blind he went deaf, there must have been others to tell him. But all that is preposterous. There is a fortune awaiting him. Why doesn’t he come and claim it?”

Camille yawned and sat down.

“I wish you would tell me.”

Glendenning pulled at his cuff.

“Perhaps I can. But you know that, in spite of Mike’s very unfortunate appearance, you had rather a tender feeling for him.”

Impatiently the girl took it up.

“What of it? And anyway I had no more intention of marrying him than I have of marrying you.”

Glendenning gulped, swallowed, and corrected it.

“No more immediate intention, you mean. But now will that tender heart of yours prevent you from considering certain facts?”

“Dear me,” thought Camille, “I wish he would go!”

But she said:

“Well, what are they?”

Glendenning raised a hand, the fingers extended.

“I’ll show you. On the night my uncle died, Mike said goodbye to you, went upstairs, sent Archibald for a taxi, and left the house. That is a fact, is it not?”

Camille nodded.

“Previously Dix had been with my uncle, who then was in his usual health. Dix was called away. Mike had hardly gone when Dix returned and found my uncle dead. There you have another fact. And here is one more—in the will that my uncle intended to execute, Mike was cut off.”

“And so were you.”

“No matter about that. To go back to Dix. My uncle sent for him to witness this will, and while they were discussing it, he showed him his manuscript and a pot of money.”

“But—”

“Then Dix was called away. When he returned, my uncle was dead and the money and the manuscript had vanished. You admit that, don’t you?”

“Yes, the manuscript was certainly missing, and Dix said some money was, also. But, like Mike, they may turn up yet.”

“Together?”

“How do you mean?”

“The three of them—the money, the manuscript, and Mike. There’s no other way out of it. They all departed at the same moment. If they did not, long since Mike would have returned. Now he can’t return. He’s afraid to.”

Impatiently Camille shrugged a shoulder.

“I don’t know whether to be angry or amused.”

“At what?”

“Why, you’re insinuating that he killed his father.”

“No, Camille, nothing of the kind. I’m merely submitting certain facts and asking you and myself what they amount to.”

“And I’ll tell you—rubbish!”

“Well, let’s look at it this way. On the night my uncle died, I was with you in the drawing-room. Mike appeared. Where had he come from?”

“I’m sure I don’t know.”

“Nor I. But I can imagine. I can imagine that he had a scene with his father, that he tried to force him to make the will in his favor, and, failing, grabbed the money and the manuscript, stuffed them into his grip, and came down to you, not realizing then what had happened, not realizing that he was a parricide, that in the struggle he had throttled his father or otherwise done him to death. The realization of that came later. But, at the time, don’t you remember how evil and sinister he looked?”

“I remember nothing of the sort. But if you can imagine all that, why can’t you imagine that since he left here, he has lost his memory? People often do, don’t they, and turn up as milkmaids or shoemakers somewhere else? Or if that is too much for you, why can’t you imagine that it was Shri who did it, provided, that is, that anything was done at all. Personally I prefer to think so.”

“It’s very morbid of you, then.”

“I suppose you’ll say that stupidity is preferable. Mike never killed his father; he never took the money; and what would he do with the manuscript? But if you can cook up a cock-and-bull story of that order, you’d far better try your hand on Shri. Why, your uncle kept me in fits of laughter over him. He was as real to him as I was myself.”

“My uncle was a fit subject for Bedlam. He—”

“See here, Arthur,” Camille interrupted, “I won’t have you speak of him in that manner. And in my presence I’ll thank you never again to speak as you have of Mike. Your uncle was an angel to me, and as for Mike, I’d like to know when these amiable suspicions concerning him occurred to you?”

“From the start. The reporters all had them and practically said as much.”

“Then hereafter you—”

Camille paused and turned. Through parting portières, Archibald, a tray in his hand, was emerging. On the tray was a card and a letter, which he brought her.

Camille, glancing at the writing on the envelope, cried:

“Why, it’s from Mike!”

In the old melodramas, when the villain was foiled, he showed it; it was part of the business. Glendenning showed no emotion whatever, but figuratively his heart sank. His uncle’s money had been so neighborly. Now, like Shri—and as suddenly—it had gone.

“What does the dear boy say?” he at last got out.

Camille, who meanwhile had read the letter, handed it to him and looked at Archibald.

“Is any one waiting?”

“A gentleman, mem.”

“Show him in.”

Hotel St. Francis, San Francisco,
10th November.

Dear Camille: Some day or other, this will be brought to you by my friend, Victor Revell. Smile on him for my sake and for his own. He is worth it.

God bless you. Mike.

At a glance, Glendenning took it in and, for further examination, he pocketed it.

Camille did not notice. She was greeting a man whom from that instant Glendenning hated, hated instinctively, hated intensely, hated without knowing why; which is the surest reason any one can have for hating anybody.

“Mr. Revell?” Camille, a hand outstretched, was saying.

She had got up. Glendenning, too, had risen.

Revell took the hand, released it, nodded at Glendenning, whom Camille then introduced, smiled into her eyes, and answered her.

“Yes, and I fervently hope that my name may not be one of ill omen.”

“He is too good looking,” thought Camille, taken at once with his appearance, which was radiant, virile, and noble.

Seating herself and indicating a chair, she asked:

“And are you just here from San Francisco?”

“Practically,” Revell, seating himself also, replied. “It was a little while, though, before I could get your address. Doctor Dix, to whom Mike also gave me a line, told it to me. Mike could not have known where you were.”

“Yes?” Glendenning, who had remained standing, got in. “How is the dear boy?”

Revell looked up at him and from him to Camille.

“I am sorry to bring you bad news.” He paused, half raised a hand, and added: “It was pneumonia.”

At that, Glendenning sat down, flopped, rather. If he had been alone, he would have danced and shouted. As it was, he closed his eyes. It was all too blissful. The estate was his.

With a look in which there was pain, amazement, and uncertainty,Camille exclaimed:

“He is dead?”

Sympathetically Revell considered the girl.

“That depends on how you look at it. From what he told me of his father’s views, it may be that there is no such thing as death. It may that death is but a garage at which you wait a while until, in exchange for your demolished motor, destiny supplies you with a fresh one.”

“What an ass!” thought Glendenning.

But he said:

“Were you with poor Mike when—er—”

“Yes, I and a physician who certified accordingly. Towers his name is. I gave his address to Doctor Dix and also some papers that Mike wanted to go to him.”

Glendenning twisted. Into the core of his being the reply cut like a knife. Before him the inhuman possibility surged that Mike had made a will. He blurted it.

“Papers? What were they?”

With entire civility, Revell answered:

“Papers concerning Doctor Dix, I suppose.”

He turned again to Camille, who in the interval had gone to the window and was looking from it, but not at the moon nor yet at the river. She could not see them; her eyes were too blurred. Revell got up and joined her.

Glendenning, considering them both, also got up, passed through the portières, closed the door, and went to the vestibule, where presently he was talking to Dix over the wire.

“This is Glendenning. I’m speaking from Miss Marcy’s apartment. A Mr. Revell who is here has just told us about poor Mike. Camille and I are very much cut up over it. Now this Mr. Revell says he left some papers with you. In Camille’s behalf, will you tell me whether they concern her?”

Clearly the answer came:

“Not in the least.”

“Well, you can appreciate that she is deeply interested. If there is no objection, will you tell me what they are?”

“No objection at all. One is a death certificate; the other a will of which I am appointed executor.”

Glendenning’s throat went dry and he coughed.

“What is its tenor?”

“Everything to Revell.”

“What?”

“Everything Mike possessed he left absolutely to Victor Revell.”

Ragingly Glendenning clutched at the instrument.

“I’ll contest it!” he thought.

But he said:

“May I run in and look at it?”

For a second the answer delayed. Then it came:

“Yes, but it won’t do you a bit of good.”

“I’ll come, all the same,” said Glendenning, who swore, grabbed at his hat, and started.

IV

From mingling faces; from forms and features that appeared, disappeared, reappeared; from these and from tumults of farewells, Camille awoke.

Through the open window, she could see the sky, an unprecised gray. that hesitantly would become blue, bluer, still bluer. As yet it was gray. It must be very early, she thought. Then at once she remembered. Mike was dead.

The fact stood out and hurt her. Over it, the night before, she had cried a little. Now again her eyes were wet.

During his mysterious absence, she had missed him, though not poignantly nor yet impatiently, for she had felt that he must return. Now he never could, and when he had been with her, she had treated him like a dog that is overattentive and therefore in the way. She wished that she had been less hard with him. His appearance had been distressing, but custom had so familiarized her with it that she had accepted it, as one may get to accept a rhinoceros in the back yard, provided the brute is there long enough.

She dried her eyes and, in a sort of retrograde vision, reviewed the incidents of the night before—Glendenning’s effort to show that if Mike were not a criminal, he would have returned; then the news of his death, the eclipse of Glendenning, and the brief afterwhile, during which she had learned from Revell what little there was to know.

That little, now that she reviewed it, seemed, like the sky, unprecised. Like the sky, there were voids in it, great stretches of nothing over which silence was spread. But then, in ten minutes, who can be exhaustive? And had there been as many as ten? Five, perhaps; six at most. Yet, during them, she had realized that, in addition to the appearance of this man, who looked as if he had stepped from a canvas signed “Murillo”—some canvas that pictured a young grandee—she realized that, in addition to this, which in itself is surely a lot, she liked the man himself. With the stranger, she had felt at home. This man, whom she had never seen before, had made her want to see him again. It was very extraordinary.

Love at first sight always is. Of the presence of that psychosis she was unaware. If she had been and had been cross-questioned regarding it, she certainly would not have blushed herself to death, but quite as certainly she would have lied. She had no Victorian ideals, but she knew what is nice and what is not and that, perhaps, is better.

Meanwhile, the sky had deepened. Through the window came the radiance of the April day. Later, when, in breeches and boots, she had breakfasted and was about to go for a run, Glendenning was announced.

Camille made a face. But, accepting the situation, she went into the drawing-room where he stood, and where, for a superior young man, he looked very ugly.

“See here, Camille,” he at once threw at her. “Did that chap tell you how he did for Mike?”

Camille flicked with her crop at her boots.

“What chap?”

“Don’t beat about the bush. You know perfectly well that I mean Revell.”

“Oh,” said Camille slowly. “Mr. Revell, is it? Well, no, he didn’t say anything at all about himself—which is more than I can say for some people.”

Glendenning caught it and tossed it back.

“Some people, at least, are honest.”

Camille twirled her crop.

“Last night Mike was an outlaw. Now I suppose Mr. Revell is a cutthroat. Why, what is the matter with you, Arthur?”

Glendenning snorted.

“Matter? Matter enough! The matter is that we have got to fight him. He told you, didn’t he?”

“About fighting him? Certainly not, and if he had, I should have understood as little as I understand you.”

“What I mean is, didn’t he tell you about Mike’s will?”

“Not a word. Why should he?”

“Because Mike has left him everything. Everything, do you hear that? He has left him property that he had no right to leave him, property that my uncle intended for you. But he was blackmailed into doing it. That is the size of it.”

In the little tempest of words, Camille sat down. It was certainly very queer, she thought, and she said so.

“Queer?” Glendenning chokingly repeated. “Queer is not the word for it. It’s undue influence—felony, for all we know, State’s prison—”

Camille laughed. She could not help it.

“Why not the chair? But nobody ever intended to leave the money to you. What are you so hot about?”

“What?” In righteous indignation, Glendenning lifted his arms. “You ask me that? Can’t you see that it is on your account? Do you suppose I shall stand by and see you bunkoed? Not a bit of it! I’ll have the will set aside!”

“Yes?” said the girl with a treacherously innocent air. “And what whould happen then?”

“We would share and share alike. I’d give you half.”

Camille cocked an eye.

“Give me?”

“Well, you see, as next of kin, it would have to pass through my hands.”

Then, at sight of the mocking eye, he extracted and flourished a handkerchief.

“But,” he resumed, “it would all be in the family. When we are married—”

“When we are!” Camille interrupted. “I have no intention of marrying you, not the faintest. And do stop waving that flag at me! I’m not a submarine. And how do you make out that Mike was blackmailed, as you call it?”

“Well, isn’t it obvious? Why, a schoolboy could reconstruct the whole thing! There was poor Mike, a stranger in a strange land. He was probably ill, in any event lonely, and certainly conscience-stricken. Then this Revell happened along, pretended to be hail-fellow-well-met, wormed himself into Mike’s confidence, plied him with drink, got him in his cups, wheedled out of him what happened the night his father died, and then threatened to expose him unless he left him everything. It’s as clear as day. I’ve seen the will. Dix showed it to me. It was executed in November in San Francisco and—”

“But Mike could have made another, couldn’t he?”

“Certainly he could, and how do we know that he did not? Even otherwise, what was Revell to him? What was he, anyway, in comparison to you or to me?”

“Oh, come now! You know perfectly well that Mike hated you and that you hated him.”

Glendenning waved it away.

“I wouldn’t go as far as that. Mike was after you and so was I. There was just the spirit of decent rivalry between us. But that’s neither here nor there. The point is that we’ve got to have the will set aside. We’ve got to contest it. We—”

“For Heaven’s sake! Do stop saying ‘oui’ all the time! Any one would think you were a Frenchman.”

“I don’t understand,” said Glendenning, who had got the jest and did not like it.

Camille sprang up.

“Nor I. If it’s not French that you’re talking, it’s lunacy. I don’t believe a word of what you told me of Mike or a thing of what you say of Mr. Revell. Not one! What’s more, I won’t listen to another. You can see me down if you like. I’m off for a run.”

Glendenning could only comply. He saw her down; saw her hop on her horse; saw her start and trot away.

Immediately he decided on a run of his own, and presently, in the neighborly subway, he was being whirled down to the offices of his counsel, Tatum.

Mr. Tatum was a large, fierce man who looked like a chucker-out, but whose voice—which was that of a prima donna—contrasted almost tragically with the aggressiveness of his appearance.

“And so,” he purred, when Glendenning had summarized the matter, “you want to fight. That is the proper spirit. But we have no evidence. We have only suppositions. What your cousin may have done or omitted to do on the night of which you tell me is now immaterial. But that his beneficiary unduly influenced him we will have to show. Meanwhile, through my San Francisco correspondents, I can make an inquiry or two. Should these lead to anything, it may be worth while to proceed, if only with a view to a possible compromise, unless in the interim the will should prove voidable per se. As soon as it is entered, I will consider that point. But otherwise—”

Tatum paused, looked at the walls wainscoted with yellow-backed books, looked beyond them at an idea that beckoned, nodded at it, and looked again at Glendenning.

“Have you anything in your cousin’s handwriting?”

“Yes, there’s that letter from him that Revell brought last night to Miss Marcy.”

“Have you anything else?”

“Well, I wrote him once asking him to advance me some money, and he answered very brutally that he would not.”

“Very good. Send both to me. It will be interesting to compare them—to compare them, also, with the signature on the will. That, too, may lead to something. But otherwise we shall need evidence.”

“And we’ll get it,” Glendenning assured him.

And they did. But the evidence they landed was quite different from what they had expected. It belonged to quite another kettle of fish.

V

Camille rode up the river and raced back. The day before, she had done the same. The day before, the run had brought her the animal joy of living. But on this morning, the wind, the light, the breath of spring, the smell of lilacs, the fiery little cob, the eager glitter of the sky—these things flushed her, reddened her lips, brightened her eyes, poured claret into the cream of her skin, powdered her face with dust, wilted her collar, made her hot and dirty, but not happy. The death of Mike oppressed her, and on that oppression had been superimposed Glendenning’s utter obnoxiousness. The manner in which he had spoken of Revell had angered her, and in spite of the run, the memory of it rankled. None the less, as she told herself, it was queer about the will.

At the curb, a groom bobbed at her. She hopped off, patted the cob’s wet nose, looked into his great and empty eyes, fed sugar into his dripping and ready mouth, flew in, flew up, tubbed, changed, and wished that she were a man and could hit out and swear.

But now Margaret, a maid, pale and plain, looked in with an announcement and a query. Luncheon was served, and would she see Mr. Revell?

Would she? Well, yes, since he was there, she supposed so, and she looked in the glass, dabbed her face with cologne, patted her hair, patted her frock, wondered what he wanted, and went on and into the drawing-room.

Revell was seated. As she entered, he got up and she thought him even better looking than he had appeared on the previous evening. But at the moment, she got, too, another impression, and she out with it.

“I’ve seen you before. Where?”

Revell, with a movement of the hand, just sketched a gesture.

“In the street, perhaps. In the theater. I used to live here.”

Camille shook her docked hair.

“Yes, I know. I’ve heard Mike speak of you. But could it have been in Europe?”

“Perhaps. But isn’t it rather unimportant?”

“I don’t know. Mike’s father used to say that nothing is unimportant—or was it that everything is? There! I’ve got it. I remember now. In the Louvre! Yes, the portrait of—I’ve forgotten whom. But I remember the picture distinctly—a man dressed for a fancy ball. You’re not dressed that way, but you look just like him. Now will you have luncheon with me? In fact, you’ll have to. I hear you are head of the house, such as it is, and I’m prepared to treat you with the greatest respect.”

“But, you see, I don’t want to be treated with respect, and moreover—”

“And moreover luncheon is served. Will you come?”

She led the way. In the adjoining room, stood Archibald, at whom she motioned.

“A chair for Mr. Revell. Claret for Mr. Revell. The best there is for Mr. Revell, and all there is of it.”

“Yes, mem. Yes, mem,” Archibald got in, pottering about, pottering away.

“And moreover,” the young man resumed, when the old man had gone, “I am not the head of the house. I’m not even the foot of it. I’m not in it at all. But if, technically and for the moment, I seem to have a shadow of a claim—”

“Let me give you some of this,” Camille interrupted.

“Thank you. If I have anything of the kind,” Revell continued, “that’s just the reason why I am here. I—”

“And let me give you some of this, also,” Camille again interrupted.

“Thank you. If I have any sort of a claim, I’m here to resign it.”

“Eh?” Camille’s brilliant eyes were on him.

“Only, in coming, I did not expect—”

“That I would know about Mike’s will already.”

“Precisely.”

Camille nodded.

“This morning Mike’s cousin, Mr. Glendenning, told me.”

“Ah!” Revell, who had been looking at Camille, looked down at his plate, on which was sweetbread and sorrel. At once he looked up. “I take it that he objects. That is only natural. If Mike had left no will, the money would have gone to him. Rather than that, Mike preferred to leave it to me and, rather than accept it, I resign it to you.”

If any one can appear both pleased and indignant, that is the way Camille looked.

“Why, I never heard of such a thing! I couldn’t let you!”

Revell smiled at her.

“I knew that would be the first thing you would say, but—”

“I shall say it first, last, and all the time. If you don’t like claret, there is some Chablis. Now, I don’t want to hear another word about it.”

“To return, then, to our Chablis Moutonne,” Revell, intent on holding his own, resumed. “Apart from Mike’s will, I have no claim or title to the property, which is triply yours. It is yours because it originally belonged to your father; it is yours because Mr. Vulper intended to leave it to you; it is yours because such was Mike’s wish.”

“But—”

“Yes, I appreciate. You will ask why, in that case, is not the will in your favor? I don’t know that I can properly explain it.”

“I should think not.”

“I mean that I can’t explain it without the risk of offending you.”

“Oh, I am not the kaiser.”

“Well, then, if I did not offend you, I might offend others.”

“And I am not a repeater, either.”

“Here it is, then. Mike felt that if he left the money to you, Glendenning might contest it.”

“But can’t he anyway?”

“Certainly he can. Moreover, he probably will. But, apart from that, Mike felt that even if his cousin did not contest a will made in your favor, he would so badger you about it that you might end by giving the money to him.”

“How well Mike knew me!”

“Yes, and probably much better than he knew this cousin of his, in whom, no doubt, he was greatly mistaken.”

“Not a bit of it,” thought Camille.

But she said:

“You are not eating anything.”

Revell took a mouthful of sorrel and added:

“You can see, then, how it is. Pending the settlement of the estate, the court practically holds it in trust for you. But once the funds are turned over to me, I shall pay them in for you at your bankers.”

Camille straightened.

“I’ll tell them not to take it.”

“The bankers who won’t take money do not exist.”

Camille frowned.

“I’ll refuse to touch it.”

“Then it will accumulate interest for you until you change your mind.”

“But you’re bullying me! Suppose I never change my mind?”

“Then you’re not a woman. But assuming that you are as consistent as all that, the property will go to your heirs.”

Camille bridled.

“I haven’t any—I never shall have any.”

“Then it will go to the State.”

Camille nodded.

“There, you see! You had far better keep it yourself.”

At that Revell laughed, and the laugh and the look that accompanied it annoyed the girl, who exclaimed:

“Are you very rich?”

Then he, too, nodded.

“Enormously.”

“What?” she exclaimed again.

“I am one of the richest men in the world,” Revell calmly replied and as calmly enumerated the rent rolls of his vast estate. “I have health, strength, youth, and a total absence of needs.”

“And extraordinary good looks,” thought Camille.

But she said:

“Mr. Rockefeller might envy you.”

Revell bowed.

“Whereas I am immodest enough not to envy any one.”

“He’s a dear,” thought Camille.

But she said:

“I don’t wonder you want to throw money out of the window. It must be great fun. But it’s a game that two can play at. If you pay money in at my bank, I will pay it back at yours.”

“You’ll have a hard time finding it, Miss Marcy.”

“Why? Where is it?”

“Everywhere and nowhere.”

“That sounds spacious. What is its name?”

“The Bank of Hope.”

“Now isn’t he a duck?” thought Camille.

But she said:

“I see. You have ambitions.”

“Only one, but that is immense.”

Camille stood up.

“Is it a secret?”

Revell also stood up.

“Can you keep one?”

“Yes, yes.”

“So can I.”

“Why, isn’t he mean?” thought Camille.

But she said:

“You haven’t eaten a thing.”

As she spoke, she passed into the drawing-room. Revell followed and took her hand.

“I’ve never had a better luncheon.” Releasing her hand, he asked: “May I come again?”

Promptly Camille dropped a curtsy.

“Señor Don Hidalgo, this house is yours.”

When, from the hall without, she had heard the door close, she went to the window, saw him as he reached the street, watched him as he moved away.

When he had rounded the corner, she sat at the piano, attacked a score of Borodine, abandoned him for Granados, and, in allusion no doubt to the latter, stayed her hands and, said aloud:

“I never dreamed that any one could be so nice.”

As she spoke, she was conscious of some one entering the room and, turning, she saw Glendenning. The intrusion annoyed her, but of that she gave no sign.

Glendenning was less circumspect. Angrily he considered her.

“So you’ve been having that man to luncheon, have you?”

She stood up.

“Really, Arthur, when you address me, I’ll thank you to adopt another tone.”

“But, my dear Camille, when Archibald told me, I could hardly believe my ears. This morning I showed the feller up to you for the confidence man that he is, and my back is hardly turned before you are wining and dining him.”

“It seems to me that it is you who are doing the whining. And, anyway, you are entirely mistaken. Mr. Revell is a very rich man.”

“What?”

“And you can attack Mike’s will all you like. But it will be me, not Mr. Revell, whom you are attacking.”

Glendenning stood on one foot, then on the other.

“How? Why? What?”

“Yes. Mr. Revell proposes to turn the money over to me.”

At that, Glendenning threw up his arms and dropped into a chair.

Camille nodded at him.

“Any one would think I had shot you. But don’t die just yet. I need not say that I can’t accept it.”

“But—”

“There you are.”

In the surprise of it, Glendenning felt as if a blanket had been thrown over him; not a wet blanket or even an ordinary one, but the Oriental variety, silken, soft, smothersome. He struggled free.

“Yes, you’re right. I am there. It’s a plant. I’ll wager that he’s not a rich man at all. Though, to be sure, he looks like a lead in a movie. But no one would suppose that he could pull it over you like that. Can’t you see that, in offering to give you the estate, his only object is to hoodwink us into standing aside, while he laughs and pockets it? No, none of that! I’ll have a deed drawn conveying all his interest under Mike’s will to you. Then you ask him to sign it. Then you’ll see.”

Camille shrugged a shoulder.

“Perhaps you didn’t hear me. I told him, as I told you, that I could not and would not accept it.”

“And you’ll never get the chance—unless it comes to you through me. What are you laughing at?”

“At you. What else? Mr. Revell said he was sure Mike must have misjudged you.”

Like a beast of prey, the exasperated Glendenning snarled:

“Yes, confound him! He’s one of the devils who speak well of everybody. The Judas!”

Camille bubbled.

“That, I suppose, is a jeu d’esprit. I might like some more, but I haven’t the time.”

Raveningly Glendenning jumped up.

“And that, I suppose, is a hint. Very good, I’ll go—but I will return.”

“Not as you did just now,” thought Camille, who, when he had gone, rang for the servant.

“Archibald,” she told him, “I shall be sorry to lose you. But I don’t wish to have Mr. Glendenning or any one else marching in here before you inquire whether or not I am at home. And I don’t wish Mr. Glendenning or any one else to be told who has or has not been here.”

“Beg pardon, mem, but Mr. Glendenning, he asked—”

“That will do, Archibald. You heard what I said.”

Camille went back to the piano. There, like a vision in a photo play, mentally, before her, stood Revell.

VI

Tatum, a fortnight later, looked up at Glendenning and in his mayonnaise voice inquired:

“Do you play golf?”

Glendenning, who had just entered the office, sat down.

“No, I loathe the stupid game.”

Tatum caressed his aggressive jaw.

“It’s fortunate that stupidity does not hurt. If it did, yelling would be continuous and New York is noisy enough already.”

Glendenning twisted.

“I thought you wanted to see me.”

“Yes,” Tatum replied, “and it’s just for that reason that I asked if you play golf. We seem to have run into a bunker.”

As the ogre purred, he took up a letter, glanced at it, put it down, and purred anew.

“My San Francisco correspondents write that your cousin registered at the Hotel St. Francis the evening of the ninth November, which is just five days after he left his father’s house. My correspondents say that the next morning he asked for a reputable attorney and was directed to the firm that attend to the hotel’s law business. According to my correspondents, he applied to this firm to have his will drawn, stating that he was in a hurry and wanted it at once. The will was then drawn for him; after which, he copied it out in his own hand, had his signature witnessed, settled with the firm, returned to the St. Francis, paid his bill, took his grip, and—goodbye.”

Tatum looked again at the letter, refreshed his memory with it, and lit a cigar.

“Months later, or, to be exact, on the twenty-eighth of March, at four o’clock in the morning, he turned up at the Morrow House, where, on the following day, he died.”

Tatum wreathed himself in smoke and added:

“And that is the bunker that we are up to.”

Glendenning swore.

“Your correspondents say nothing else?”

“Plenty,” Tatum trilled. “They enter into all manner of irrelevant details. It appears that when Mike turned up at the Morrow House, he was accompanied by a man who paid his lodging in advance, saw him up to the room assigned, came down, and went away, but not until he had summoned a physician for your cousin, who badly needed one. The physician, Doctor Towers, diagnosed the case as pneumonia, to which alcoholism, complicated with exposure, had been contributory. Your cousin then was dying. What is it, Freddie?”

A clerk entered. Apparently young, he was quite bald.

“It’s Jerolomon about the St. Chrysostom Church matter—”

Tatum puffed and murmured:

“Ask him to come again. Say that I am closeted with the cardinal now.”

When the clerk had gone, Tatum, in his prima-donna voice, asked:

“Where was I? Oh, yes! At noon, a man appeared who presumably was the man of the night before. In any event, he represented himself as a friend of your cousin’s, agreed to pay, and did pay, all the expenses, and later had the body removed to the morgue of a crematorium, where it was afterward incinerated. Meanwhile, your cousin’s identity had been properly established. Among his effects, was a passport on which was his photograph, or, at all events, a photograph; and that, together with his few other effects, this friend of his removed.”

Tatum again took up the letter, put it down once more, glared, and in his opera voice resumed:

“If I were younger, I would run out there. I hear that Frisco is a delightful place. But I hear also that the food en route is the reverse. Besides, there is the coming back. No, I couldn’t do it. But you might.”

For a moment, Glendenning considered it.

“I would if I thought I could nail that scoundrel.”

“Well,” Tatum affectionately replied, “if you conclude to, you’d best not put up at the Morrow House. It is not, I hear, a place for a gentleman. And that reminds me. What could have induced your cousin to go there? Why did he not go back to the St. Francis? Of course there is no law in the matter. He was free to do as he liked—free to drink, free also to expose himself. When it rains in San Francisco, I hear that it is something to boast about. Your cousin appears to have been subjected to it. He appears, also, to have grown a beard. There is no law against that, either. But perhaps that is the reason why he did not return to the St. Francis. Perhaps he feared that he would not be recognized. Doctor Towers told my correspondents that he looked like a tramp. For the heir to a fortune, that is interesting, but not exceptional. In England, before the war, I saw a man who looked like a poacher and who turned out to be a duke.”

“What do your people say about this Doctor Towers?” Glendenning, biting a finger, moodily got in.

“Old established family practitioner with a thoroughly good reputation. Which also reminds me. This friend of your cousin’s in his last moments has no reputation at all. He has not even a doubtful past, though it’s probably better to have a doubtful past than a past about which there is no doubt whatever. But this deathbed friend has nothing of the kind. Who is he?”

“Revell,” Glendenning sullenly replied.

“Precisely. And who is Revell? In San Francisco no one ever heard of him. Your cousin—yes. Your cousin stopped at hotels; he wrote letters; he visited lawyers. But of Revell there is not a trace, not one. Who is this man who seems to have sprung from nowhere and who owns the earth?”

“My cousin’s murderer.”

Airily Tatum waved it away.

“No, not that. The man in the Morrow House died of a perfectly defined disease, of which the predisposing causes were sufficiently indicated. The man in the Morrow House died a natural death. But your cousin did not. Or, at least, so far as we are yet aware. So far as we are yet aware, your cousin may enjoy the same good health that you do.”

Glendenning started.

“Then who was the man in the Morrow House?”

“It is to find out that that I spoke of going there. But, apart from the mysteries of the dining car, the crematorium tells no tales.”

“Then we’re dished.”

“No, not that, either. On the face of it, a Mike Vulper died at the Morrow House. But before the will is probated, it has got to be shown to my satisfaction that that Mike Vulper was your Mike Vulper. And even should that be proven, it must be proven, also, that it was your Mike Vulper, who, in the offices of the San Francisco attorneys, executed this will.”

Glendenning groped, but he could not get it.

“You think—”

Tatum sat back.

“I don’t know what to think. When you first spoke of Revell, you said that he looked like a mummer. He may be one. In which case, he could certainly make himself up and pass for your cousin to people who would have no suspicions about him and who might at most be expected to vaguely describe him long after.”

“That’s it. That’s it.”

Tatum gestured and scowled.

“It may be. For, as you may remember, when the will was drawn, he copied it. Why did he? Such a proceeding was absolutely unnecessary and becomes all the more curious when you consider that he was in a hurry. Why, then, did he? The answer is obvious. He did it for no other reason than because he felt that his identity might be questioned and, possessing, in addition to other talents, the ability to imitate another’s writing, he wrote it in Mike’s hand, on which he had previously practiced.”

Savorously Glendenning gulped.

“Bravo! We’ve got him! The will is a forgery.”

“Yes,” Tatum purred at him, “that is the way I look at it. But even if we can prove that, as perhaps we may, then, before we can claim the property, we’ve got to prove also that your cousin is dead.”

“If he’s not dead, where is he?”

“Ask Revell.”

“By the Lord Harry, I will!”

“He knows, but he won’t tell you. He knows why the man in the offices of the San Francisco attorneys was in a hurry. He won’t tell that, either. He knows and he won’t tell why the body of the man in the Morrow House was burned. But I can tell. It was to cover his tracks.”

Glendenning’s face darkened.

“Then he’s got us again.”

Tatum laughed fatly.

“I don’t think so. If, as is possible—and probable—we can show that the will is a forgery, we can accept without question the evidence of your cousin’s death. In other words, Mike Vulper died at the Morrow House; he died intestate; and the estate is yours.”

“Tatum, that’s great!”

“Yes, and my bill is going to be greater,” thought the lawyer.

But he said:

“When do you think you will see this impostor?”

Glendenning sprang to his feet.

“Tonight, and—confound him!—I know where.”

Tatum looked up at him.

“Tonight I am going to ‘The Ring Around the Rosy’ show. Afterward, suppose you meet me at the Tap House. Meanwhile, don’t fail to ask Revell where your cousin is. He won’t tell you, but—”

“Oh, I’ll jolt him all right,” answered Glendenning, who was leaving the room.

VII

That evening, Camille dined alone, or as much alone as a young woman can be who is served by a servant and whose mind is thoroughly occupied. Of Archibald, she was subconsciously aware that, always old, latterly he had seemed to be older. But Revell inhabited her thoughts. Since that high noon when he had lunched with her on a mouthful of sorrel, she had seen him every day. He had sat with her, walked with her, ridden with her, and, where a girl like Camille is concerned, few young men can do that without saying the same thing over and over again.

Revell had omitted even mentioning it. But there are always ways of telling, and Camille knew the state of his mind as well as she knew her own. She knew that she was head over heels in love with this man of whom she knew nothing. Yet, although she lacked the experience to recognize it, that very fact increased his attractiveness. In the history of love, the most sudden, surprising, and devastating passions have been inspired by people who had mystery for sole asset.

Revell had many another. He was very good looking and equally unassuming. In addition, he was distinctly well bred. He never talked about himself. When questioned, he switched. In spite of which, Camille felt at home with him; felt, as girls who have read Mrs. Besant sometimes do feel, that in anterior, forgotten, and enigmatic lives, they had met and loved before. For precisely as she had become conscious of her own psychosis, she was conscious of his. She knew that he loved her. He had made her feel that he meant the very thing he did not say. For the subtlety of that—and subtle it certainly was—she loved him all the more. But as she would have loved him anyway, it perhaps did not matter.

It mattered, and monumentally, to Glendenning, who, on several occasions, had succeeded in making himself even more obnoxious than usual. There was the defunct Mrs. Grundy, whom he evoked and flung at her. Living as she was, and, as he put it, without the ghost of a chaperon, such goings-on did not do. Besides, what did she know of Revell? Was she even sure that his name was Revell? Et cetera and so forth and so on.

To all of which Camille had turned an angry ear and on each occasion had turned him out. None the less, when there is mud enough, some of it will stick. It affected the girl. It made her realize that, on the subject of the one and only, she was considerably in the dark.

At the moment, she was not only in the dark; she was really alone. Archibald had vanished. A moment more and there he was again and would she see Mr. Revell?

Camille moistened her lips, went into the adjoining room, gave him her hand, and said:

“I was just thinking about you. Sit down and tell me all about yourself. It’s perfectly ridiculous. I don’t yet know what your middle name is.”

Revell, who was looking very fit, smiled as he answered:

“That must be because I haven’t any.”

But Camille was not to be denied. “Your middle name can stand for you, then. We’ve talked about me, or, rather, you have, and that topic is threadbare. We’ve talked gastronomy, and I’ve found that you know very little about it. We’ve talked art, and you’ve found that I know less. We’ve talked horses, war, submarines, aëroplanes, the czar, the kaiser, and the weather. Barring horses, I never want to talk of any of them again. I want to talk business. Who are you?”

Revell’s smile deepened.

“Didn’t somebody put the same question to Plato, and didn’t he answer: ‘I wish I knew?’ ”

“Oh, if you’re going to bring out your seventeen-inch guns! And, anyway, Plato probably found out. If you have not, I’ll help you. Your name is Victor Revell. You are nice, quiet, and gentlemanly. You were Mike’s friend, and now you are mine. I like you very much, But I know nothing of you.”

“You might not like me so well if you did.”

“Why do you say that?”

“Well, as somebody said, the soul of another is a dark place.”

Camille shook her head at him.

“I’m sure yours isn’t. I feel as if I had always known you. And yet, at the same time, I feel that I don’t know you at all.”

Revell looked down, then up.

“No one knows another. We seldom know ourselves. How can we? Life is a procession of phenomena, of which one departs as another appears and of which each, created by what has gone before, creates that which follows, the result being that, though from cradle to grave, a man is called the same, never, either mentally or physically, is he. The man of this instant perishes. He is replaced by a new one during the next.”

“Do you think that is a pretty way to talk to a girl?” Camille with an air of severity inquired. “Why don’t you tell me something I can’t understand. Or if that is difficult, treat me like a fellow of your own size and tell me some of your adventures. Don’t you want to smoke, Señor Don Hidalgo?”

Revell lit a cigarette, shifted, and answered:

“Adventures consist more in what we put in them than in what they contain. Of themselves, they are empty. It is our imagination that fills them. The only adventures worth having are those that come not from without, but from within. Take Napoleon. His existence was a dream from which he awoke at St. Helena. It was there only that he really lived.”

Camille made a face.

“There you go again! More artillery!”

“Well, then, take Mrs. Druce, take Madame Humbert.”

“I’m willing. Where are they?”

“Where they deserve to be—among the immortals. With nothing more ponderable than a belief, perhaps justified, in human stupidity, Madame Humbert had herself recognized as the heiress of a plutocrat who never lived.”

“What?”

“Not only that, she evoked vanishing litigants, phantom millions, a grand phantasmagoria that included a safe full of government bonds, a safe in which those bonds were officially attested to be, a safe before which guards patrolled, a safe with which she rooked the world and the ghetto and which contained precisely one collar button and a penny. Where are the great prestidigitators after that? Where are Poe, Collins, Gaboriau, and Conan Doyle? Madame Humbert invented the most picturesque fairy tale of the age. It is true she had to cut and run for it, but genius is seldom appreciated.”

Camille made another face.

“I don’t like that story.”

Revell got up, put his cigarette in an ash receiver, nodded at the girl, and sat down.

“Then you may prefer the Druce poem. Considered as pure poetry, the Tichborne case is drivel beside it. In the latter, an Australian butcher caused an English gentlewoman to recognize him as her son. In the Druce case, the daughter-in-law of a London tradesman recognized a dead duke as the grandfather of her child. She did not stop there, either, though, unlike Madame Humbert, she did not have to run for it. Besides, what is a wicked woman who takes to flight by comparison with a wickeder duke who takes to trade? For that is what this lady claimed he did. She claimed that the Duke of Portland, after murdering his brother, transformed himself into a furniture dealer, had himself die and be buried, and, reappearing, frightened his shop folk into fits. Madame Humbert had a safe in which there was a new penny. Mrs. Druce had a coffin in which there was old iron. But both had imagination. Both understood intensive living. Together, they added to the gayety of nations and, incidentally, to mine.”

Camille moved uneasily.

“Perhaps you have intensive adventures of your own to relate.”

Revell covered her with his eyes.

“Not yet.”

“You mean that you’ll tell them later?”

“If I ever go to jail.”

The room was warm, but Camille shivered.

That’s rather a gruesome possibility, isn’t it?”

“Inspirational, I should call it. When Bunyan was under lock and key, he enjoyed every kind of temptation and every variety of danger, with no other inconvenience than that of putting them all down in black and white. He was not a prisoner; he was a pilgrim. When Cervantes was jailed, the walls parted, and through them cavalcaded Sancho Panza, Don Quixote, and that great lady whose name is Fame. From a prison at Mons, Paul Verlaine issued with a sheaf of verse that carried him to Parnassus, carried him to the top. That’s the life! Life behind the bars!”

“Don’t!” she cried at him.

With real concern, he considered her.

“But I am only jesting.”

Camille shrank.

“Then your jests are horrible! You frighten me with them. I can’t bear to have you praise cheats and prisons. Particularly as—”

“As what?” he asked, for visibly she hesitated.

“I can’t tell you. Yes, I will! I will tell you! Ever since you got here, Arthur Glendenning has said—No, I can’t say it.”

But Revell helped her.

“That I am an impostor? Isn’t that it?”

“Yes,” the girl slowly got out. “But I don’t and won’t believe it.”

Revell moved over to where she sat.

“Camille, you know I love you.”

She looked up at him.

“And I love you. I love you absolutely.”

“Then trust me.”

“There’s something that you don’t want me to know?”

“Yes. For the present.”

“And when I do know it?”

“You shall be judge and jury.”

“But you are Victor Revell?”

“In flesh and blood.”

“And Mike was your friend?”

“That I can swear to.”

“And you’ve done nothing that you wouldn’t wish me to know?”

For a second, before him passed a flying picture torn from the long cinematograph of time. A second only and he answered at once:

“Nothing whatever.”

“Then you need tell me nothing else, except—”

She hesitated and he repeated it:

“Except?”

“Except that you love me.”

He moved closer.

“I don’t need to tell you. You know it.”

“A girl likes to be told,” she smiled and replied. But the smile faded and she added: “Only I do wish that mysteries had not been made out of molehills. They give me the creeps.”

“You mean about Mike? But Mike is not a molehill. Though your Mr. Glendenning probably thinks I put him in one.”

“I don’t!” Camille hotly protested. “I never have! I never could!”

Revell laughed.

“But he does, and that is a trait of real genius. For it, he deserves a niche between Madame Humbert and Mrs. Druce.”

Camille turned from him. The portières were parting. Through them Archibald appeared.

“Mr. Mike, mem, and will you see him?”

VIII

At the announcement, a whirlwind tossed her thoughts. Into them entered stretches of night. From Archibald, she turned to Revell. He had moved away. With an air of amused wonder, he was considering the servant. If, through the portières, a giraffe had peered and spoken, he could not have seemed more pleasantly surprised.

Camille, turning again to the servant, agonizedly repeated:

“Mr. Mike?”

Archibald blinked.

“Mr. Mike, mem? I meant Mr. Glendenning.”

Camille, who had gasped and half risen, sighed and sank back and, not in relief, but in the abeyance of the shock, motioned that he was to come in.

Then, in a moment, as Glendenning appeared, affably Revell nodded.

“We were just talking about you.”

Icily Glendenning surveyed them both.

“You must have been very idle.”

“I could have screamed,” said Camille. “Did you hear Archibald announce you as Mike?”

Glendenning sat down.

“He’s crazy. Since my uncle died, he has not been the same at all.”

Camille, who had got her breath, replied:

“Mr. Revell says that no one is ever the same, that life is—I’ve forgotten what, but that you are here one minute and gone the next.”

Glendenning looked over at Revell.

“You must have been referring to Mike. Personally, I would give a red pippin—I would give two of them—to know where he did go.”

Revell, who was standing with his back to the mantel, smiled pleasantly, but exasperatingly.

“If I can tell you anything, command me.”

Glendenning glared.

“You carry modesty to excess. Since he left here, no one knows anything at all about him but you.”

“Oh, I assure you, there are others in plenty. The people at the Morrow House, and more at the White River, good chaps with rough names—Ootona, Keok, Adlooat, Iyatunk—”

Camille moistened her lips.

“Who are these dears?”

Revell turned to her.

“I’ll introduce them properly. Before Mike left here, he intended to go to France; he had even obtained a passport. Meanwhile, I had written, outlining possibilities with which I was familiar and asking him to join me. He had made money at cards, more in Wall Street—enough, at least, for a while—and he started West. In San Francisco, he learned about his father and made a will—though why in my favor is momentarily unimportant—and went on and up to where I had told him he would find me, but where he contracted pleurisy and where, for medicine, there was only drink. The effect of both was such that I brought him back. When he reached San Francisco, he was dying, and at the Morrow House he died.”

To it all Camille listened with an air of such visibly absorbed interest that Glendenning, seeing that in drinking it in she was accepting it wholly, laughed.

“Where did this occur?”

Revell turned to him.

“On and about the White River.”

Glendenning grunted.

“I never heard of it.”

“No, possibly not. Before the war, you may not have known whether Verdun was in Poland or Peru. The White River is in Alaska. The climate did not agree with Mike, though it did agree with others who knew and liked him there—with, for instance, Iyatunk, Adlooat, Keok, and Ootona.”

“Confound him!” thought Glendenning, who thought, too: “What evidence could be got out of these savages even if one could get at them?”

But he said:

“I infer that you are a prospector.”

“The meanest of us have our little talents,” Revell, in his agreeable way, replied. “I was applauding yours only a moment ago.”

“You quite turn my head,” Glendenning retorted. “But you would clarify it if you can tell me why Mike made his will in your favor.”

Camille flushed and motioned:

“Arthur, that is none of your business.”

“Forgive me, Camille. I have had to make it my business. Mr. Revell will not misunderstand my attitude, either. Mike knew that rightfully the property was yours. In spite of which, he turns it over to this gentleman, and frankly I don’t understand why.”

In that same pleasant way, Revell considered him.

“I follow you there. But don’t you think that there are mysteries that are better ignored than elucidated?”

It was a moment before Glendenning could unravel the remark, and when he did, he almost whinnied:

“Ha! Yes! If there were no lawyers to do so for us.”

“And have they succeeded?” Revell, with an air of eating nougat, inquired.

The thrust, keen and prompt as the point of a sword, pricked before it could be parried. From it Glendenning backed.

“May I ask you a question, Mr. Revell?”

“I am entirely at your service.”

Glendenning braced himself and straight at him threw it.

“Then where is Mike now?”

Camille sprang up. She was not red, but she saw it.

“Arthur, I am ashamed of you! Mr. Revell is my guest. I won’t permit him to be insulted!”

But Revell, who seemed perplexed, merely, and not insulted in the least, intervened.

“Mr. Glendenning has probably some good reason for asking that.”

“I should say so!” Glendenning exclaimed. “And with no reason to conceal it—or anything else—either.”

Camille stamped a foot.

“Then what is it?”

Glendenning twisted and fired:

“The fact that the Mike Vulper who died in San Francisco was not Mike at all.”

Camille went white. She stared at Revell, who was looking at something that she could not see—a flying picture that showed dawn, drizzling rain, and the feverish and friendless derelict who, accosting him then, had begged for the love of God the price of a night’s lodging. A moment only. The picture faded. Revell was looking at Camille, who was staring at him.

From her he turned with a smile to Glendenning.

“You remind me of Hegel. Hegel propounded contradictory propositions. That is what you have done. It is very difficult. Let me applaud you for it.”

“He is swamping me with words,” thought Glendenning, who fired again:

“The man in the Morrow House was a tramp with a beard.”

Pleasantly, but indifferently, Revell nodded.

“There are no barbers on the White River. No tailors, either. Life there has its penalties.”

“And its rewards.”

“Undoubtedly, and you may share them if you care to go and join my friends there.”

“He has an answer for everything,” thought Glendenning.

But he said:

“What became of Mike’s effects?”

“Together with my own, they went down from an overturned canoe. When we reached civilization, we had only the rags we stood up in. The coat that Mike then wore I still have. In the inside pocket is a tag that reads ‘Johnson & Jordan, Fifth—’ ”

“Avenue,” Camille cut in. Relieved and appeased, she had reseated herself. “I went with him there once when he was ordering a suit. He wanted me to select the material.”

“May I smoke?” Revell asked.

The girl nodded.

“Yes, and you, too, Arthur, if you want it. Only, for Heaven’s sake, let it be the pipe of peace.”

But Glendenning was on his feet.

“I’m off. Good night.” And he pranced himself out.

Camille turned with a smile to her lover.

“He acted like a wild boar, didn’t he?”

Revell approached her.

“No, not wild exactly. I should say that he has lucid intervals in which he is merely tedious.”

Then at once they were in each other’s arms.

IX

From Broadway’s blazing cereals, glittering corsets, coruscating gums, and fiery cats; from its pandemonium of lights, people, and bellowing motors, Glendenning entered the taproom where he was to meet Tatum.

He looked about, and not seeing his lawyer among the men there who were talking money in thousands, in hundred thousands, talking money noisily and talking nothing else, he seated himself at a table and ordered a whisky and soda.

When, with a pop, it was produced, he swore deeply, tossed it off, lit a cigar, and through the smoke of it turned the matter over, looked at it, as he had on the way down, from this angle, from that, from the other. Yet, however he viewed it, though it had the same fishy smell, the fish itself was invisible. It was there somewhere, but, try as he might, it escaped.

He swore again. Fate, in the shape of Revell, was slowly, but surely, dragging from him the two things that he wanted most in the world—that girl and that money. But hope is forever saying “good morning” to you, and, the whisky prompting, he told himself that Revell had not got either of them yet—and never would so long as his lungs held out and he could cry, “Stop thief!”

Only, to whom could he cry it? Not to Camille; she would not listen. Not to Revell; he would only laugh. But thank the Lord there still were the courts. Yet there, too, at the moment, he was stumped, for, barring the certainties of his own intuitions, he had not a thing to go on.

For him, those certainties were ample. They screamed at him. They shrieked the loose joints in Revell’s armor. They flaunted the fact, undeniable and beyond peradventure, that in the problematic event of Mike’s having made a will, it was in Camille’s favor that he would have made it. Therefore, he had but to show that the will was a forgery and that impostor would be jailed, the estate would be his, and, in the rebound, Camille also.

From that dream he started. Tatum, with his chucker-out air and prima-donna voice, was addressing him.

“Well, and did you do him?”

At a hovering waiter he murmured, “A high ball.” After which, he sat massively down and with a bulldog look listened while Glendenning recited the Alaskan epic.

The tale ended, Tatum drank and wiped his mouth.

“That was a very good show I saw tonight, but Revell must be a better one. Have you a match?”

Glendenning shoved him a box.

“Thanks. Have you a cigar also? Thanks again. As our friend probably knows, no law of God or man runs north of fifty-three. His Alaskan romance is, therefore, admirable. In it is the real artist’s surety of touch. It ought to be put to music. Of course, if I had him on the witness stand, I could run a limousine through it. But haven’t him there and I doubt now that I ever shall.”

“Why, today you—”

“Yes, I know, and afterward I saw Marvalho. As an expert, he has no superior and but one equal, Bakharoff, who lives in Petrograd, unless he is dead at the front. Marvalho said that the writing in the will and in Mike’s letters is identical. He said that I could take it or leave it, but that all three were written by the same man.”

Tatum drank again and added:

“It’s a great pity.”

He meant it, too, but he was thinking of his bill.

“I had quite counted on landing the estate,” he continued. “But as this life is ordered, nothing is certain except what has already happened. None the less—”

He paused, beat a brief tattoo on the table, nodded at Glendenning, and resumed.

“None the less, with the least adroitness, we ought still to grab the lion’s share. We have only to adopt toward Mike the same fiduciary position that Revell occupies and we will have turned the trick.”

Glendenning, who took it for granted that Tatum was drunk, groaned helplessly.

“Yes,” Tatum was saying, “it may be, as you once said, that Mike did for his father, and it may also be that Revell knows it. For the moment, however, all that is obscure and immaterial. But for reason, Mike shuns the light of day. For some reason, he is hiding. For some reason, he covers his tracks, makes a will, and pretends to die, having previously arranged with his beneficiary to share the estate with him. But we can do any sharing as well as Revell, can’t we?”

Glendenning covered his mouth with a hand. Tatum, he saw, was not drunk, but was he mad?

“Of course we can,” Tatum, answering his own question, ran on. “Better, even. For Revell would certainly pocket it all; whereas we, as men of honor, would see to it that Mike received—well, a third. Perhaps a trifle less. But we would do the square thing.”

“Tatum,” Glendenning got out, “what are you driving at?”

“The estate of course. What else? I want my share in it, too. And I’ll get it. For Mike did not die in San Francisco and, since he omitted to there, it’s even money that he omitted to entirely. We have only to find him and—”

“Yes!” the exasperated Glendenning exclaimed. “But where?”

“Why, here in New York. I doubt if he ever left this sordid city.”

“But since Marvalho says that the will is in his writing, he must have made it out West.”

“Not in the least. He drew it here, signed it here, and shipped it to Revell, who, in affecting to recopy it, flimflammed the San Francisco lawyers with the original. These lawyers certainly did not reread it. Why should they? They merely had their clerks witness a paper which Revell pretended to sign. Anyway, if Mike was not here then, he is here now. Consequently, all we have to do is to find him, tell him that we will do as well by him as Revell, put on the thumbscrews, and there you are.”

Helplessly Glendenning looked into his empty glass. He could not see it and said so.

Tatum took it up.

“Then follow Revell.”

“Oh, as for that, I have.”

Tatum nodded.

“Good! You are over seven years of age.”

Glendenning nodded back.

“At the hotel where he is stopping, he has no visitors, receives no mail, never telephones.”

“Pays his bill regularly?”

“And in cash.”

“In twenty-dollar bills, perhaps. Where does he go?”

“To the Public Library or else to Miss Marcy’s.”

“He’s a bigger man than I thought.”

“In what way?”

“He stands alone—or appears to. What hotel is he stopping at?”

“The St. Jasper.”

Tatum beat another brief tattoo.

“There are a lot of rooms in that house.”

“What of it?”

“It’s a pity we can’t go through them all.”

“Why?”

“Because Mike is in one of them. Have you a match?”

“There’s a box before you, but here’s a cigar. How do you get that?”

“Through the process of elimination. If Mike is not dead, he must be somewhere. If he and Revell are in league, they must be in touch. Since Revell has no visitors, receives no mail, does not telephone, and goes nowhere, they are in the same hotel. You told me that Mike was a good mimic, did you not?”

“And a born actor.”

“Then he is masquerading there, and probably in the room next to Revell. Anyway, he’s at the St. Jasper. Glendenning, I’ll stake my reputation on that. Well, yes, since you insist, I’ll have another high ball.”

Darkly, for a while yet, the two men talked.

X

“Oh! Miss Marcy—”

At the cry, Camille, who was dressed for a run, stopped and turned.

In the hall, hurrying after her, was her maid, Margaret. As Camille stopped, she stopped also.

“What is it?”

But Margaret, her mouth working, made no reply.

“What is it?” Camille, perplexed at the mummery, impatiently repeated.

“Oh, Miss Marcy, Archibald’s on the floor. He—”

Camille hurried by her and on and beyond to the extreme end of the apartment. There, in a little room which she had not seen since she first took the flat, the withered servant lay in a heap, the eyes staring, the face mottled, one corner of the mouth lifted as a dog’s when about to bite, and with things wrapped in paper beside him.

Camille looked in and bit her lip. Her tender heart reproached her. Only a little since she had said—and crossly enough—that she would not be sorry to lose him and now she had, or at least she supposed so, but she could not be sure; it might be but a fit of some kind, and she hurried back to the other end of the apartment, where she telephoned and waited until at last Dix appeared.

Telling him what little she could, she sent him in with the maid for guide, and that only because she was young and, to those that are, death, instead of being the normal interruption that it is, always suggests something spectral.

She was still in the hall when Dix returned.

“Cerebral hemorrhage,” he told her, and together they entered the drawing-room.

In the physician’s hands were two packages, which he put on the piano.

“I can’t say I did not expect it,” he resumed. “He has been in to see me several times. He had nephritis—and other things.”

Camille sighed.

“I am very sorry, He was queer, but he was faithful.”

“It’s difficult to be that and not the other,” Dix, with frank cynicism, replied. “I’ll have an undertaker come and—”

“You say he had things the matter with him?”

“Yes, his conscience was affected. It was that that made him what you describe as queer. For the last few months, he has lived in a panic, and there are few toxins more depressive than fear.”

“Why, what on earth had he to be afraid of?”

Dix seated himself on the piano stool.

“What have we, any of us, to be afraid of except danger, damp sheets, and our own misdeeds? There is nothing else.”

Camille flicked at her boots.

“Yes, but—”

Dix waved at her.

“An hour before your guardian died, I was with him; so was Archibald. Mr. Vulper was then apparently in his usual poor health. I was called away. When I returned, he was dead. You remember what occurred?”

“Yes, you sent for me. It was very painful.”

“I mean in regard to the safe.”

“You said that money was missing—money and papers.”

Dix indicated the packages.

“There they are. In one of those bundles is ten thousand dollars in twenty-dollar bills. In the other is ‘Alpha and Omega’—a manuscript that your guardian intended to leave to the British Museum.”

Camille, who had stopped flicking at her boots, sat down. A few minutes before, when, in answer to her call, Dix had come, she had not noticed the packages. Now she supposed that he must have brought them with him, though how and where he had got them she could not imagine.

“Well?”

Dix plucked at his beard.

“As Mike’s executor, I have impounded them. They are now part and parcel of the estate.”

“But where did they come from?” Camille, in a crescendo of surprise, exclaimed.

Dix glanced at her. Ordinarily he had thought her a bright young woman. At the moment, she seemed unfathomably stupid.

His arm shot out.

“From that room yonder. Where else?”

Camille stared and gasped.

“You mean Archibald’s? Then he took them! Then—Why, then it was he who killed Mr. Vulper!”

At the thought of it, she shuddered. The thought that, since then, the man had been with her, under her roof, serving her, throttled, and she gasped again.

“Nothing of the kind,” Dix irritably replied. “It was chloral. After I had gone, cardiac paralysis supervened and narcosis resulted. Then Archibald happened in on him, and realizing, not, perhaps, that he was dead, but that he was unconscious, he took the money. And thinking—very innocently—to lay it on that fantastic hallucination, Shri Shankira, took the manuscript also.”

Dix removed his eyeglasses. By nature and by profession he was modest, but he could not help saying it: “I always knew it.”

In annoyance, Camille shook her crop.

“Doctor Dix, you should have told me!”

But Dix was not afraid of her.

“Oh, when I say I knew it, I mean I took it for granted. But I had no evidence. Archibald was aware of that. At the same time, he was aware, too, that I suspected him and, though he lacked the courage to own up, it would have been a sheer relief to him if I had said: ‘Thou art the man.’ ”

“Yet always before that he had been honest,” Camille wonderingly put in.

“How do you know? Anyway, he had probably never been tempted before by such a bevy of beautiful bank notes. ‘Carry us off,’ they cried at him. At that, all the cells of his brain fell asleep, all except one, and that cell, vehemently active, incited him to elope with them. When he did, somnambulism ceased; his entire brain awoke. He knew what he had done. He knew, too, the penalties for it. But it was too late. The theft had been discovered and ever since he has lived in a panic. When jurisprudence is more advanced, it will be recognized that any crime belongs to the domain of mental pathology. But forgive me for mistaking you for a clinic.”

“Well, I never!” Camille exclaimed. “And all the time Arthur Glendenning has been saying that it was Mike!”

Dix took the packages and stood up.

“I don’t think you need disturb yourself about what he says. By the way, how do you like Revell?”

“Very much,” the girl replied, but she flushed as she did so.

Dix, who saw everything, saw that.

“Oho! So we are in love, are we?” he thought.

But he said:

“Then I take it that Glendenning does not like him.”

Camille, too, got up.

“Like him! The last time he was here—or was it the time before?—he said that Mr. Revell had killed Mike.”

“Ah?” Dix indifferently rejoined. “Well, stranger things have happened.”

With the packages under his arm, he went on and out and reached his office, where he learned that the reception room was full. Before seeing any of the patients, he telephoned instructions to an undertaker, telephoned more to the Amsterdam Trust Company; after which, one at a time, with businesslike expedition, he bundled his patients off.

When all had gone, the bank messenger arrived. Dix gave him the packages.

“Here is a manuscript that belongs to the Vulper estate. Here are ten thousand dollars that belong to it, also. You may give me a receipt for both.”

Even an expert cannot count ten wads, of fifty bills each, in two minutes. Dix, judging that the messenger might be four or five at it, took down an old copy of a review.

In it was an account of a series of surgical operations performed on a woman who, though the account did not say so, perhaps wanted to be a belle—a vocation for which she had been rather handicapped, for she had had a squat nose, high cheek bones, protruding ears, thick, wide lips, and eyes, like Anne Boleyn’s, each of a different color.

According to the account, these pleasantries of nature had been one and all—and without a scar—corrected.

The account continued:

“The cartilages were detached from the nasal bones, and the periosteum and tissues separated from them. A small portion of the septum was also removed, and so much of the bridge was then cut that when, toward the median line, both sides were broken with a forceps, they met and formed a perfectly straight Greek nose.

“With the lips, a longitudinal incision was made from the corner of the mouth, a half inch from the vermilion border, and run parallel with the white skin line, the incision being continued to the opposite corner. An oblong piece of the submucous and cellular tissue on each side of the median line was then removed, and, after turning away enough of the membrane, the operation was so conducted that, when the wound and its edges were approximated with fine silk sutures, the margin of the lip could be drawn down and rolled under, thereby acquiring the Cupid’s bow.

“With the cheek bones, the mucous membrane in the mouth was divided from the median line to the posterior border of the supermaxillary; all tissues, together with the periosteum, were separated; and when, with a chisel, enough of the molar bone was removed, a face symmetrically oval resulted.

“With the eyes—”

But now the messenger interrupted.

“I’ve been over them twice, sir. I make it nine thousand nine hundred, and eighty dollars. Will you count them yourself?”

Dix shook his head.

“Make out a receipt accordingly.”

That done and the messenger gone, Dix turned again to the story of the happy lot of the lady who wanted to be a belle.

Meanwhile, Camille, aware of the impatient cob and the patient groom and aware, too, that she was no longer in a mood for a run that day, sent Margaret to tell them not to wait. Deciding then that, temporarily at least, she could eat nothing in the apartment, she telephoned to Kate Delafield, arranged to have the girl join her for luncheon at a Fifth Avenue inn, and changed her costume for street dress.

Later, over eggs cooked in potatoes, a mousselined chicken, and poached peaches, the two girls talked as only two girls can talk, until Kate Delafield, remembering an appointment, abandoned Camille, who, in a taxi, sailed up again and on through the Park to Seventy-second Street, turned for the Riverside.

But in a moment Camille screamed, poked at the chauffeur, stopped him, jumped out, and darted down the subway stair. A ticket taker yelled and swore at her. She did not heed him. She did not hear. Intent only on catching up with a man whose face for a second she had seen, the cries of a hundred ticket takers would not have stopped her. Only, as it happened, an express was just pulling out. She had missed him.

“You wasn’t leaving me like this, was you, lady?”

She turned. Before her was the chauffeur.

There are explanations that explain nothing. Camille attempted none. Accompanied by the chauffeur, who, on the landing above, winked with unfathomable good-fellowship at the fuming ticket taker, she reentered the taxi and drove to her home, where, as she was paying the man, Glendenning marched up.

“I’ve had such a start!” she told him. “I thought I saw Mike.”

“Where? When?”

“Just now, at the subway entrance.”

“Well, you may have. But I hardly think so. He never goes out in the daytime.”

Camille moved back.

“What do you mean?”

Glendenning, balancing himself on one foot, replied:

“Revell has him locked up at the St. Jasper.”

Indignantly the girl’s lip curled. “Oh, come now! First you had Mike murdering his father. Then you had Mr. Revell murdering Mike. Now he has him in a cage. Well, I believe that as much as I do the rest of it.”

“Camille,” he snorted, “there are things that you never consider. Who took the money from my uncle’s safe? Who—”

“Ask Doctor Dix.”

But already, with a gesture of annoyance, she had turned. It was from over her shoulder that she threw those three small and, to Glendenning, entirely enigmatic words.

At once he protested.

“I will come in with you.”

Angrily she shook herself. Never again would she allow him or any one else to say a word against Revell, who, from the drawing-room window, was at that moment smiling down on both.

“You need not, then,” she threw as before at Glendenning. “For I won’t be at home.”

She flew in, flew up, and, finding Revell, flew into his arms.

XI

“There is something so commercial about a diamond. You never see one without wondering what it is worth. But in the ruby is the secret of beauty. Like the rose, it charms and does nothing.”

Camille, listening to Revell’s remarks, looked at the stone he had brought her. After the manner of the modern girl that she was, she cared little for jewels. But there are old-fashioned conventions that still persist, and an engagement ring is one of them.

Already she had told him about Archibald, about the money and the manuscript—a little string of episodes that interested him hugely, far more, indeed, than she had imagined they would; and it was after he had absorbed the story that the ring—and the remarks—were produced.

“But though I love you with all my heart,” he resumed, “though I loved you from the beginning and shall love you to the end, I cannot decently ask you to marry me until you are informed of certain things.”

Camille assumed the look of a martyr.

“Don’t! I’m overburdened with information now.”

“So am I,” answered. “I must share it with you. One night in San Francisco, Mike and I ran into a poor devil who was so ill that he could hardly stand. He said that he was without a friend or relative in the world and begged us, for the love of God, to help him. On the corner was a cheap lodging house where we took him and got him a room in which Mike left his passport. The next day the man died, and it was the name on the passport that was entered on the death certificate.”

Through the window came the light and eagerness of the April sun. But the room seemed suddenly dark. In that darkness Camille, who had been sitting very close to Revell, edged from him. She did not know what to say, nor yet what now to expect. It was a moment, even, before she could speak.

“You say Mike was with you?”

“Certainly he was with me.”

“Then what became of him afterward?”

“Nothing in particular. He’s very well, though, if that is what you mean.”

“But his will, then? A live man can’t have his will entered for probate, can he?”

“Now that you mention it, I don’t think that any live man ever succeeded in doing so before. But Mike can be very surprising. When he first learned of his father’s death and of the suspicions his absence had aroused, his first impulse was to return here. But as I told him, first impulses are to be guarded against. They are almost invariably noble. Then, on reflection, he agreed with me that it would be stupid to run the risk of being arrested for a crime that he had not committed, that he could not disprove, but that inevitably Glendenning would try to fasten on him. And he agreed too, that, meanwhile, it would harm no one if he remained out of sight. Now, though, in view of Archibald, it is all quite different.”

Camille, who had been looking down, looked up. The room seemed brighter, the air less charged.

“I told you an awful whopper about it,” Revell continued. “But though I lied like a thief, it was for you. Honest men never lie except to those they love. For those they love, a good, straight lie is often a great protection. It preserves them from that vulture of the mind that worry is. Then, too, agreeable people only say agreeable things, and there is nothing better for the complexion. If, when I first got here, I had told you that Mike was playing possum and that I was just masquerading as his heir, you would have shown me the door—which I admit is very pretty and well worth being shown. But you wouldn’t have liked it. Perhaps you don’t like it even now.”

Camille sighed and shook her docked hair.

“Oh, I suppose I shall when I get used to it. But just now I feel all upside down. Whenever I get mixed up, it gives me a headache. Why is that?”

Revell took her hand.

“In the present case, I suppose because you don’t know whether or not you can forgive me.”

At that, she put her other hand on his.

“Victor, when a girl loves a man, she can forgive him anything. Only—”

“Only what?”

“Don’t give me any more headaches.”

“Not if I can help it, though Mike may.”

“Oh, that reminds me. I could have sworn I saw him today in the street.”

“And I can swear you did not,” thought Revell, but he only smiled.

“It gave me such a start! Afterward I told Arthur Glendenning, who said that it could not be Mike—that you kept him locked up at the St. Jasper.”

“Where the deuce did he get that?” thought Revell.

But he said:

“Glendenning is a very amusing person. He ought to be on a barrel organ with a chain around him.”

“Anyway,” Camille continued, “Mike might come to see me. Where is he?”

“He’s here. He’s in town. But what would be the use of his coming? He said you wouldn’t look at him.”

“But I always liked him.”

“He said he didn’t want to be liked. He wanted—”

“I know, and I couldn’t. I was waiting for you, Victor! For you!”

“But he will dance at our wedding, if you’ll forgive me my lies.”

Then, through the brief blue afternoon, they talked. Finally Revell stood up.

“I’ll come again tonight, dearest. But meanwhile do you remember anything about a silver coin? Mike told me he gave you one the night he went away.”

“Yes, I have it somewhere. Why?”

“Mike told me to get you to run a finger around the edge of it.”

Perplexed, and very prettily perplexed, Camille got up.

“He did? What for?”

“In order that you may find what otherwise you might never discover—a spring on which you are to press and say, ‘Sesame!’ The coin will open like Aladdin’s cave—or was it Aladdin’s? Anyway, that’s what you are to do.”

“And then?”

“I’m not supposed to know anything else. But after you’ve opened the coin, will you telephone?”

“Certainly I will, Victor. But as you’re coming this evening, what do you want me to say?”

“That you want me to come.”

“But I can tell you that now.”

“You see, between now and then, you may change your mind.”

“Oh, now I’m all mixed up again! And you promised not to give me another headache!”

“But I was careful not to promise for Mike. This is his doing, not mine.”

Then, in a moment, after certain ceremonies, Revell went out and on to the St. Jasper, where two men ominously waited.

XII

Late that same afternoon, Tatum, sitting back in his office chair, glowered fiercely at the Archibald episode, which Glendenning, who had got it from Dix, was relating. He glowered the fiercer because already he had been assured by the St. Jasper’s house detective that there was nobody masquerading there, no mysterious guest.

The tale about Archibald, dumped on top of that, knocked momentarily the props from under. But the fiercer Tatum looked, the more gently he talked, and in his mayonnaise voice he summarized it.

“Well, then, we have got to get at it another way, and this, I’ll lay a cooky, is the way of it. Since Mike has no reason to be in hiding and yet can’t be found, he is dead, dead as a doornail. In view of which, we can now accept that Alaska romance as truth—some of it at any rate.”

Glendenning, pulling at his long nose, whinnied:

“Ha! Revell did for him up there, pitched him overboard, drowned him in that White River.”

“Possibly,” Tatum cooed, “and very probably. But previously, in San Francisco, two men were planning to go prospecting for gold far up in a land that has its hazards. One of the men—Revell, let us say—mentions the dangers, and with noble disinterestedness offers to make a will in his partner’s favor; whereat Mike, not to be outdone, makes one in favor of Revell, who, in return, sandbags him at the first opportunity. After which, unable to show that Mike died a natural death, he is up a tree and stays there until, through sheer luck, he happens on and rechristens a moribund tramp. That’s the size of it.”

Glendenning kicked a foot out.

“And it fits!”

“Now,” Tatum, in his prima-donna manner, resumed, “we go to this Mr. Revell, you as your uncle’s heir and I as your counsel. We get him in a quiet corner and drive those two facts quietly home. Then I say: ‘Mr. Revell, we—er—propose to attack the will on the ground that while—er—personally I am convinced that the testator is dead, I know that—er—he did not die in the Morrow House.’ First blood. Eh? What?”

“Good for you! Hit him again!”

“I say to him: ‘Mr. Revell, the proceedings may be long and costly and in any event will have—er—the widest publicity. In the course of that publicity, it may be discovered just—er—well, just what did happen to my client’s unfortunate cousin. Now, Mr. Revell, my client wishes to avoid proceedings, precisely as you, I am sure, wish to escape—er—notoriety. For your own sake, let us spare you that. Moreover, we are not bandits; we are honest men. Deed us two-thirds of your interest under the will and in consideration of that, we, for our part, undertake not to contest it.’ ”

Glendenning jumped up.

“That’s the talk! Let’s be at him!”

Tatum consulted his watch.

“He may be going to make a night of it.”

“Not he!” Glendenning snorted. “He’s one of those devils that sit in their room and read.”

Then, in the subway presently, the two men were en route for the St. Jasper, of which the hall, saturated with tobacco and electricity, full of people, of hurrying pages, of parties coming in for dinner, and of guests eying each other hostilely or with indifference, resounded with voices, with the click of the typewriter, and the noise of lifts that ceaselessly rose and descended.

The two men, entering there, asked for Revell and, learning that he was not then in his room, stood about for a while and waited.

Finally Glendenning nudged Tatum.

“There he is now.”

Through the hall he lounged along and, seeing Glendenning, approached, but without any of the amenities, without even a nod.

Glendenning was more gracious.

“Revell,” he began, “this is Mr. Tatum, my counsel.”

Revell looked the lawyer up and down.

“Well, what of it?”

The insolence was so marked that it gave Glendenning pause, but suavely, in that voice of his, Tatum took it up. “Mr. Revell, we would like a little private conversation with—”

Revell cut him short.

“I dare say. But it will have to be public and it will have to be brief.”

For a man usually so civil, it was all a bit odd. But toward the world at large and these men in particular, Revell felt waspish. He did not know what, at any moment, the telephone might have to say.

“Mr. Revell,” Tatum oleaginously resumed, “it is not a matter that you would wish to have us talk of here.”

Revell, extracting a cigarette, lit it and with the same insolent indifference replied:

“You may scream it, for all I care.”

For a fierce-looking man Tatum could smile very archly. That smile he exhibited.

“Mr. Revell, you are—er—in a very awkward predicament.”

Revell nodded.

“I should say so! It’s always awkward to be held up. What the devil do you want?”

Oilily Tatum rubbed his hands.

“Perhaps we had best adjourn to the café.”

Revell blew a ring of smoke.

“I seldom drink, and never with strangers.”

“Mr. Revell, believe me, we are your friends.”

Revell laughed, but it was not a pleasant laugh.

“Then, to employ an antique jest, you ought to sue your faces for libel.”

Archly once more Tatum smiled.

“You may think better of that when I tell you that you are in imminent danger of arrest. Don’t you think now that we’d better find a quiet little corner?”

“Less than ever. If you have any charges, call the police.”

At that, into it, Glendenning jumped.

“If he does, the charge will be murder!”

Tatum turned to him.

“Tut, tut! Softly does it.” He turned to Revell. “My client is a bit brusque. He probably wished to represent that the man who died at the Morrow House was not his cousin.”

“Well, what of it?”

“What of it?” Tatum, affecting the profoundest astonishment, exclaimed. “Why, Mr. Revell, if that man was not Mike, where is Mike?” He paused, dropped his voice, and unconcernedly added: “But I don’t need to ask—I know.”

“What the deuce do you want, then?”

“To save you, as I said, from a very awkward predicament.”

“Thanks. I can take care of myself.”

“Mr. Revell, you will hardly say that when I, as the representative of this gentleman, my client, oppose the probating of the will of which you are the beneficiary on the ground—Shall I tell you what it is in some quieter place?”

“No. Moreover, I don’t care a rap what your grounds are. I don’t care a rap whether you contest it or not. But meanwhile I have no intention of being blackmailed.”

Glendenning squared himself.

“You shall answer for that.”

Revell laughed again.

“See here, Glendenning. Do you believe in miracles? For you ought to, you know. It has taken a procession of them to keep you out of Sing Sing and I dare say that the same is true of your fat friend.”

Before either could retort, a page came bawling:

“Mr. Revell! Mr. Revell!”

Revell stopped him.

“Mr. Revell? Wanted at the telephone, sir.”

“Ask them to hold it a moment,” Revell instructed the lad and turned again to Glendenning. “Now drop your airs. Do you remember the last thing Mike said to you? He said, ‘I’ll surprise you yet.’ Mark my words, he will.”

He turned again, lounged down the hall, entered a booth, closed the door. He was in a quiet place at last.

Uncertainly, for a moment, the two men eyed each other. Tatum was the first to speak.

“That fellow has got a card up his sleeve. A card? He has a whole pack of them. Now, what are they? At the same time, he might have been more civil. That mention of miracles was very ungentlemanly.”

Glendenning did not immediately reply. When he did, he swore.

“Confound the brute! When he first got here, I felt that I had seen him somewhere and told him so, and what do you suppose he said?”

“What?”

“That he went there now and then.”

“Think of that, now! Sh! Here he is.”

Meanwhile, over the wire, Revell had been listening to Camille.

“Victor, I found the coin and the spring. It opened like a locket. Victor?”

“Yes?”

“In it was a slip of paper on which Mike had written that the slip was just to establish his identity in case of dispute. Victor?”

“Yes?”

“Mike said that he was going to have his face entirely altered and that Doctor Dix has some Medical Record which tells how it is done. Victor?”

“Yes?”

“Oh, Victor, are you you or are you Mike?”

“I don’t hear you?” replied Revell, who heard perfectly. “But no matter. Have you changed your mind or shall I come?”

“Come! Come! Whoever you are, I adore you!”

Now, that conversation at an end, Revell lounged along to finish the other, and very fit and fine he looked. And that scorn, that anger, where were they? Actually, he was offering Tatum his hand.

“I’m sorry to have kept you standing here. It was most inhospitable of me. I would have asked you elsewhere, but I was expecting a message. Now, though, if I may advise you, Mr. Tatum, and that gentleman your client, let me suggest that you ask Doctor Dix for a Medical Record that he has in his office and that contains an article written by a San Francisco surgeon. The article, if I remember rightly, is entitled ‘Facial Sculpturing,’ and when you have looked it over, you will perhaps understand what a man of your ability might have grasped long since.”

Tatum, glaring his fiercest, gently asked:

“And what is that?”

Revell had been speaking very engagingly, but he had been speaking, too, in a voice other than that which he habitually used, a voice before which Glendenning backed in sheer terror.

“What is it?” he repeated. “To my regret, I have hardly the time to tell you. But summarily the article is to the effect that a man—for the sake, let us say, of winning a girl—may have his appearance so altered that the girl will not recognize him—or, for that matter, his own cousin, either.”

Glendenning, clutching at Tatum for support, spluttered feverishly:

“You don’t mean that you’re Mike?”

The impostor, smiling cruelly at him, smiled also at the lawyer.

“Take him home, Mr. Tatum. The dear boy never was strong—particularly in the upper story.”

The effect of that was as abrupt as it was blighting. Tatum and Glendenning fell, open-mouthed, apart, fell literally to pieces. For a second, Glendenning, his jaw working, his eyes bulging, stared and swayed. Then, drunkenly, he staggered to the door.

But Tatum, who, with a mighty effort, was recovering, stood his ground. “Mr. Vulper, just that I may preserve your respect, let me assure you that from the start I suspected it. If now, or later, I can be of use, my address is—”

Mike laughed.

“I don’t expect to die just yet, but, when I do, I may ask you to draw another will. It will be simple enough. Everything to my wife.”

On Tatum’s fierce face that arch smile feebly showed itself.

“Oh! You are married, then! I—”

“Not yet,” Mike, making for the lift, replied. “But I shall be tomorrow. Good night.”

“Good night,” murmured Tatum, who, at the door, put that last straw on the broken Glendenning.

The Nameless Shame

“It is most unusual!” said the Duchess of Kincardine. “Most!” she added. Then, rallying, she exclaimed: “What is the world coming to?”

There had been a stupid discussion that had arisen, how, the Lord only knows, apropos of the tea things, perhaps, on the subject of poached eggs. I had ventured to state that it was sinful to poach them in water, that no one with any sense of self-respect would touch an egg that had not been cooked in milk and mushrooms.

“Why not in champagne and pineapples?” Agatha, the duchess’ daughter, had suggested. “Yes, why not?”

But here solemnities were interrupted. Yorke—the Honorable Eric—a beautifully preserved young man of forty, glided in.

“Ferrol is dead,” he soothingly announced. “Howdy do? He was found on the floor. Good-afternoon. Thanks, very much. No sugar.”

“Dead!” cried a fat, rancid-faced woman, known as Lady Massingbird. “How shocking! And his engagement to Miss Rivers off only yesterday! But what was it? A fit?”

“No,” Yorke replied, in the same soothing way. “No. It appears that somebody strangled him.”

It was at this juncture that the Duchess of Kincardine made her notable exclamation.

The duchess, it is hardly more than worth while to relate, was nee, as you may remember, not merely retroussé, but Genevieve Bridgewater, of Washington Square. The story of her marriage to a Scotch bankrupt is common property. It is also ancient history. So ancient that long since she found time to develop the Kincardine burr, and therewith a perfection of dowdiness which even in London was considered successful. Yet these laurels must have been insufficient. Whether because of her nose, or the immaculate atmosphere of lower Fifth Avenue, in which she had been brought up, or both, or something else, natural ambition, perhaps, she had also succeeded in being talked about. But that, too, is ancient history.

I had known her when she was a little thing in short skirts, and I remember still the spindle legs which she then exhibited. That rather intimate reminiscence constituted my passport to her very dingy house in Hill Street, where, of a June afternoon, she was inquiring what the world was coming to.

In London, anything that has not occurred every day since the memory of man runs not to the contrary is always unusual, unless it happens to be most so. The remark of the duchess was, therefore, in accordance with precedent. But in this instance it was justified.

The death of Ferrol—Lord Henry Grafton Ferrol—was, when you got at the facts, not merely unusual and most unusual, but altogether extraordinary. It was the curious circumstance that his engagement should have been broken one day and he should have been killed the next which astounded the duchess and, for that matter, the rest of us who were with her. But that circumstance, however astounding, was tame beside the surprises which followed.

With Ferrol I had had a slight acquaintance, one which had begun in Hill Street and had continued—of all places in the world—in the British Museum. Incidentally, I was also acquainted with Miss Rivers. Like the duchess, she, too, was a New Yorker, a millionairess to boot, and a tip top sample of what our commerce in beauty can exhibit. Joined to her looks and her dollars she had an air of dauntlessness which, to me, was very fetching, but which, in London, I had heard catalogued as “so American,” a phrase which, being interpreted, means, I believe, very vulgar.

Of the breaking of her engagement to Lord Ferrol I was aware, but not of the reason. On that subject no one in Hill Street could, I found, enlighten me. It was known merely that the day previous the girl had gone to Paris. But with conjectures I was presently supplied.

Into the room there had erupted a compatriot, Lady Silverstairs, a delightful little woman, who knew pretty much all that was going and a good deal that was not. She, too, had heard of Ferrol’s death and also of the broken engagement. Concerning the latter, Lady Massingbird was at the moment holding forth.

“It must be, don’t you think?” she indulgently put it, “that either she found out something awful about him or else that he found out something still more awful about her?”

“May not the discoveries have been mutual?” Lady Silverstairs suggested.

“Yes,” said the duchess; “but, then, you see even that does not explain how he got strangled.”

The word seemed to stir my delightful compatriot voluptuously. “Strangled?” she repeated. “I thought it was a rupture of a—of a thingumagig.”

“Oh, no,” Yorke consolingly corrected. “Howdy do? No. Ferrol’s man ran out and saw Simpson in a hansom. Simpson, you know, is the chap who looks after—what? Yes, physician in ordinary. Well, from what I heard this afternoon at the Bachelors’, Simpson said that it was due to compression of the carotid artery.”

“Where is that?” asked the Lady Agatha, who, with affected precipitance, added, “Don’t tell me, though, if—if—”

“Oh, no,” Yorke reassuringly answered, fumbling as he spoke at his neck, “it is here.”

“But who did it? They don’t suspect Miss Rivers, do they? Or did he do it himself?”

“No one knows who did it. But, of course he did not do it. Simpson, don’t you see, says that that isn’t possible. I dare say—”

Yorke proceeded to lose himself in amiable hypotheses. But presently whipped in by the duchess, he got back again to what he had heard. What he had heard was to this effect:

Ferrol, the evening previous, on returning to chambers which he occupied at the corner of Piccadilly and St. James Street, had dismissed his man for the night. This servant, who had been with him forever, had then gone to his quarters below stairs, and had remained there until the next morning, when, in fetching up Ferrol’s breakfast, he found him flat on the floor, the mouth and eyes wide open. Then Simpson had been called in and he, deciding that it was a case for the police, had notified Scotland Yard. The latter had been stumped at once. In the dead man’s chambers nothing relative to the crime or to the presence of a criminal had been found, though, from the housekeeper, a hint had been pulled. This woman, the night previous, had been to a music hall. She had returned about one o’clock. In proceeding to her room, which was at the top of the house, she had, in passing Ferrol’s door, noticed that it was open. Then, on reaching the floor above she had heard a lady going down. She had not seen her. She had but heard the rustle of her skirt.

Yes, but whose skirt? Murder is painful, but a skirt is demulcent. Whose skirt was it? The question, ping-ponged over the tea things, finally lost itself among them. No one knew anything about Ferrol’s clandestine affairs; but then, of a man’s surreptitious amours, no one does know anything unless they get in the papers, where they are so generally befuddled that the culprit himself would not recognize them.

Then, too, it may be that Ferrol was hardly the kind of a chap to go in for the illicit. To me he had represented a reunion of attributes which I have never found out of England, and not often there—that of smartness and scholarship combined. He knew the world, possibly the devil, but certainly the literature of India which he read, not in the Clarendon Press translations, but in the original. His scholarship did not stop there. He had produced a work which had gained for him the respect of European Orientalists. It was a commentary on the Soûtras of Patandgali.

To a man of that caliber the clandestine and the surreptitious are usually vulgar, and always inane. Yet, then, in the hearts of the best what abysses there may be! There are men, as there are women, dwelling on the uplands of life who, in spite of the contrast, perhaps because of the contrast, are seized by absolute nostalgias for mud.

Even so, concerning that skirt I had my doubts. Besides, it was yet to be shown that it had rustled from Ferrol’s rooms. Of one thing, of course, I was certain. It did not belong to Miss Rivers.

That certainty, however, was not shared by Lady Massingbird. On the contrary. It was a visible enjoyment to her to assume that it could belong to no one else. But with these views only Lady Silverstairs agreed.

“There is no doubt of it,” declared that delightful little woman. “It must have been hers, unless, indeed”—and here she smiled, and, smiling, disclosed a glimpse of teeth as pretty and as keen as a kitten’s—“unless she happened to be flaunting it in a can-can at the Moulin Rouge. That would be so like her. Yes, wouldn’t it?”

In the ripple of laughter that ensued I got up to go. It did not seem that anything further could be added. Nor was there for a while. At the inquest nothing not already known was developed except that Simpson was an ass, and one equally meager item. This item was produced by Ferrol’s servant, who testified that for several days prior to the murder his master had seemed not quite easy. Asked how this condition had manifested itself, the man made the remarkable statement that Lord Ferrol had instructed him to pitch downstairs any one that he saw trying to get in.

The item, if meager, was suggestive. Taken in connection with the main episode, it became dramatic. It showed, or seemed to show, that Ferrol was anticipating, if not what actually occurred, at any rate, something sinister. Then, suddenly that something had come, and as suddenly had gone, leaving not a clew behind, leaving not even a trace, leaving no sign of its presence, no indication of a struggle, leaving nothing but a corpse on the floor, the eyes open, the mouth distorted, a human being choked out of life in a jiffy.

Scotland Yard had become very active. So, too, had the press. The latter dripped with the mystery. Everybody was bewitched by it. It had even the merit of interesting an exalted personage. Meanwhile, no suspicion of any kind rested on Miss Rivers, who, on the evening of the murder, had, with her retinue, descended on Paris at the Hôtel du Rhin. But though no suspicion attached to her, it was felt in Scotland Yard, and more agreeably still in exalted circles, that, because of the unexplained rupture of her engagement, she might, if she chose, possibly provide a clew.

But the matter was very delicate. For here was a young person, the Stars and Stripes wrapped all about her, who had done nothing save cease to be affianced to a man that was subsequently killed. The police could not approach her. Only diplomacy might. And then only diplomacy of a kind which British embassies lack; for where among them is the Metternich who, without violating every canon of decency, could presume to question the girl?

Nevertheless, it was felt that an effort should be made. That feeling, naturally enough, was induced, less by a desire for justice in the abstract, than by the hope that the damnable and haunting enigma of the mystery would be explained. In this, the exalted personage to whom I have referred was, as I afterward learned, as keen for a scent as the police.

Of that, at the time, I was ignorant, and so remained until there came a note from the duchess bidding me again to Hill Street, where I learned, not merely what had been going on, but of a triumph of diplomacy that had resulted.

The diplomat who had effected it was, together with a lot of other people, in Hill Street when I got there. He had, it then appeared, been chosen not by reason of any particular astuteness, but simply because he knew Miss Rivers rather well. This diplomat, whom I had met before, and originally in the arms of his nurse, was Lord Nevis, a son of the duchess, and as nice a looking boy as you ever saw.

At the moment he was gorging himself with sandwiches. But, presently, prodded by his mother, the fruits of his mission—already, as I discovered, displayed in high quarters—were produced.

“Well, you know,” he at last began, “Miss Rivers said that the reason—er—the reason why she broke with Ferrol was—er—that he was crazy, don’t you know. Yes. That’s what she told me. She said that he saw things.”

“Fancy that!” murmured the endearing Lady Massingbird.

“Well, not things, perhaps,” the young lord resumed; “but people; or, rather, a person. Ferrol, you know, had written a book about—about—”

“The Soûtras,” I suggested.

“Yes. Quite so. And this book made the people who believed in them rather nasty, or he said it did. Then he got from Benares a letter—where the dickens is that thing gone now?” the diplomat interrupted himself to ask, and, asking, burrowed in several pockets. “Oh, yes, here it is,” he added, extracting a bit of paper on which, seemingly, he had jotted hard words. “Yes, Ferrol got a letter from a yogi who signed himself Anagarika, saying that if, within a certain specified time, he did not make public retraction of the lies which he had printed concerning this—er—this system of philosophy I believe it is, if he did not do that he would be visited by the”—here the lad examined his notes again—“he would be visited by the parapoutra.”

“The what?” Lady Massingbird exclaimed.

“The parapoutra.”

“What is that?”

“Blessed if I know. But that is what would happen if he didn’t.”

“Do you know what it is?” Lady Silverstairs inquired of me.

I had not an idea. But though I am an ignorant brute, I saw no use in admitting it.

“Yes,” I modestly answered. “The parapoutra is the nameless shame.”

“What sort of a shame is that?”

“Oh,” I replied, “it is hardly a subject for the drawing-room.”

“It must be very chaste, then,” Lady Silverstairs joyously concluded, while the young lord ran on:

“Yes, that is what was to happen if he didn’t retract. Whether he got in a funk over it or not I don’t know, but shortly he began to see things. He told Miss Rivers that one night, on entering his library, he saw a man whose back was turned toward him seated at the table. The man was writing. Ferrol said that he could hear the quill squeak on the paper. He went forward to find out who he was, but when he got to him there was nobody.”

“What!” we all exclaimed.

“Yes, that is what he told Miss Rivers. He told her that when he got to the table the man broke like a bubble. That was his expression.”

“It is most unusual,” said the dear duchess, though whether she referred to the incident or to the simile or to both, she omitted to state.

“Ferrol told Miss Rivers,” Lord Nevis continued, “that of course he was rather rattled, but that he was absolutely flabbergasted when, on looking down on the paper which was there, he found written the name Anagarika.”

“Then he had written it himself,” the Lady Agatha indignantly interjected.

“I dare say. But he did not believe it. What he did believe was that it was written by that yogi and that he had seen him there and seen him vanish. When he told that to Miss Rivers and she saw that he was telling it in dead earnest she broke the engagement, and if I had been her I’ll be shot if I would not have done the same.”

“Is that all?” Mr. Yorke, who had been ambling about, soothingly inquired.

“What more would you have?” Lord Nevis retorted.

“You see,” Mr. Yorke answered, in his consoling way, “it doesn’t quite explain—now, does it?—how Ferrol came to be strangled.”

Lord Nevis helped himself to a liquor. “No, it doesn’t. And when I told them at Sandringham about it he said that he didn’t like the looks of it all.”

“It is most unusual!” the duchess repeated. “Most!”

On this occasion I quite agreed with her, and presently in the general conversation which ensued, after telling her so, I got away.

Sut the mystery accompanied me. It followed me through Berkeley Square, through the lovely quiet of the spacious street. Then, unconsciously, such knowledge as I had once had of the Patandjali Soûtras emerged from some one of memory’s ablated cells. I recalled that these Soûtras taught of union with the supersensible, and of the supernatural powers which that union confer. I remembered that among other things they taught how the devout may exteriorize themselves from the body, project themselves through space, materialize partially or wholly, appear and disappear at will.

Tenets such as these are to the Occidental just so much nonsense. But is it not, I reflected, a beneficent Providence that has enabled us to despise whatever we do not understand? Then, too, may it not be that there are possibilities to which we are blind? May it not be that there are forces of which we know nothing, but which subtler intellects have grasped? May it not be that with those forces there are powers of which we know less, but of which acuter minds make use? May it not be as we learned—or should have learned at school—that everything is possible? And granting these forces and powers and the possibilities of them, might it not be that, among the apes and the peacocks in a grove of the sacred temple at Benares, a yogi was now, perhaps, recovering from a catalepsy, self-induced, during which his entity, exteriorized, had crossed the seas, crouched in that room of Ferrol’s, waited for him and strangled him there?

If everything be possible, that is possible, also. If not, then there is, I concluded, but one other solution. The threat of the parapoutra, the meaning of which Ferrol necessarily knew, may have so affected him that he imagined the presence of the yogi, really believed that he had seen him, and then, still more affected by the hallucination and affected more greatly yet by the rupture of his engagement, had, in an access of desperation, throttled himself.

At the inquest Simpson had denied that such a thing was feasible. But it is feasible. It is a form of suicide of which the old galley slaves and a few modern actors know the art. Histrionically, it is utilized to cause the appearance of suffocation which it produces and which is effected by swallowing the tip of the tongue.

It is that, perhaps, which Ferrol had done. Simpson had testified that death was due to heart failure, superinduced by compression of the carotid artery. Even so, the diagnosis would be the same. But where is the physician, in or out the witness box, who does not like to air a phrase, particularly when there is no one to refute him?

In this instance a layman could have refuted that ass. Heart failure is not induced by compression of the carotid artery. Only narcosis is. Heart failure may of course occur, but, in that event, it is merely coincidental. Yet, assuming that in Ferrol’s case it had occurred, what could have caused it? What but fright? What but the sinister and sudden return of the intangible something which he had once seen break like a bubble before his eyes—what but Anagarika abruptly clutching and gibbering at his throat?

Such an adventure might, I thought, induce heart failure in me, and, if in me, why not in Ferrol? The hypothesis was so spacious that I luxuriated in it. It was also so picturesque that I at once gave it preference over the alternate theory of suicide. It was so unusual, too, that I determined, when I got the chance, to set it before the duchess and, while I was at it, to suggest to her that the rustle of the skirt on the stair had come from the robe of a priest of Siva.

But, when at last the opportunity arrived, the duchess rather took the wind out of my sails by announcing her son’s engagement to Miss Rivers and declining to discuss the death of Ferrol any more.

Fortunately, or, more exactly, as luck would have it, unfortunately for me, Lady Silverstairs was less reluctant. Sometime later I found myself next to her at dinner. During the initial courses I unfolded the beauties of my hypothesis which, in the interim, I had had the leisure to elaborate and to which she was good enough to listen. But when I got into occultism and pictured Anagarika floating over the seas, filtering into Ferrol’s rooms and finishing him there, she smiled, providing as she did so, glimpses of teeth perfect enough to make a saint envious, not of her husband, but, on the contrary, of any remplaçant the poor devil might have.

“Perhaps you don’t believe in yogis,” I remarked, in answer to that smile.

“I believe that two and two make four,” the delightful woman replied. “I believe that if one yogi could do all that, it would not require more than a rabble of them to take British rule by the ear and conduct it out of India. Did that ever occur to you? No. Did it?”

“It occurs to me,” I answered, “that argument is agreeable, but futile, with a woman who talks like Solomon and looks like a seraph. But,” I added, “if my explanation explains nothing, Ferrol must have killed himself. In which case, whose was the skirt?”

Lady Silverstairs nibbled at a strawberry and shook her pretty head. “Ferrol did not kill himself,” she presently announced. “The skirt, I am told, belonged to a woman who was in his rooms that night.”

“A demi-rep?”

“Oh, dear me, no. A woman like the rest of us.”

“But,” I objected, “surely it is not supposed that a woman of that kind would act like a wildcat? Such things are not done in Mayfair.”

Again there were glimpses of those teeth. But this time my delightful compatriot laughed.

“What isn’t done?” she asked. “Or, rather, tell me what is not done? Half the peerage is on the the way to the divorce court and the other half ought to be.”

To this I hastened to agree. “Of course, there are everywhere—breaches of decorum, shall I say? But between bagatelles of that kind, and doing people up, there is a margin, don’t you think?”

But here Lady Silverstairs’ attention was claimed by a neighbor. When at last she got back at me it was with the same angelic smile.

“From what I hear,” she resumed, “I fancy that the woman in the case had expected to be Lady Ferrol. I fancy, too, that she first frightened Miss Rivers into breaking the engagement and then, disappointed in an effort to get Ferrol to renew an anterior pledge, lost her temper and he his life. That is the idea, though as yet the proofs are not in. But meanwhile—entre nous n’est ce-pas?—the lady is under surveillance. To-morrow, the day after, to-night, it may be, she will be arrested and we will all assist at the trial.”

“How disgusting!” I exclaimed.

“Why disgusting? Don’t you care for trials?”

“Oh, it isn’t that,” I answered. “But all this eliminates my hypotheses, exiles the occult and dismisses the picturesque. It is that which is disgusting. But permit me. You forget, do you not, that Miss Rivers gave as her reason for breaking the engagement that Ferrol saw things and—”

“Precisely,” my fair compatriot interrupted. “And so does she. And knows a good one, too, when she is about it. She did not dillydally much, now, did she, about snapping Nevis up?”

“After all,” I rejoined, “it is nobody’s business but her own why she broke with Ferrol. But if she invented that beautiful story about Anagarika she has an imagination to beat the band. Though, on the other hand,” I added, “Ferrol, on receipt of some letter from Benares, may have told her what those chaps out there are able to do, and what he advanced theoretically she may have accepted as fact.”

“Oh, as for that, she is great at accepting. It has been one man after the other ever since she got here. But, now that you remind me, that is pretty much the idea that they have at Sandringham.”

“Well, then,” I replied, “if that is the inside of it I do wish you would tell the duchess. It would seem to her so unusual.”

“But I have told her.”

“And what did she say?”

“Nothing. She had heard it before and looked upon it as the most natural in the world.”

“There is nothing commonplace about her, is there?” I exclaimed.

But immediately there was a move. Our hostess was rising. As I got from my chair I was conscious of a sense of loss. Under the table Anagarika lay, pitched there by inside information. In lieu of the splendid possibilities he had evoked I had an inkling of a stupid crime. The exchange was not compensatory. I regarded it as a swindle—as worse yet, a nameless shame.

The Noose Matrimonial

“Mr. Jones, mem, is down stairs, and your aunt and your father. Your father, mem, he has been here three times.”

It was Harriet, Marie’s maid, talking vainly through the door.

Marie turned on a pillow and carefully, as though engaged in a matter of great importance, made with a hairpin little punctures in it. The room was big and bright. From without there mounted the rumble of Fifth avenue.

The puncturing of the pillow continued. There was a square, quite even, which she completed, and into which she stuck, one by one, a row of dots. In the middle she planted the hairpin, left it there and turned again.

Because of the silks with which the bed was covered it looked like a garden, and in it the girl resembled a flower, a rose chimerically fair. Her purple eyes were sultry, her scarlet mouth was moist, the red tangles of her hair made a burnous of flame, her fingers glowed and her wrists were such as those on which, in days gone by, falcons alighted and kisses fell.

She patted a yawn and interrogated a clock. It was not yet noon, but she had fancied it earlier. Pushing the silks aside, she got from the bed to the bath. Before the latter was a mirror. For a moment, the point of her tongue just visible, she looked herself up and down. Then absently, her thoughts on other things, she perfumed the water and hid herself there.

The chill aroused her. Presently, without haste, she began to dress. The ceremony was one which she always accomplished alone. The presence of her maid annoyed her exceedingly, and, though this morning differed from all others, it was not until she had her hat on that she opened a door and called:

“Harriet!”

“Yes, mem.” The maid entered, prim as a Puritan Sunday. “They are waiting for you, mem. Your father⸺”

Marie interrupted her. “Put those things in the bag and give it to Harris with the boxes. Are they packed? How do I look? Go down and tell Mr. Usher I am coming. When did my father get here? This morning?”

“Yes, mem.” The woman nodded and turned.

Marie went back to the mirror. Her dress was of cloth, light violet. It had fur effects that were repeated on her hat. In spite of her coloring, or, perhaps, because of it, it became her. And now, as she looked, she bent forward and kissed herself in the glass.

“Good-bye, Marie.”

She looked about the room. On a mantel were some photographs.

“Good-bye, everybody.”

Her voice was contralto. As she spoke she smiled and showed her teeth. They were small, slightly uneven, and semi-transparent.

On the stair beyond was a man. He looked as though he had seen worse days and never intended to see them again.

“I was coming for you,” he began. “I must speak to you.”

Marie interrupted him as she had her maid. “I expected you last night. How do you like my hat? Have you seen Paul?”

From an adjoining room a clergyman issued. He was in full canonicals. The girl went back a step, stretched a hand, showed her teeth and the point of her tongue.

“I am Miss Mermex.”

“For but a brief while now,” the clergyman answered.

“This is my father,” she added.

“I am just in town,” Mr. Mermex announced. “I got here an hour ago from San Francisco. I⸺”

Marie interrupted him again. She gave him a slight shove, which he obeyed, and down the stair all three went.

In the wide hall below people straggled from the drawing-room to greet her. There was her aunt, Mrs. Metuchen, a little old frump. There was her immediate husband, Paul Usher. There was Mrs. Usher, his mother. There were the Enevers, society folk of the toppest notch. There was also Alphabet Jones, a man of polite letters.

Mrs. Usher’s costume indicated mourning, Mrs. Metuchen’s the Flood, and Mrs. Enever’s the Rue de la Paix. Marie, fair as an angel, yet, of course, much better dressed, beamed on them all.

Usher took her hand and kissed it. Had he not been a broker you would have suspected him of it. Marie, smiling still, showed again the point of her tongue. It was like a little piece of watermelon. Meanwhile, everybody was talking to her; Mrs. Metuchen very shrilly. Mrs. Usher approached, gratified her with a frosty caress, and stepped gingerly away.

“Many happy returns,” Jones murmured, seductively.

“Gracious!” Mrs. Enever exclaimed. “Gracious!” she repeated, delightedly. “What a congratulation to a bride!”

“She reminds me,” Mrs. Usher whispered, “of a beautiful animal. But I have found it well not to be too precipitate.”

“Gracious! I should hope so!”

“Marie,” began Mr. Mermex. He had got near his daughter again, but Mrs. Enever’s husband was talking to her. The girl interrupted them both.

“Suppose we go in.”

The group parted. Through it, into the drawing-room, the girl passed, the clergyman following, the others at his heels. At one end, between the windows, two cushions had been placed. The clergyman got behind them, his back to the wall, and, fumbling in his skirt, produced a book. At once he assumed an attitude that was amiably austere.

“Dearly beloved, we are gathered together here⸺” Before him the bride and groom were standing. The others, distributed as for a photograph, seemed reverently disposed. Mr. Mermex alone was restless, and, in a moment, as the opening exordium concluded with the mandate, “If any man can show just cause why these two persons may not be lawfully joined⸺” he raised a hand, his mouth opened, something trembled on his tongue. But, save Marie, who turned, smilling still, no one noticed.

“I require and charge you both, as you will answer at the dreadful day of judgment.”

Marie had turned again. She was listening now devoutly. Into her sultry eyes there had entered an expression almost saintlike. From her moist mouth the smile had gone.

“Paul, wilt thou take this woman⸺”

The questions continued. At the demand, “Who giveth,” Mr. Mermex made a gesture. Though vague, it sufficed. The promises were exchanged. The troth was plighted. Bride and groom knelt and arose again.

“Those whom God hath joined,” the cleric continued, and, mumbling the phrases that follow, concluded with the finishing “Amen.”

“Let me congratulate you, Mrs. Usher.”

Abruptly the man of God had disappeared. It was the man of the world who was speaking now. Then, extending his hand to the husband, he was about to ask for the paper which the Bureau of Vital Statistics exacts, but Mr. Mermex gave him no time. He had the groom by the sleeve.

“I want to speak to you.”

“What about?” Usher asked.

“Come from here and I’ll tell you.”

With a hand still on that sleeve the father led the son-in-law from the room. In a moment the clergyman rustled and vanished. Marie had seated herself, Enever on one side, Mrs. Metuchen on the other.

Across the room Mrs. Usher mère had also seated herself. Mrs. Enever and Jones were sharing the charm of her talk.

“It is incredible,” she was announcing to both from behind a fan, “but I am not sure that anyone knows my son’s wife, that anyone knows her father, either.”

“Gracious!” Mrs. Enever exclaimed. “That is such an advantage, isn’t it? Just look at the Menemons! When they first appeared I heard people saying, ‘Shall we receive them?’ In no time those very same people were asking, ‘Will they receive us?’”

“It may be that I am censorious,” the groom’s mother continued, expansively. “It may be, though it is a fault which I try to guard against. But I am not precipitate, and that, I fear, Paul is. You will not believe me when I tell you that he has not known his wife eight weeks.”

“Gracious! I thought they had made mud pies together. Perhaps they will. Matrimony, don’t you think, is just full of adventure?”

“And I need not tell you,” Mrs. Usher added, “how grateful I am to the dispensation of Providence which, in putting me in mourning, relieved me of asking people here to-day. So, while there is that for which I am thankful, there is also that which perturbs. Do you not agree with me, Mr. Jones?”

“Entirely, Mrs. Usher. Every silver lining has its cloud.” The novelist was about to add further novelties, but Marie beckoned to him. He crossed the room.

“Where is Paul?” the girl asked.

“Playing billiards with your father, I fancy. In Latin countries it is customary for a bride to be taken aside by her mother. Here it is becoming fashionable for a father to disappear with the groom. But don’t let it worry you. Disappearances are deceptives.”

In the doorway the butler loomed.

“Harris,” the bride called, “is the carriage here? Fetch me a cup of bouillon.” She turned to the others. “It is after one. The ship sails at two. But you will all stop and lunch with my father, won’t you? Mr. Jones, would you mind very much telling Paul that the carriage is here?”

“It is so unusual,” said Mrs. Usher mère, “for young people to sail for the tropics on their wedding day. Does it not seem unusual to you, also, dear Mrs. Metuchen?”

“Gracious!” Mrs. Enever exclaimed. “When I was married I took my husband to Iceland.”

The butler reappeared, preceding a footman who carried a tray, on which there were little cups.

Marie took one. So also did the dowager. As the servants were leaving, Jones, followed by Usher, reentered the room.

“Before we go, Paul, don’t you want some bouillon?” Marie asked.

But either he did not hear or else he did not heed. “Mother,” he said, “bring Mrs. Enever and come.”

Mrs. Usher, who was drinking, lowered her cup. “We are to lunch here after you and Marie are gone.”

“Marie and I are not going anywhere.”

As he spoke he looked at his bride, and as he looked the cup which she held fell from her hand, spilling over her dress, and then to the floor, where it broke, musically, after the fashion of Sèvres.

Her eyes followed it meditatively. When, presently, she lifted them, the front door had opened and closed. Usher had gone.

“What is the meaning of this?” demanded the dowager. She turned to Mrs. Metuchen, from her to Mrs. Enever, then to Jones.

“What is the meaning of this?” she repeated. This time she addressed the girl.

Marie nodded, tried to smile, tried, perhaps, to speak. The effort, though, must have been too great. She dropped forward on her face.

Mrs. Metuchen made a dive at the girl. But almost immediately the latter straightened herself.

From without there came a ring.

“Gracious!” exclaimed Mrs. Enever. “It is like a scene in a play.”

Jones blinked appreciatively. “It is better. This is real drama in real life.”

“But, gracious! what do you suppose⸺?”

Jones, however, had no time to waste on Mrs. Enever. The groom’s mother, with the air of a Gorgon, was promenading toward the door. She seemed smitten by that disease which pathology catalogues as noli me tangere. Her eyes were open to their widest extent, her mouth shut very tight. But Jones was not afraid.

“You’d best wait a moment, Mrs. Usher; there is a newspaper man in the hall.”

But the lady herself was not afraid. Her promenade across the room continued, rigidly, almost mechanically, perhaps pleasurably. In a moment she, too, had gone.

Jones turned to the bride. Apparently now she had wholly recovered. She looked precisely as she had five minutes before, as pretty as she could stick, a Venus in her teens. Mrs. Metuchen, talking as though the tongue would fall from her mouth, was standing on one side of her. Mrs. Enever, doing her best to get a word in edgewise, was standing on the other. Though the one was old and the other young, conjointly they set her off.

Jones was not permitted to stare at her undisturbed. Enever had him by the arm.

“If you love Mammon and abhor righteousness,” the latter was muttering, “and even if you don’t,” he interrupted himself to add, “tell me what all this mystery is about.”

There are men who can’t say, “I don’t know.” It sounds too flat. Jones was one of them. Pontifically, in his deepest note, he replied, “Mystery, dear boy, exists only in the dictionary. There is no such thing. But there is ignorance, and that is very fertile. The less we know the more we believe. Now, if you want a guess⸺” and drawing Enever nearer he whispered in his ear.

Enever shook him off. “Nonsense!” he sputtered.

“Well, perhaps,” Jones, with silken sweetness, answered, “perhaps it is nonsense; but then, you see, we have been exchanging ideas.”

The shot might have told, yet it lacked the time. Before it could hit, there was Mr. Mermex.

“Archibald,” chuckled Mrs. Metuchen, “look at your work! You have killed your daughter, you⸺”

Marie interrupted her. She had risen. “You might better have stayed in Frisco, I think. Don’t you?” she added, longly. As she spoke, she smiled. “And just look at my dress! I am dripping with soup.”

Brushing her father aside, leisurely, without haste, smiling still, she crossed the room and left it.

“There goes a dream in lilac,” Jones confided to Enever.

“One from which Usher appears to have awakened.”

“The more fool he, then.”

Enever had no chance to reply. His wife sailed up to him and sailed him away.

Mrs. Metuchen had evaporated. Jones and Mr. Mermex were alone.

The latter coughed. “You are a literary man, I believe?”

“Oh, no. I write little things for the magazines. There is nothing literary in that.”

To this Mr. Mermex assented, but absently. It was evident that he was sparring for wind. “At least, you are a friend of these people, a friend also of my daughter; and here I have few. Will you give me a moment?”

“The plot thickens,” Jones reflected. “He is going to use me for a sewer.”

“Now,” Mr. Mermex continued, “when you met my daughter last summer, did it occur to you to ask her where she had been?”

“But, my dear sir, a man of sense never asks a lady where she has been. He asks where she is going.”

“No doubt. Even otherwise Marie would not have told. Explanations are not her weakness. But that is a detail. She had just left Sioux Falls.”

“Ah!” In the rug which Jones had been studying abruptly understanding dawned. An entire panorama unrolled—the cat, the bag, the key to the whole situation. “Was that what you told Usher?” he asked.

Mr. Mermex nodded.

“But permit me, why, of all other moments, did you choose the one which you took?”

“Why, indeed! I had to take what I could get. I only reached here an hour ago.”

“Of course. Then, too, postage is dear and telegraphing expensive; yet I can’t help thinking, since the matter appears to have weighed on your conscience, that a little extravagance⸺”

The father coughed again. “There is the point. Marie wrote me that she was to marry Usher. I wrote her to go ahead. On the train this morning I met the beast from whom I thought she was free. He told me that he had never been served, that the divorce was invalid, that he intended to rip it up—all of which I had to tell Usher, and when I did, you saw what occurred. He reasoned, I suppose, that if Number One got at him he would be in for damages, and heavy ones, too. Don’t you think so?”

“Really, the processes of Usher’s reasoning exceed my powers of imagination. If your supposition be correct, certainly his commercial instinct is beautifully developed. But personally I regard it as a great mistake to neglect pleasure for business.”

“Now,” said Mr. Mermex, “there is a reporter out there. What shall I say to him? There is no use keeping him waiting.”

“None at all. Particularly as in all probability he enjoys it. Tell him the reverse. Tell him it is a great mistake to neglect business for pleasure.”

“Quite so.”

The door-bell rang again.

“There is another of them, I suppose, and that reminds me, you will stop, won’t you, and have lunch with us?”

“No, thanks very much; but you might say to your daughter, with my compliments, that divorce is the mother-in-law of invention, and that I wish her again many happy returns.”

“You are very thoughtful of others,” a lady in lilac called from the adjoining room, “yet in the circumstances a trifle cynical, too.”

Jones picked up his hat. “I dare say, but then, you see, it is in thoughtfulness of others that cynicism begins.”

“Yes, indeed,” said a voice from the doorway, “let us think of ourselves. There,” Usher continued, as he entered where they stood, “I have been off reconnoitering. The divorce is all right. The forces centripetal and centrifugal couldn’t touch it. Marie, where are you?”

From the adjoining room the bride strolled—a festival of beauty in the festival of life.

With a look cannibalistic in its longing to eat her, Usher added, “My dear, we have lost the boat.”

The girl’s moist lips, parting in a smile, disclosed the point of her tongue. “Then can’t we,” she inquired, with an air of innocence which was simply seraphic, “can’t we manage to find a train?”

“Any port in a honeymoon,” Usher answered. “Let’s be off at once.”

“My blessing on you both,” cried Mr. Mermex.

“’Twas ever thus,” said Jones. “Woman proposes and a poor devil accepts. For such is the noose matrimonial.”

The Plot

Has the Figaro come yet?”

It was at Nice, in the reading room of a cosmopolitan club. A little before, I had dined on dishes that a poet had prepared. Now, for after course, and although I had a novel under my arm, I wanted to look at a paper.

“Pardon, monsieur,” said the servant to whom I had spoken. “Behold a gentleman who is reading it.”

I had beheld the gentleman before. That morning I had seen him on the Promenade des Anglais, and that afternoon I had seen him again in this club, where I had heard him talking over the green baize at baccarat. He was a pleasant-looking chap in Saville Row clothes, which he wore with a sort of studied negligence. He wore also a monocle, and his voice was deeply Belgravian.

In that voice he addressed me: “You are asking for the Figaro. Let me relinquish it to you.”

As he spoke, he got up from a chair in which he had been seated, and approached me, the paper in his hand.

In my own hand was the novel, a story by Eric Hereward, which I put on the table before us.

He glanced at the book. “Do you find it interesting?”

“I have not opened it,” I answered.

Before he could say more—that is, if he had intended to—Spencer Poole, an Englishman whom I had long known, sauntered up and joined us.

“If this is a private conversation,” he threw out, “I should like to hear it. Otherwise, I will go away.”

“You may,” I told him. “We were talking opiates.”

“Let us all go,” Poole affably resumed. “There are a thousand louis in the bank. Don’t you want some of them? I know I do.”

“I would rather not add to them,” I remarked.

But already Poole had turned, the other man with him, and I followed them into an adjoining room, where, about a long, oval table that was colored with bank notes, with hillocks of gold, with patches of cards, a crowd of members were gaming.

The room, saturated with tobacco smoke, resounded with brief exclamations, with the announcement of points. Fronting it, two windows that reached to the floor opened on a balcony and the night.

Idly, after a moment, I passed through one of them. A chair stretched its arms to me. Above were the stars, and beyond, on the inky syrup of the Mediterranean, a warship rode. The vessel was strung with lights, and from it, faintly over the waters, a tinkle of music came.

“You don’t play?”

I turned. The man who had offered me the Figaro was drawing a chair beside me.

“You see,” I said, “it seems to me that there is but one thing stupider than winning money you have not earned, and that is losing it.”

He adjusted his monocle. “What I like is the hazard of it. Yet is there such a thing as hazard? I hardly think so.”

He paused, got out a gold case, offered it, and, on my declining, extracted a cigarette, lit it, and, a bit ponderously, inquired whether I believed in fate.

“Not after dinner,” I told him. Ordinarily I would have said nothing of the kind, but I divined that he wanted to use me for a sewer, and, at the moment, I did not care to be so employed. Yet, civility prompting, I added: “Why do you ask?”

“Because I fancy that anyone who really thinks—so few people do think—must believe that somewhere—beyond, above, yet about us—there is a power that knows neither mercy nor wrath, but that compels every cause, great or small, to work out its inevitable results.”

“Let me,” I interrupted, “translate you if I may. As you mete it to others, so shall it be measured unto you.”

“Precisely. You at least believe in that?”

“Whether I have dined or not, I do.”

“I am glad to hear you say so. I have such a curious case in point. Would it bore you if I run it over?”

I felt that it would, but I assured him to the contrary, and for surcease let my thoughts wander among the stars. When they returned to earth, or, more exactly, to the balcony, he was telling of a maiden’s beauty:

“Fancy a lily that for perfume has a heart, and you may perhaps see Janet Mar as I saw her when, for her perdition, she came to Stratton. In my life I have seen nothing fairer. Her hair was a turban of gold, her eyes were pools of purple, her features were those of a Psyche on a fan, and she conveyed just that suggestion of unmateriality that the old masters gave to figures whom they represented as floating off the canvas into space. A painter would have admired her for what she expressed, a poet would have loved her for what she was.

“That, from the ambush where it lurked, fate should have sprung and felled a human flower such as she is explicable only on a theory that I will set before you. But that the point of it may be clearer, other pictures must be shown, and primarily that of her brother, who was her twin, and who worshiped her as only a twin brother could worship a sister so adorably constructed, and so constructed to be adored.

“Together they completed one another. What was fragile in her he made up in strength; what was material in him, her spirituality attenuated. Had you not known they were brother and sister you would have said: ‘There is the ideal couple!’ In some former life perhaps they were.”

“What!” I exclaimed.

“Well, yes, why not?” my companion rejoined. “For if we believe in fate, it is difficult not to believe that we have been here before. Nothing else explains the inequitable inequalities of life. Nothing else explains why some are rich and some are poor; why some are wise and many are not; why some are strong and others weak. Nothing else can give the reason of our joys and sorrows. As in former days, we have meted it to others, so now is it measured unto us.

“Yet, of course, the theory is, I admit, heretical, and if I offer it, it is because it is the one hypothesis that frames this girl. Without it, she would present but a fair portrait smeared, and wantonly smeared, with mud and with blood.

“But now, to fill the picture in, a detail is necessary. When Janet and her Brother Hubert came to Stratton, which, as you may know, is a village in Surrey, they were in mourning for their father, who but recently had left them, and who had left them, moreover, with means so slender that Janet gave lessons and Hubert wrote.

“If there are two more beggarly ways of making a living, I have yet to hear of them. Tennyson, I believe, got a guinea a word. For five minutes’ instruction De Reszke, I understand, gets as much. But there has been but one Tennyson—though there are two De Reszkes. For the horde of other teachers and other writers, rates fall sheerly from relative munificence to absolute minims. Sometimes they lack even that.

“Sometimes Janet and Hubert supped on dry bread. Sometimes they had cheese with it. But they knew—what epicures rarely do know—that Epicurus never had more and Caesar frequently less. They were poor, but they were young, and it is a form of genius to be that. Besides, they worked, and I always pity those who do not, though, of course, we both know people who pity those that do. But am I wearying you?”

The question reminded me of Doctor Johnson, who, asked by Boswell how he would feel if he were alone in a tower with a baby, replied that he could not be more vilely distressed than he was. But I am less brave than Johnson, and I hope more polite. As a consequence, I lied. Yet obviously my companion did not expect me to do otherwise. He accepted the lie for what it was not worth, and ran on at once:

“You have now, then, not the frame—that will come in a moment—but the picture. That is, you see that while Hubert hacked in Fleet Street, Janet toiled at home; or, more exactly—and what is worse—in the homes of other people. To children who would never succeed in more than hiccuping French, she tried to impart the proper façon de parler. With others, who had as much taste for music as those who detest mathematics have for algebra, she connived in the murder of Chopin. And for what? In the States a scullion would have been better paid.

“But everything happens because it has to happen. In the course of the lessons, she saw that which she mistook for the recompense. She saw the splendor of splendors, the face and flaming wings of Love.”

“He is becoming lyrical,” I tormentedly reflected, and felt, if possible, more Johnsonian than before. To be alone with a baby is bad, but to be alone with a bore is bitter. For relief, I tried to pretend to myself that I was not there. I even succeeded, I think, for for a minute or two I lost him. When I caught up with him again he was playing another air:

“That was, I think, the case with Janet. She had never loved before, and, now that she did love, the universe became concentrated in this individual who to her was the Unique. To Hubert he was a very ordinary person, the form and substance of that curious thing that is called Antipathy. He said as much and more—and might have saved his breath, for Janet was madly in love with this man, who, at the time, was quite mad about her.

“But madmen have lucid intervals. I have told you of Janet’s beauty; I have told you, too, of her poverty. The one was a charm, the other a douche. Beauty her lover wanted, but also he needed coin. To give the due to the devil, who usually takes it, I have no doubt that in the first fevers, which are so contagious, he meant well by the girl; but to certain temperaments the menace of moneyless matrimony is, perhaps, a febrifuge. Do you not agree with me? Do you not agree, rather, that circumstances alter kisses?”

“Yes,” I replied. “Particularly reduced circumstances.”

“Precisely, and there you have what dramatists call the central situation—a delicious girl wildly in love with a brute whom she considered an angel. The fellow had a keep of his own, and little or nothing to keep it up on—a gaunt, gloomy Tudor affair which had come down to him, and which, unless repaired, would come down on him. Around and about were secular trees that made it all the gloomier. A moment ago I mentioned Tennyson. Somewhere he tells of ‘the moan of doves in immemorial elms.’ That line will give you the place.”

“I don’t want it,” I threw in.

“No, and you will want it less when I tell you more. Where was I?”

“In the central situation.”

“Ah, yes. Well, now enters the other woman, the widow of an astronomer who had died of sunstroke. Her grief for his death, which, if abrupt, was not disagreeably paradoxical, could not have been excessive. In any event, such as it may have been, it was at least assuaged by the fortune that he left her.”

“And which,” I hazarded, “appealed to the brute.”

My companion gestured. “And which, as you say, appealed to Lord Cullen. Now, you will think, we are in the thick of it. Wait a second and you will find it gets thicker. For at the moment—that is, when the blue eyes of the widow’s check book first entranced this man—Janet was unconscious that he was looking into other eyes than her own.

“Not so the widow. She was discerning possibilities in Cullen, who, instead of following the traditions of his caste, and marrying a Gayety girl, had become engaged to a governess. But, if discerning, she was decent, which, of course, the brute understood, or, rather, he realized that no decent woman, however discerning, would consider a man who was the property of another.

“The point with him, therefore, as you may see, was to fight free of Janet and then lay siege to that check book. Already mobilization had been secretly begun. Then came the call to arms, a bugle blast blown at Janet.

“Cullen told her that with him everything was going to the devil, that he could barely maintain a servant. But poverty had no terrors for this girl, who supped, when sup she did, on a crust, and she answered him with smiles.

“Now, however perverse a cad may be, he cannot beat down a dog simply because it loves him. There are limits even to human turpitude. Then, too, I have never known a man, good, bad, or indifferent, who would not prefer to brave mythical redskins, than face a woman’s tears. Janet had shed no tears as yet, or, if she had, they were but tears of joy. The fanfare had been so much music to her.

“Seeing which, Cullen varied his tactics. He defiled into his keep, and from that stronghold wrote Janet a dozen pages, pages in which sordidness struggled with grammar, pages that one word would have covered, pages that said only “Finis.” Only that! Only the trumpet’s note that heralds an eternal silence.”

After that fine phrase, which I had heard before, my companion stopped to light another cigarette. Then at once he was off again:

“I was not with Cullen when he committed that crime, and I cannot tell you how he felt; but I may tell you that when I heard of it I felt that there was no man living whom I envied less. Yet even now I must omit to judge him. We are all of us strangers to one another; not infrequently we are strangers to ourselves. The motives of human actions are not always for human ken. Because of the fate prepared for him, it may be that, whether Cullen, wished to or not, he was impelled to act as he did.”

“Yes,” I told my companion. I no longer felt like a boor with a baby or even with a bore; he had got me at last. “Yes, for among all our uncertainties, this perhaps alone is certain—never do useless events occur.”

“Never,” he repeated, “no matter how useless, in our blindness, the events may seem to us. And that fact, while it applies to Cullen, applies also to Janet. I was not with her, nor, poor child, was anyone with her when she got that infamous letter; yet had all the world been with her, she still would have been alone. In the great crises of the soul, every one is, and Janet was so thoroughly alone that she could not bear it. When at last her brother found her, she had gone.”

“Gone?”

“With a hatpin she had run herself through that aching heart of hers, which, because of the ache, she well knew where to pierce.”

At this, I shifted in my chair, and, whether because of the night air or the story, or both, I shivered. Through the window behind me drifted the hum of talk. From beyond, over the inky syrup, the music from the warship came.

“Beside her was Cullen’s infamy, and beside that, one line: ‘I forgive him, and may God forgive me.’ ”

“And Hubert,” I asked, “was he as generous?”

“Would you have been?”

“You see,” I answered, “when ignorant people are injured, they blame others; the wise blame themselves; the evolved blame no one.”

“Quite so—when the injury is personal. But if it affected someone for whom you deeply cared, would you not then take reprisals? It is a case of conscience, no doubt. Yet, in any event, Hubert did, or at least attempted to. He secured a pistol, and went straight to Cullen, whom he found seated beneath one of his immemorial elms, and occupied, if you please, with a copy of Punch. At sight of Hubert, at sight, rather, of the menace of him, he sprang up. Point-blank, Hubert fired. Cullen dropped, and Hubert, turning the pistol, killed himself.”

“Killed himself also!” I exclaimed.

“No, not also. Cullen was not touched, or but barely touched. The bullet singed the hair above an ear, and lodged itself in the elm. In the elm, mind you, not in Cullen. But the imminence of death, combined with the unlordliness of the lord, did, at the moment, for him. He fainted and toppled over. It was then that Hubert, fancying him dead, turned the pistol on himself. What do you think of it?”

“What do I think of it?” I repeated. “I think that the dice of destiny were strangely cogged. It was Cullen who should have died, Cullen only. What had Janet done that she should have been forced to kill herself? What had Hubert done to have a similar fate?”

My companion raised a hand. “How do I know what they had done? All I know is that Cullen appeared to have wronged them.”

“Appeared to!” I exclaimed. “That seems a bit colorless.”

My companion readjusted his monocle. “Perhaps. But not from the standpoint of anterior lives. According to the theory of it, we none of us can be injured except by those who embody our past. Whatever we suffer comes from there. People who harm us are but puppets come to claim such debts as we ourselves have incurred. Apparently Cullen was but an ordinary brute; actually he may have been the hand of fate.”

“Not a very clean one, then,” I had to protest. “Fate, I think, might have deodorized him.”

“It did,” my companion replied. “And there is the remarkable part of it. By the way, are you superstitious?”

“Oh,” I answered, “when the new year begins on the thirteenth, then, like every one else, I am apt to fear it may be unlucky. Otherwise, superstition seems to me the parody of faith. But why do you ask?”

“Because Cullen developed a curious dislike for the tree before which he had been shot at. The estate was entailed, and legally he had no right to lop so much as a branch. But he took the law in his own hands. While he was about it, he took an ax. He might as well have used a penknife. But Cullen, who had two deaths to his debit, was not to be balked by an elm. He bored a hole in it, and inserted an explosive. That explosive—”

My companion paused, leisurely lit a fresh cigarette, exhaled the smoke, considered me.

I prodded him. “Well?”

He nodded. “That explosive discharged the bullet that Hubert had fired, the bullet that had been intended for Cullen, but that, having missed him, had bided its time, there in the tree, until it could, and did, get at him.”

“You don’t mean—”

Again my companion nodded. “I do. I do mean it. The bullet went straight through his throat, and severed the carotid artery. Lord Cullen was dead. What do you say to that? Don’t you think it was fate?”

What I did think was that it seemed rather odd that I, who read the papers, had missed an account of a matter so unusual, and I was about to say as much when my companion stood up.

“I should much like to stop and talk it over with you,” he obligingly resumed. “But,” he added, indicating, as he spoke, the warship, “I am due on the Thunderer. They are having a dance there. Good night.”

Feeling that I had been having something of a dance myself, I turned and watched him go.

He passed through the open window into the room from which we had come, and, as he passed, I saw him stop and say a word to Spencer Poole.

A moment later I, too, got up, and entered the room, which, as before, resounded with the call of numbers, the announcement of points.

“Who was that chap?” I asked my friend.

But Poole, his eyes on the cards, did not immediately answer. Then absently he looked at me. “What chap?”

“The man that just spoke to you, the man who was with me in the reading room when you joined us.”

“Oh, that fellow? Why, I thought you knew him. That’s Eric Hereward, the novelist. Has he been rehearsing one of his plots to you? If so, I can sympathize. He did it to me.”

The Proper Thing

The street was empty, the night starless, the hour homicidal and serene. As the taxi flew up, Wentworth had the impression of lights extinguished, an impression which he at once revised. It was, he told himself, lights in the house adjoining that he had seen. He got out, paid the fare, ascended the steps. The cab turned. Across the street a cat cried. Beyond, afar and above, a train shone, rattled, vanished.

Wentworth opened the door. The hall was black. Feeling his way, he entered the drawing-room. That too was black. At the entrance was the button of the switch. He groped for it, then stopped. Though he could see nothing and had heard nothing, he had become conscious that he was not alone. There was someone else in the room. At the sudden apperception, his nerves, dominating his flesh, made it creep.

It was one of those moments in which the past surges. In a sort of retrograde vision a panorama unfolded in which, centrally, was Julianne, his wife, who, unaware of his return, was then asleep in her room above.

That morning, with the purchase of a villa by the sea in view, he had gone from New York to Boston where ordinarily the details of it would have detained him at least until the morrow. But the matter had been more speedily concluded than he had expected, and he had taken the night train back. The villa was on the North Shore, and shortly with Julianne he intended to return there for the summer, when guests would come, among others Gordon, a relative of Julianne, one whom she had latterly unearthed. Long before Wentworth had met him, as for that matter he met everybody who was worth it, but it was only recently, since the exhumation, that he had got to know and to like the man.

Now, as he stood in the darkness it was not Gordon that the vision presented but Julianne, and it was then that he felt his flesh creep. Whoever was in this room might already—

At that inhuman possibility he touched the button. With a regret that was to be eternal he wished he had not, wished rather as many do when it is too late, that he had done otherwise, that he had vacated the room, gone upstairs, given them time, himself too, only the few minutes in which any situation may be saved.

In the light which the button brought, he lost that chance. Beyond, behind a center table, looking tolerably strained and, as he afterward thought, equally stupid, there they stood.

In the unawaitedness of it, with a subconscious movement, he turned the light off. Then immediately he turned it on again. But now Gordon was firing away. “We saw you coming and—” It must have been a bit difficult but, with an attempt at a grin that twisted his face, he carried it off. “Rather a joke on you, eh?”

For a second Wentworth looked at the ceiling. It was charming. On it cupids sprawled. He did not see them. What he did see was that which in every spiritual crisis we all see—that he stood absolutely alone. He looked at the man and nodded.

“Yes, you have a rare sense of humor.”

From Gordon he turned to Julianne. She differed from the ordinary. On seeing her you had the impression of one of those mother-of-pearl sultanas that peer from the illuminated text of Persian script. Her voice was luscious. Wentworth loved it. He loved her beauty, her grace, the contour of her mouth that glowed with ardent life, her eyes that were light as blue water and yet large and profound. But most, it had been her heart that he had loved, that enigmatic heart of hers that had also its depths, depths hitherto unsounded. It was covered now, as she was, with what is ridiculously known as a saut-de-lit.

From the woman he turned again to the man. Gordon’s white neckcloth might have been better tied. Under his overcoat it showed loosely.

Already Wentworth had reconstructed it all; Gordon who had been about to go, Julianne who had accompanied him down, then the taxi, the alarm, the lights switched off, the wait, the suspense! Well, they had had enough of it, so too had he.

“Yes,” he repeated and mercifully dropped it there.

As he spoke he removed his hat. About the ears his hair was gray. He was nearly forty. Gordon was younger, more the woman’s man perhaps, but less fine than Wentworth, who had that air of extreme distinction which certain New Yorkers occasionally attain.

In removing his hat he approached the table behind which they stood and looked at Julianne again.

“That is a very pretty thing you have on,” he told her. “But a trifle thin perhaps. This is one of our nice, warm April nights when everybody catches cold. Better get something heavier, don’t you think?”

Beneath the flimsy frippery, that enigmatic heart of hers had been beating, beating, beating. She did not know what might happen. In circumstances not similar perhaps but cognate a woman seldom does know. Though usually a beautiful woman becomes aware that in her existence there is always something of the fairy tale. Now, in the rain of his calm, colorless words there was that reassurance which, au fond, she had expected. Her sultana air, momentarily disturbed, but momentarily only, returned. Her lips glowed, her eyes shone, she smiled, and lusciously she spoke:

“I will, dear.”

With those unique syllables which in a woman’s mouth are so fluid, she undulated, moved to the door, looked back. The hall engulfed her. On the marble there, the slight click-clack of her slippers sounded.

Wentworth turned to Gordon. “I haven’t seen an evening paper. How did the market go?”

But Gordon was not Julianne. He knew nothing of fairy tales. He had not found life a dream fulfilled. None the less there was a game to be played, and he played it.

“Well,” he threw out, “the best I can say for it is that it did not go sidewise.” Without transition he added, “I thought Julianne might be lonely, and I just looked in.” For a moment he hesitated, scrutinizing Wentworth’s face. It was quite blank. Then zealously he resumed, “But you must be tired. I’ll run. Good night.”

“Good night.”

Less thoroughly now than before Wentworth was again alone in this room which, fitted with things costly and futile, seemed to him bare. For a while at the table he stood occupied with that journey to the irreparable which is at once the quickest and the longest that any man can take. In considering things, he considered, too, his own attitude. In circumstances such as these he saw that another might have merely gone and, in going, omitted, technically at least, to condone. Or else he might have shot—yes, and shouted. Or again he might have beaten the man, abused the woman, thrown them both in the street. More barbarously still, he might have laughed and said, “Good God, sir, is it possible that you have been embracing this lady without being obliged to?”

One or another of these things a man might do, but not a civilized man or, more exactly perhaps, an evolved one, and Wentworth at least was that. The point did not detain him. What preoccupied him was the question of duty, the proper thing to do.

Opposite, across the room, hung an inferior daub that had been signed by a superior name. Absently he looked at it, and suddenly it counseled, reminding him that a prophet, discovering that his wife was in love with another man and that the other man was in love with her, had moved aside, got her a divorce, attended the wedding, given her away.

Wentworth was not Ruskin, and certainly Gordon was not Millais. But the procedure appealed to Wentworth to whom it seemed the only way in which he could rightly act.

He did not reach the decision at once or even as here summarized. It was the next day and after much mental wrestling that he attained it. Meanwhile he had inquired concerning his wife. With her Pekingese she had gone for a drive.

It was then high noon. Shortly, in one of those trains which the night before had shone and vanished, he got to the office of a lawyer. The latter, Mr. Tatum, was a man with the air of a chucker-out and a manner of almost infantile gentleness.

“And so,” he cooed, when Wentworth had had his say, “you want to give Mrs. Wentworth a divorce. Well, now, that presupposes a corespondent. From what you tell me I assume that there is none, in which case if for the purposes of Mrs. Wentworth’s action, you procure one, it is collusion.”

Wentworth nodded. “And consequently more expensive.”

Mr. Tatum moistened his lips. “But I think it can be arranged. The main difficulty may be with Mrs. Wentworth’s attorneys.”

Again Wentworth nodded. “And who need not consider the expense either.”

“I wish all my clients were like you,” Mr. Tatum comfortably replied. “Or rather I wish you were not my client at all. Yes, I do. It is not for me to go behind what you have told me. But it is clear that you are here to do, not the right thing, but the gentlemanly one. The gentlemanly thing is the conventional thing, and all conventionality is cowardice.”

“I think I have heard that before,” Wentworth got in.

Mr. Tatum made a gesture. “Perhaps then you have also heard this: There are certain edicts that no court can dissolve. Issued by our forefathers ages ago they determine our instincts, make us what we are. These instincts used to make men so agreeable that they stoned certain women. Nowadays, in men of your class, they urge them to open all the doors, all the windows, run around and jump off, fish for a divorce and bring it back on a silver platter.

“I’m not a married man,” the lawyer resumed, “but if I were, and I—well, let us say the devil tempted me, I should deeply regret to have my wife discover it. But if she did I would expect her forgiveness. Certainly I would, and if she were a good woman and cared for me, in time I would get it. All love is pity. On the other hand, if the devil tempted my wife, I would forgive her. The one affection worth having is that which can, not only forgive, but console. The majority think otherwise, but in all matters stupidity is very generally diffused. Personally on that score I have no cause for complaint. It is on general stupidity that we lawyers subsist.

“In other words, you mean that I am an imbecile,” Wentworth again got in.

“I mean in matters of this kind, the proper thing is to run a sponge over whatever may be amiss. None the less I am at your service. Mrs. Wentworth shall have a divorce, if you still wish it.”

“Still wish it? I did not come here to change my mind.”

Tatum laughed. “Do you know, I have a room that I use for no other purpose. Changing the mind is a cleanly habit and consequently hygienic.”

But as he laughed, he stood up. Mantled with the dicta which he had let fall, his client was leaving.

These dicta, in the train back, that client examined. They did not seem to him very cogent. To employ a sponge was, he reflected, all very well. But there are sponges of different sizes and classes. The kind he required was a divorce sponge, one that would release Julianne and enable her to marry Gordon who, confound him, would jump at the chance of it. However Tatum might argue, that, he determined, was not only the proper thing, it was the only thing.

But now, abandoning the train, he crossed to Fifth Avenue and entered a club where behind a paper for a while he sat and waited. A member strolled in and yawned; another appeared; a third; finally the one he wanted.

He waved the paper. “Gordon!”

At that, Gordon, had he been able, would have turned tail. He had an animal feeling of being snared. Heartily he wished himself out of it. But, summoning a smile, he approached, straddled a chair, and quite affably looked Wentworth over.

“I have been to my lawyer,” the latter told him.

“And how was he?” Gordon inquired. He found but that. Yet since the morning he had been in and out of the club thinking that, at any moment, a message might come from Julianne to whom—lest Wentworth should get it—he had discreetly omitted to telephone. Now without knowing at all how the land lay, here he was in the thick of it. None the less the smile remained, and at once he was on again.

“By George, you will never believe me, but the last time I consulted a lawyer I had to advise him. On my word I did. He was in a stew over some mess of his own, and I reminded him of Antoninus and how, one night, when the empire was in a turmoil, and the old chap was dying, the captain of the guard came to him for the watchword, ‘Equanimity,’ he replied. You remember?”

“Yes,” Wentworth answered. “It is one of the most consoling things in history.”

Gordon’s smile deepened. “And precious few of them there are. History is dull as ditch-water and ought to be brilliant as a ballet.”

He was but sparring for wind, only he rather felt that Wentworth knew it.

“I had to advise my lawyer, too,” the latter was saying.

Appreciatively, smiling still, Gordon nodded. “They are just like physicians. It is stupid to go to a doctor unless you can tell him what’s wrong with you. If you don’t know, how in the world can you expect him to? If you can’t tell a lawyer how to act—”

“I told mine.”

“And paid him too. That’s always the way.”

“I told him to get Julianne a divorce.”

“Eh?” Gordon exclaimed. His smile vanished. He sat back. He had not known what to expect, but of all things he had not expected that.

“It will be quite simple,” Wentworth continued and would have said more, but now a man in a blue swallowtail and a waistcoat of slashed mustard approached.

“You are wanted at the telephone, sir.”

It was Gordon whom he addressed, and Gordon rose to it. It was a straw, a plank, a raft, rescue from the awkwardness of the situation. With a gesture of excuse he got to his feet, followed the man, entered a corridor in which there were booths.

“Number two, sir.” The operator announced.

Gordon, closing the door, took the receiver. “Hello! Oh, it is you! Well, he’s here. Have you seen him since? You did not see him this morning? I have a bit of news for you then. He has been to his lawyer. No, no, not that at all. It will be for you. All the honors of war. No, honors I said, not horrors. What? I did not get it. Rubbish? Did you say rubbish? Well, rubbish is always a point of view. Hello! Hello!”

The connection was cut. Gordon stared at the instrument. But it was not that which he saw, the necessity rather of returning to Wentworth and of taking medicine which it was shameful of him to dose him with. But, he instantly decided, he could avoid all that. The telephone was excuse enough. He could invent a message and vanish.

“Here,” he called to a boy as he left the booth. “My hat and stick.”

Weaponed with these, he went and waved at Wentworth. “Got to run. In a taxi at that.”

But Wentworth stood up and approached him. “Is it so very pressing?”

Gordon turned and made for the door. “My father’s had a fit.”

Wentworth followed. “I had rather hoped for a minute with you, but—”

“Yes, I’m sorry. Another time.”

Both now were on the pavement. Gordon beckoned a chauffeur, threw him an order, entered the cab.

“You see,” Wentworth said to him through the window, “when it is all over you can marry—”

He was about to add “Julianne.” But Gordon was too quick for him.

“When what’s all over? Good Lord, what are you driving at? I’m not a marrying man.”

Already the car was in motion. Before Wentworth could reply, it spat, veered, darted.

The house of cards about him, Wentworth reentered the club. He had been sure that Gordon would jump at it. Now the man’s defection left him in the dark. In that darkness he sat until, another darkness supervening, he went out into it and on to his home.

In the hall there a servant addressed him. “Mrs. Wentworth has been asking for you, sir. Mrs. Wentworth’s in the dining room. Dinner is served.”

Lusciously, a moment later, that lady also addressed him. “Now tell me, dear, all about your trip.”

Never had she seemed more fair, more desirable. Her mouth glowed, her eyes deepened, and, confident in her charm, she smiled.

Wentworth, coerced by that charm, sat down. “There is not much to tell,” he replied. “But I think you will like the house.”

He paused, looked at her. At the spectacle of her beauty something spoke in him.

“I know that I shall,” he at once continued. “It is almost directly on the sea.”

And why not? he reflected as he helped himself to an oyster. Why not, since love is pity? Besides, he decided, as he helped himself to another oyster, Tatum is right. It’s the proper thing.

The Shudder

“I don’t know where to begin.”

“Begin at the end.”

We were in the library of a metropolitan club. It was in the morning, a trifle after two. Barring the caryatides of the bookshelves, we were alone. The members had gone, the servants also. There was no one about except Parr, the night watchman, who an hour before had brought me a glass of hot water. Ordinarily I would have been at home and in bed but, earlier that night, on leaving the Opera, I had entered the club where, in my letter box, I found Royal Cambridge’s card and a note from a literary agent asking if I could not give him a story with a shudder in it. Thereupon I had gone to the library, ordered the hot water, which to me is always very inspiring, and then, while devising impossible situations, I had seated myself at a table, the water before me. But the water grew cold, the club vacant, my mind as well, and I was about to tell Parr to call a cab when, abruptly, Cambridge entered.

Cambridge is one of the few millionaires of my acquaintance with whom I have a thought in common. Yet then we have affiliated virtues. His nature is that of a sundial. It is only serene hours of which he takes count. For a literary person that is in the order of things. For a millionaire it is a feat. There were other ties. I had always known him, and I was best man at his wedding—an event that had occurred a few months previous and during which he had seemed most reposeful. On this night he was oddly excited.

“It has taken forty years to make my hair gray,” he threw at me. “One hour has made it white.”

He had been standing, but he dropped on a chair, into which, like an omelette soufflée, he seemed to collapse.

Suddenly he straightened. “You don’t know—no one knows what horror is. I alone do.”

“There, there!” I cut in. “I have a note from a man who makes a specialty of it.”

“But first,” he ran on, “you must look at this.”

With that, he produced a picture, a photograph of his wife.

I glanced at it. “You know, Royal, I have always said that there are a hundred ways of being blonde and but one way of being brunette. Mrs. Cambridge has it.”

He nodded at me. “You told me to begin at the end. I will. It is ended.”

“What is?” I asked.

“Do you know anything about demonology?”

“Vaguely. I once wrote a tract about it—but that was only to display my ignorance.”

“In any event, you must be aware that it was a woman who changed Lucifer into Satan.”

“I am at least aware that you are too sensible not to know that you are stupid.”

“Stupid!” he cried. “Why! Why do you say that?”

I indicated the picture. “To fancy for an instant that I will listen to anything against—”

He tossed his head. “On the contrary. I used to say that she was an angel; now I swear that she is a saint.”

I lit a cigarette. “Your metaphors are a bit mixed. To become a saint after having been an angel is a step backward.”

As I spoke, I looked again at the picture. It did not do her justice. No camera could. One might as well attempt to photograph a perfume. The beauty of Constance Cambridge was the least of her allurements. She exhaled everything that is best in woman—sincerity, simplicity, sweetness and strength. The photograph did not display these things. What it did show was a perfect oval, delicate features, a turban of black hair and lips lifted at the corners by the upturned comma of the Athenian mouth. It was not a good likeness, but it might have been worse.

In looking at it, I recalled an episode, faded now and not entirely ideal. Mrs. Cambridge, before her marriage, had lived with her father and her sister. Her father, an estray of fortune and of health, mongered in something—in just what I forget; in aquamarines it may be, or in old anchors—anyway in something fishy. The mongering left Constance unaffected, though apparently it had an influence, perhaps occult, on her sister, a twin, who had also found the one way to be a brunette and to whom other surroundings probably appealed, for she marched off one day and never came back.

“Do you?” I heard Cambridge asking.

I turned to him. “Do I what!”

“Do you remember Dugald Maule?”

At the question, memory raised a latch. I was back again, a schoolboy, in the fifth form at St. Paul’s, with Cambridge and this Maule, a garish fellow whom since then I might have thought dead had I thought of him at all.

“Yes,” I answered; “and since you ask I suppose he must have a local habitation and a bad name.”

Cambridge did not seem to hear. He was wandering afar, into that region known to New Yorkers as Down Town.

“I had to see my brokers today,” he explained. “Their office is in Exchange Place. I told the mechanician where to go. By the way, do you believe in fate?”

“I believe that never do useless events occur.”

Cambridge looked down. “Through some hideous mockery the mechanician stopped at the wrong door. How wrong it was it would take Victor Hugo to describe. It was there I met Maule.”

At mention of the man, Cambridge gave a sort of uneasy shake, and looking up again said: “Have you a cigarette?”

On the table between us was the glass of water, the photograph and my case. The case I shoved over to him. Then, as he helped himself from it, I noticed that his hand trembled. He must have noticed it also. He looked at me and away. But in that look I saw that his eyes were dilated and bloodshot. Already I had seen that he was not in evening dress. Now, for the first time, I saw that the clothes which he wore exhibited, and rather ostentatiously I thought, a sort of studied indigence. In a man of very large means anything of that kind is eminently correct. It was his eyes that perplexed. They looked as though he had been trying, in drink, to drown some specter, yet only to discover that the specter could swim.

But, at the moment, my attention was diverted. Parr had peered in on us and vanished. When I turned to Cambridge again he was ashamedly concealing his hand.

“No matter,” he exclaimed. “Maule made a great fuss over me. He would have it that I come into an office which he had, for my perdition, nearby. I took it for granted that he wanted to borrow money. It is one of the misfortunes of having any that you always think that. But not at all. He wanted only to talk about himself. He had, it appeared, been in France ever since he left St. Paul’s, and only recently, as representative of a champagne house, had returned. He got a bottle out from somewhere which he asked me to try. Of course I refused. Then, from one thing to another, he said that, after Paris, it surprised him to find that the women here were all pretty and the men all in a hurry.”

I patted a yawn. “Why should that surprise? It is merely an example of cause and effect.”

“Finally, when I got up to go,” Cambridge resumed, “I asked after his wife, whom I had known—she belonged to a good old family here—and he told me that she was separated from him.”

“The nicest people become disconnected by marriage,” I threw in, but I threw it with another yawn. Never had I known Cambridge to be so tiresome, and earnestly I wished myself in bed.

“But,” Cambridge continued, “the beggar confided in me that he rather fancied himself on a way of his. It seems that on Fifth Avenue, the day before yesterday, he had joined an unknown beauty; he had seen her again yesterday and she had given him her picture and the promise of meeting him tomorrow.”

Once more I patted a yawn. This unending story about nothing at all was boring me to extinction.

“He showed me the picture,” Cambridge added. “I don’t speak of the delicacy of the proceeding, but of the infamy of it. There it is.”

“What!”

Cambridge was pointing at the photograph of his wife.

I stared at him. He no longer bored—he frightened. It was not anger nor yet hatred that his face expressed, but determination, indomitable, inflexible, menacing as a sword, and of which I seemed to feel the point and the chill.

He glanced at the picture, and from it at me. “It was like a nightmare in broad daylight. I took it—tore it rather—from him and knocked him down.”

“It can’t be possible!” I exclaimed. I found but that. Yet immediately I reflected that nothing earthly has ever prevented a woman from having the fantasies and caprices of her sex. On the heels of that reflection, instantly there trod another. There are social felonies that a gentlewoman never commits. The consciousness of that fortified me. I felt that I did not believe Cambridge, that I could not. This story of his was not only incredible—it was preposterous.

I told him as much.

To my surprise he agreed with me. “You are right,” he said. “It is preposterous. So is any nightmare. But you have lived long enough in romance to have at least a bowing acquaintance with life, and, for the majority of us, what is life but a dread and a dream?”

“Well,” I replied, “I am glad you can philosophize over a matter which I cannot and will not swallow. The point is, if you can philosophize, you can also forget. In any event, you have got to.”

“Never,” he threw at me.

“Then you must forgive.”

“Never.”

“Yes, for, assuming for a moment the truth of what you tell me, how shall it matter unless it does teach you to forgive? If it does not do that, then I may admonish you, as in similar circumstances a poet also admonished, nothing has happened to you at all.”

At this, and at me, he nodded. “Quite so. To forgive another is easy enough. It is different with oneself.”

I was about to interrupt. He checked me.

“I left Maule on the floor where I had thrown him and went directly home. On the way I could not but wonder at my relapse into the primitive. Decent men don’t go stalking women. The fact that he was not decent was his misfortune no doubt, but clearly not his fault. The blame was hers. So at least I decided, and when I got to my house I went directly to her. She was in her room, lying on a sofa, dressed in silk, a scarf of silk about her neck. That detail may seem unimportant. It is momentous.

“As I approached, she smiled. In her face was the tint which you may have noticed in the arbutus. I saw it then. I can see it now.

“ ‘Where were you yesterday?’ I cried at her. ‘Where were you the day before? Where are you to be tomorrow?’

“At the first question the smile went; at the second the flush faded; at the third she was white as white paper.

“I sprang at her, caught at the scarf and garroted her with it. I did it so quickly that she had no time to scream, barely to struggle; only her eyes spoke—and what volumes!”

“Great heavens! You don’t mean that you killed her!”

It was all I got out. But if previously he had frightened, then he appalled. He was livid. One side of his mouth was raised as is that of a dog when about to bite. I knew he was saying something. Yet what? It was a moment before I caught up.

“Yes, it was on her writing table, across the room.”

As he spoke, he produced a letter which he began reading aloud and which, so nearly as I can remember, ran somewhat as follows:

It was so dear, Sybil, to have seen you, and much as I want to see you again, I cannot until Royal knows and permits me. To get his consent I must tell him your whole sad story. When he hears it I am almost sure of what he will do. If I do not come then, as I hope to, tomorrow, you will understand that I have not yet had the chance to tell him about my meeting you yesterday and the day before. Meanwhile at least I have your picture.

Lovingly always,
Constance.

Cambridge put the letter on the table, took up the photograph and turned it over.

“Look at that,” he told me.

On the back was written: “Constance, from Sybil.”

Blankly I stared at the inscription. “It was your wife’s sister then that Maule—” I could get no further.

Cambridge helped me out. “And it was my wife that I killed.”

Nervously I lit a cigarette. The bar, I knew, was closed. Had it not been, I would have ordered a drop of shamshoo—a Chinese liquor popular among certain members for its steadying effect.

But it was for myself I would have ordered it. Cambridge had obviously no need of anything of the kind. Long since his hand had ceased to tremble. His eyes, previously dilated, had dwindled strangely. They seemed small and shrewd, like those of a hippopotamus. Moreover, he was quite at his ease, revoltingly calm; he even looked at his watch, after which, much as though he were giving the time of day, he threw out:

“And now I shall kill myself.”

At that I exploded. “You can’t! It is not psychically possible. There is no such thing as death. Afterward you will find yourself quite as abominably alive as you are now. What is worse, instead of having but one crime to pay for, you will then have two. Besides, what is the use? There is not a particle of evidence against you. A silk scarf, employed as you employed it, leaves no trace whatever. What you did will be attributed to natural causes. Moreover, it is all so screamingly vulgar. If it is remorse that is inciting you, live and repent. If you don’t, by George, I tell you what, I’ll cut you dead!”

“Who is George?” he indifferently inquired.

With a whoop, I was at him. But his arm shot out. He was pointing at something across the room. I turned to look. Save the books and the lights, there was nothing. I turned again. In the momentary interim he had emptied a little bottle into the glass of water, and before I could prevent him, had tossed it off. Immediately, in just the same manner that he had previously collapsed, he sank like an omelette soufflée.

“Parr!” I shouted. “Parr!”

But it was all a bit too much. My head swam; the lights went out, or I did. When I came to, Parr was standing before me.

“Yes, sir.”

I blinked at him, at an empty chair, at the floor, at the table, about the room, then at Parr again.

“Where—how—what became of Mr. Cambridge?”

“Mr. Cambridge? I haven’t seen Mr. Cambridge—not for a week. No, sir.”

“Curious,” I muttered after a moment. “Yet even in dream I ought to have known that millionaires don’t kill their wives. They perhaps find it simpler to detest them.

“Parr,” I added, “I seem to have been asleep. Now I will write for a while. Just see, please, if you can get me some more hot water.”

Then presently, when the water was brought, I drank it and set to work on “The Shudder.”

The Splendid Lie

“This is Mr. Tatum.”

In the hall of the Athenaeum Club an introduction was being effected. A young man was actively engaged in making his uncle acquainted with his future father-in-law. The latter was Mr. Tatum. The uncle was Mr. Farquhar, and the young man Harry.

There, barring the lady, you have what I think I have seen described as the dramatis personae. The lady will appear in a moment. Though not, of course, in the hall where these three men were standing.

Two weeks previous Harry had crossed the ocean. On the way, chance, or the chief steward, had at table placed him side by side with the daughter of Mr. Tatum. The girl was pretty, she was endowed with superior health and manner, and, though reticent, could listen to anything worth listening to with glimpses of teeth as perfect as Harry remembered to have seen before. To provoke those glimpses Harry said whatever entered his head, which, I admit, was not much.

In spite of this, or, perhaps, precisely on that account, it so fell about that in the wide leisures of the voyage, companionship became pleasant to them both, so pleasant, indeed, that neither felt it could properly terminate with the journey, both concurring that it would be agreeable to take a longer trip, one in which not chance, or the chief steward, but matrimony should place them side by side.

Yet that perhaps was in the order of things. The girl was very fetching, and Harry was a nice-looking boy who came of what is known as the best people—those people who are still the best, in spite of plutocratic invasion. Such things count with a girl, particularly if she have money and social aspirations.

Miss Tatum had both, but not what is perhaps pretentiously described as position. Metropolitan hostesses never thought of asking her to their entertainments, for the excellent reason that, in a city like New York, where the few are obvious and the many obscure, she was an entirely unknown quantity.

Mr. Farquhar, Harry’s uncle, was just the reverse. An old New Yorker, he had been everywhere, seen everything, known everybody. He had been interested in a number of ladies since dead and departed, and at balls and dinners related the fact to their daughters with tender calm. He was not only an old New Yorker, he was an old beau. As such he had two manners, one very gracious, the other equally remote. In the hall of the Athenaeum Club it was the latter that he was displaying.

“Uncle Reginald, this is Mr. Tatum.”

At the introduction, Mr. Tatum raised his hat, extended a hand, and smiled. Mr. Farquhar smiled also. But he did not seem to think it necessary to acknowledge the introduction in any other way. He kept his hat on his head, and his hands in his pockets.

Mr. Tatum was a large man, very stout, with a face like a brandied cherry. It was dull red all over, except on his forehead, where there was a white scar. He mumbled something about the pleasure which he was experiencing. Mr. Farquhar made no reply. Harry said something to the effect that he was glad to bring his uncle and his future father-in-law together. Mr. Farquhar did not appear to have heard. But still he smiled.

Yet in that smile of his was a gleam as chill as the point of a sword. Before it suddenly the scar on Mr. Tatum’s forehead flamed. He dropped his hand, replaced his hat, stalked to the door. Harry followed, saw him out, and returned to where his uncle stood.

“Have you lunched, Harry?” that uncle asked. “No? Very good! Then lunch with me. Your fat friend has given me an appetite.”

“In that case,” Harry angrily retorted, “I can’t say that you seemed very grateful.”

At this, Mr. Farquhar smiled as he had smiled before. Taking the nephew by the arm, he led him into what is perhaps the most elaborate breakfast room in New York.

“Suppose we sit here,” Mr. Farquhar continued, indicating, as he spoke, a table at a window. “What would you say to a ragout à la Sardanapale and a glass of Moselle? Archibald,” he added, turning to the head waiter, “will you see, please, that the ragout has saffron in it, and that the Moselle is not iced? Now,” he resumed, when the waiter had gone, “this Mr.—er—Tatum is quite well off, I think you told me.”

“Ten million,” snapped Harry.

“His daughter, I presume, will come in for it all. Well, ten million is just enough to entertain on. Nowadays, a penny less and you are pinched. So-and-so used to say that no one could live like a gentleman on less than a thousand dollars a day. At four per cent, ten million will yield a trifle more. I can remember when twelve thousand a year was regarded as wealth. Times have changed, but not customs. Always it has been considered as easy to marry a rich girl as a poor one, besides being, as Major Pendennis remarked, much more comfortable. By the way, you know of Hank Jones, don’t you? The papers have been rather busy with him lately.”

Harry, who had been looking out of the window, turned.

“The policy man? What of him?”

“Nothing. He occurred to me in connection with days—and nights—when living was less expensive. At the time, there were a number of gambling dens about here. The dealers represented a type which, like the epoch, has gone. They wore diamonds, dressed in black, and affected to be supremely apathetic. In those days Hank Jones was one of that sort.”

“Here is the ragout,” Harry, vaguely bored, interrupted.

“But there was,” Mr. Farquhar continued, helping his nephew to some truffles and game, “there was nothing apathetic about Hank Jones, except, of course, in appearance, and in appearance only for appearance sake. He was a great hand at making a stranger feel at home, and then in taking that stranger’s home away. A gift such as that is apt to lead to curious experiences. More than once it led him to jail.

“But he had other adventures. On one of those sumptuous April days of ours, which are not of the spring nor yet of the summer, but a mingling of both, a girl came sauntering before the Fifth Avenue Hotel where he stood. Whether or not she gave him so much of an invitation as may be conveyed in the quiver of an eyelid, I, for one, do not know. What I do know is that he followed her, spoke to her, joined her, and accompanied her to her parents’ home. In a week she was—”

“I think I will take some of the Moselle,” Harry, with a yawn, again interrupted.

“Help yourself, dear boy. Where was I? Oh, yes! In addition to the girl—whose name, if I have it correctly, was Arabella, and who, in becoming his wife, became also his cook—in addition to her he had an assortment of equally agreeable acquaintances. There was Johnny Slope, for instance, a plumber by trade, by practice a thief. There was Banjo Pete, a lively you fellow, who, after vacating the minstrel world, had passed initiate into the high art, of illuminating with dark lanterns. There was also George Percival, a poet, born without scruples, and who had neglected to acquire any. These friends of Jones’ were all interested in policy. Through their aid, and through the aid of others similarly accomplished, he was multiplying joints all over town. If I am correctly informed, these amusements made him quite wealthy.

“Meanwhile, in the quarters over which Arabella presided, occasionally there were festivities. That brisk young Pete would bring his banjo, play he was Mr. Bones again, sing wonderful songs, and tell a rattling story. Johnny Slope—Mr. Slopely in private life—would sometimes come with his lady, sometimes with his father, as nice a looking old gentleman as ever cracked a crib. There also Percival, with his poetic ways, would lounge by the hour.”

“I’d like a bit of bread, please,” Harry once more interrupted.

“Now, it so happened,” Mr. Farquhar, reaching a plate to his nephew, continued, “that in the course of one of these festivities, Hank Jones was called away, and did not return until all the guests, save Percival, had gone. He was then just in time to hear Arabella call ‘Help!’ and to see Percival, with an arm about her. At once he was at him. Percival dropped the girl, caught up a bottle, and struck him. Later, when Jones came to, Arabella had washed the blood away, but not the wound. Time itself has not obliterated it. The scar was quite visible when he was in the hall here a few minutes ago. Have another truffle?”

“What!” Harry cried. His anger had gone, his boredom with it. “Do you mean—”

“That Mr. Tatum and Hank Jones are one and the same? Why, of course I do. But I have not finished. There is an epilogue to the story. A fortnight after the bottle incident, Percival was assisted out of the world. Your fat friend was arrested for it, he was tried, and—never say you don’t believe in miracles—was acquitted. It was then that he changed his name. Professionally he remained Hank Jones, but for the private purposes of private life he developed into Mr. Tatum. After all, there is no law against it. Though, if there were, I hardly fancy it would trouble him. A little more of the ragout?”

“A-a-and you say,” Harry stuttered. “Y-y-you say—” He did not seem to get any farther.

“Did you not hear me?” Mr. Farquhar asked. “Or would you wish me to tell it all over again? Yesterday, on receipt of the note in which you acquainted me with your engagement, I called on my old friend, the district attorney. It is the summary of his conversation that I have related to you.

“Interesting, isn’t it?” Mr. Farquhar, after a momentary interlude with knife and fork, resumed. “In any event, your future father-in-law is certainly a fine old party. Though I admit, in the hall here, he looked so wretchedly ill, so manifestly apoplectic, that I felt really sorry for him. Now I feel sorry for his daughter.”

“I’ll chuck it,” Harry morosely muttered. “And deuced hard luck it is. A nicer girl never lived.”

To this, Mr. Farquhar, fully occupied now with the ragout, said nothing. But the description of the girl seemed to him highly impressionistic. She was, he was convinced, both inane and vulgar. Inane, because she had accepted Harry, and vulgar because she could not help herself. The daughter of a cook, and also of a crook, how, he asked himself, could she be otherwise? None the less, ten million, and the father en route for the cemetery, after all, it did seem a pity.

“Yes,” Harry repeated. “I’ll chuck it.”

He threw a glance out of the window, and wished he could follow it. He was profoundly unhappy, overwhelmed by one of those enormous griefs which, in the youth of life, the morrow disperses utterly.

Meditatively, Mr. Farquhar patted his mouth with a napkin, moved his plate aside, and considered his nephew.

“You will have to tell her,” he at last remarked. “That will be a bit awkward.”

Manfully, Harry exclaimed: “I’ll write her.”

Mr. Farquhar flicked a crumb from his sleeve.

“Suppose I take a hand. Suppose I go and break it gently. That would be better than writing—unless you used a pencil. Writing with a pencil is like talking in a whisper. Ink, don’t you think, is so emphatic?”

“But,” objected Harry, “I’d have to give you a line to her.”

“There, there!” Mr. Farquhar soothingly replied. “Don’t run into excesses. Besides, while I have received any number of letters of introduction, never yet have I presented one.” With an uplift of the chin he resumed: “My name is sufficient.”

As he spoke, he arose.

“You will go to her now?” Harry, rising also, heroically inquired.

“Yes.”

Mr. Farquhar was as good as his word. Presently, in a hansom, he was sailing along toward the residence of this girl, who, on alighting, he learned was at home.

Telling the servant the sesame of that name of his, he looked about the room into which the servant then showed him. It was furnished with plenty of taste, and, to his surprise, none of it bad. But his surprise heightened when the girl herself appeared. Instead of the vulgar young person whom he had imagined, here, a hand extended to this uncle of her betrothed, was a superselect beauty speaking in a voice that was silken:

“I am so glad to see you. Harry has so often—But won’t you be seated?” Mr. Farquhar heard, but did not heed. He was thinking how could he tell this loveliness that his nephew would not marry her, and would not, moreover, because of distasteful things of which she was innocent, and doubtless unaware. He simply could not. All the innate gentility in him rebelled. It was impossible. He would lie first. And at once, in an unhallowed inspiration, the lie hopped out:

“Harry is no more!”

The girl started.

“Dead?”

“Worse!”

At this questions and exclamation marks shot from the beauty’s eyes.

“Yes,” Mr. Farquhar resumed. “Not an hour ago the young scoundrel eloped with an old harridan, hang him!”

Bewilderment lifted the girl visibly, like a lash.

“What?”

“And hanging is too good for him; he ought to have his ghost kicked.”

“But—”

“An old harridan! A hunchback dwarf! With a harelip at that!”

“But—”

“I know. When he could have had you! How, you wonder, can such a thing be. Believe me, in your wonderment I collaborate.”

“But—”

“I know. I appreciate. Yet now, as you may see, it is but a case of good riddance to bad rubbish. I came to condole, I remain to congratulate.”

The girl turned, crossed the room, recrossed it, sat down.

Mr. Farquhar eyed her, and, eying, divined the effort she was making to readjust herself. In looking at her he saw she was looking at the floor, and saw, too, that she looked infernally pretty. Beauty in distress is very appealing. Yet was she, Mr. Farquhar asked himself, really distressed? Concerning Harry, he had no illusions. He was a nice boy, but, otherwise, from the avuncular standpoint, an imbecile, whereas this girl was charming—so charming that he realized, as never before, what a confounded fool Harry was.

Through what miracle charm of any kind had been evolved in this young woman, whose antecedents were SO clearly precarious, Harry’s uncle, accustomed as he was to the multiple surprises of metropolitan life, no more thought of attempting to determine than he would have thought of dissecting a rose. Instead of anything so futile he moved to where she sat.

There, impelled by sudden sympathy, by a sympathy which was new to him, he spoke:

“My dear child, you think you have lost something. Believe me, you have gained.”

The girl, who had been looking down, looked up. Her eyes—diamonds on purple velvet—were tearless. In their deep depths grief had either sunk away or else been throttled.

“You are undoubtedly right,” she answered, in that silken voice of hers. “Besides, it is at least consoling to know that—”

“That love returns to the heart as the leaf returns to the tree,” Mr. Farquhar swiftly and sagaciously interjected.

But the feminine in her was not to be denied.

“It is at least consoling to know that the lady is—er—well—what you tell me.”

Subtly, with tender calm, Mr. Farquhar retouched the picture: “A monster!”

The girl smiled.

“I wish them both joy.” As she spoke she stood up. “Will you have some tea?”

Mr. Farquhar would, and did. He had tea with her that day, and on the next, and on the day after, and the day succeeding. He had tea with her so often that he found time to tell her certain things, and to learn certain others.

He told her that he was not as young as he might be—which perhaps was evident. He told her that in point of worldly goods, he classed himself among the newly poor—which, it may be, she suspected.

Then novelties were produced. He told her that he had loved her at first sight—which, he told her also is often second sight—and that phenomenon sufficiently explained, he told her that he was lonely, and learned that so was she; learned, too, and rather to his surprise, that this loneliness she attributed to her father.

“I did not know you knew,” said Mr. Farquhar, who, at the moment, found but that.

The girl nodded. “I have for years.” She brushed a tear. “But how shall it matter? The doctors say he cannot live.”

Nor did he. Afterward, after a decent interval, that is, Mr. Farquhar told her something else. He told the rhyme and reason of his lie.

“But!” the girl exclaimed.

Her hand had been in his, her head on his shoulder. At once she moved a little away. A perspective had suddenly unfolded. In it she saw a nephew’s cowardice, an uncle’s bravery. The one amused, the other appealed. But of these inward emotions she gave no outward sign. Instead, she murmured demurely:

“I thought that gentlemen never told—”

“Sometimes,” Mr. Farquhar interrupted. “Sometimes they do.”

Those eyes of hers she lowered, and it was as though addressing the carpet that she asked:

“To whom, then, do they?”

Mr. Farquhar caught up, and repeated, the question.

“To whom do gentlemen ever lie?” Drawing her to him, he continued: “To whom, indeed, except to those they love? Won’t you forgive me?”

The question was needless. Already in the girl’s now-lifted eyes laughter floated.

Harry was less indulgent. When he learned the truth he reviled his uncle and his aunt-to-be.

“Nephews are so intolerant,” Mr. Farquhar, with his usual calm, commented. “You see, my dearest, truth is not suited to everybody, nor, for that matter, are lies.”

At which his dearest smiled, and said:

“No, of course not; unless, like your own, they happen to be splendid.”

The Suspect

“How much do you want?” the pawnbroker asked.

“Oh,” I said, with an air of assumed indifference, “a hundred will do.”

The pawnbroker gave me a queer, sharp look, one which he instantly diverted to the gold cigarette case, a rather elaborate affair, that I had offered him, and which had on it in jewels the initials K. M.

He looked up at me again.

“At auction it wouldn’t bring half that. Twenty is the best I can do.”

It was idle to argue; besides, I never can haggle. But I needed more. I told him so. In the telling, I produced a watch, also gold, also initialed, one that had in it the miniature of a girl’s fair face.

He looked it over, and, darting another queer glance at me, snapped: “Fifteen!”

At once, as I nodded, he got out some bills, which he fumbled meditatively, much as though he had never seen them before.

Behind him was a telephone; also a row of shelves on which were hideous things. In between was a counter, topped with glass, through which I could see brooches, bracelets, rings—the lamentable tokens of disastrous days. Beyond, at the rear of the shop, a man bent heavily over an enormous ledger. Without was the roar of the Bowery; within an odor of camphor. At my elbow was the telephone book, and before me the pawnbroker, a sinister and sinewy brute.

“I haven’t quite got it,” he suddenly exclaimed.

He turned, put the watch and case on a shelf, took the receiver from the hook, and, after a moment, called: “Three thousand one hundred, Spring.”

“Three thousand one hundred, Spring?” he presently resumed. “This is Alfred Cohen. Yes. Send Jakey with change for a hundred. What? Sure! Shake a foot.”

With that, he replaced the receiver, turned again, and threw out: “Fine day!”

“Very,” I threw back.

Then indifferently, as though for the mere distraction of it, I took up the telephone book, and opened it, haphazard, in the middle. I had hit the mark, though. There it was: “Police Headqts, 3100 Spring.” I turned the page, flipped at another, closed the book, put it down, and dropped into the obvious:

“What would we do without telephones?”

Mr. Cohen gurgled appreciatively:

“There you are!”

“Or,” I continued, “without cigars?” While we are waiting for Jakey, I’ll go and get one.” Ingratiatingly I added: “I’ll get two.”

As I spoke, I turned. Before me, through the grating and glass of the door, came the glitter of the street, the shriek of trains, the grunt of cars, the shapes of passers—instantly effaced.

Between me and the door was Mr. Cohen. He had vaulted the counter, and at the moment was calling overloudly, I thought, to the man with the ledger.

“You be quiet,” he oddly admonished me. “Here,” he interrupted himself to bawl over my head, “this feller’s wanted.”

I turned again. From the rear of the shop there had sprung a creature who more nearly resembled a gorilla than any human being I had ever seen.

Unconcernedly I nodded.

“How do do?” Then, rising to his level, I added: “Our friend here seems to have got them again.”

“I’ve got you!” I heard Cohen retort.

But at once, so far as I was concerned, he and the gorilla ceased to exist. I was concerned only that now at last I was in for it, and the consciousness brought that sense of curious relief which I suppose is known only to those who, like me, have been “wanted,” and who, in consequence, have been obliged to turn and twist, to walk in silence and in secret ways, to feel always that they are hunted.

That is the way I had felt, and so acutely that now, the end of my tether reached, I forgot that Cohen and the other brute existed. But to such an indignity, they must have refused to submit. I heard them talking—calling, rather—at each other in German; but their greasy gutturals were as unheeded by me as was the slam bang of the elevated.

That which finally aroused me was the entrance of Jakey—two men; one slim, in plain clothes; the other fat, and in uniform. The latter, a billy pendant but probably prompt in his hand, marched up and put his other hand on my shoulder. As he did so, I noticed the ledger fiend slinking, with an air of abasement, away, and it occurred to me that his conscience was not, perhaps, all that it might be.

“When no man pursueth!” I flung at his retreating back; but he squirmed, dodged, vanished.

At this the plain-clothes man, who had been talking with Cohen in an open, unaffected, and very uncomplimentary manner about me, sidled suddenly up, ran his hands over me, found that I was unarmed, and said—and nicely enough: “You’ll go quietly?”

I smiled at him.

“Dear me! I hate a fuss as much as you do; perhaps even more. But would it be indiscreet of me to ask where I am going?”

He smiled back at me. “It would not be indiscreet; it would be excessive. You know.”

Well, as for that, he was right; and during the immediate and brief promenade to headquarters I said nothing further, except to ask for a cigarette from that case which, with the watch, Cohen had turned over to him. He obligingly gave it to me, flattering me as he did so by saying: “I like your nerve.”

But as we were entering the building I again spoke to him:

“I must have an attorney, you know, and I will have to get bail.”

He nodded.

“You’ll get an attorney in court fast enough. This, though, is not a bailable matter.”

“Nonsense!” I exclaimed. “There is only one of that kind.”

“And that’s yours.”

The reply sent a shudder through me. Robbery—yes, I had expected that; but murder! At the moment I felt that no one had ever known what horror is—that I alone knew. But I have at least a modicum of common sense, and it surged at once to my rescue. Often I have told myself—and others—that it is stupid to be afraid of anything, no matter what, except danger, damp sheets, and one’s own misdeeds. I told myself so then. In the telling I reflected that while, after all, I may have murdered a tune or two, yet otherwise—no, they might hold me, but never could they keep me on any such charge.

Further meditations were for the moment interrupted. Between the two men, one of whom still had a hand on my shoulder, I had marched along a hall, and was now taken into a room where sat one of the finest—a good-looking chap, with alert eyes and a drooping mustache.

“We’ve got him, inspector!” said my friend in plain clothes. In the restrained idiom of the street, he added: “And with the goods on.”

In speaking, he produced the watch and cigarette case, which the inspector, with a curious smile, examined.

Abruptly he looked up at me. The smile had gone.

“Where did you get these things?”

I was about to tell him I had forgotten; but, rallying, I answered:

“They were given me.”

At that, point-blank, he fired:

“By Kenneth Mar?”

I dodged it:

“No, not by Kenneth Mar.”

Before firing again, he pursed his lips.

“You knew him, though?”

I shrugged my free shoulder.

“Slightly.”

For a second he seemed to be taking that in; then at once, without warning, he shot out:

“What did you do with the body?”

At this explosion I started.

“Nothing whatever. What should I have done with it? Why do you ask?”

He helped himself, coolly enough, I thought, to a cigarette from that case, lighted it contemplatively, nodded, and said:

“I’ll tell you.” He paused, inhaled the smoke, blew it, and added: “A week ago to-day, Kenneth Mar escorted a young woman to her home. He went to the door with her, waited until it was opened, went away, passed an acquaintance, who saw him approach an apartment house in which he lived, and which was a bit beyond. But that house Mar never entered. No one has seen Mar since. On the day when he disappeared, the young woman whom he took to her home knew that he had that case and that watch with him. In that watch is her own picture. Where did you get it? Answer me!”

It was rather a volley, but I faced it.

“Really, inspector, I shall have to throw myself on your indulgence. I have a very poor memory—particularly for anything important—and I can only assure you that—that—”

He cut me short:

“Where have you been living these last few days?”

The unexpected twist pulled the truth out of me:

“Nine ninety-nine Great Jones Street.”

At this, with that gravity which, even in serious matters, officials will display, he motioned at the policeman.

“Take him in there.”

Immediately to the plain-clothes man he added:

“Telephone for Miss Faille.”

In so ordering, he looked at me, to judge, perhaps, the effect of that name; and at once, as I turned to enter the room which he had indicated, I fell to thinking of this girl whom I knew Kenneth Mar had loved. Knowledge of that intimate fact was not confined to me. Everybody knew it—everybody, that is, who reads the papers; and for the past week the papers had dripped with this matter which the inspector had briefly resumed. But though the outlines, and particularly the headlines, of the mystery were familiar enough to all, yet the deeper mystery that was behind it was not solved until later; and then generally resolved itself into the verdict that Kenneth Mar was cracked.

A man in love usually is a bit off. In France, pathologists so ordinarily recognize the fact that they classify the condition as a disease induced by a fermentation of the molecules of the imagination. Assuming the diagnosis to be correct, necessarily there must exist a superinducing cause. In the present instance that cause was Janet Faille. The mere sight of her was headier than cups of champagne. At the risk of appearing extravagant—an appearance parenthetically for which I have no great dislike—I can compare her only to the first heroine of the first hexameters, that vision at sight of whose undreamed-of beauty the Trojans stopped, and stood, and mused.

A young person of such allurement is bound to have many suitors, and Janet Faille had. Among the favored were Kenneth Mar and another man, who must have been a genius, for thus far he had managed to keep his name out of print.

Between the two Janet Faille had seemed to hesitate. Yet it may be that she seemed to only. In the depths of her delicate heart, perhaps she knew.

It was in these circumstances that the mystery occurred, and I, who, for my sins, had been instrumental in it hid in shabby lodgings until what money I had was gone, and I was forced into the disastrous visit to Cohen and his gorilla friend. Never in the world would I have gone to that shop, or to any other of the kind, had I known that descriptions of the watch and of the cigarette case had been sent about. The papers had supplied me with every variety of imaginable and unimaginable information concerning the matter; yet of these things not a word.

On the contrary, you were told that Kenneth Mar was not precisely a pauper; that he claimed to be a composer; that he was young, blue-eyed, dark-haired, without an enemy in the world or an idea in his head; in short, a nonentity with a few dollars in his pocket, who, on that account, may have been held up, knocked out, and otherwise disposed of. Or, if not, then that he must have developed a secondary personality, lost all knowledge of who he really was, and would ultimately be discovered in the guise of a dairymaid on a Kansas farm, or as an eremite in a Harlem flat. These things, and more besides, the papers gave; but of the watch and cigarette case never a word. There was the trick that caught me.

Meanwhile, from the outer room there had been filtering the sound of voices and of brief, unemphasized commands. If I heard, I did not heed. Engrossed as I was in that trick, I had forgotten even the presence of the fat policeman, who sat beside me—a club in one hand, my arm in the other.

But now my attention veered. Before me over the open door was a painting of a girl, the mediocre copy of an inferior daub which, years before, I had seen in the Paris Salon. At the thought of that jungle, of its mile after mile of improbable nymphs and vaselined landscapes, ardently I wished myself back there. Two hours of it, succeeded by massage, was, I knew, excellent for obesity. No doubt a bicycle is better, but that is no longer modish, and I told myself there should be something for every taste, however infastidious.

Again I looked at the painting. In spite of the sin of it, it suggested somebody—but whom? Then suddenly I knew, for as suddenly I heard her. In those accents which certain sections of Fifth Avenue share with Mayfair, Janet Faille was talking to the inspector.

I started. But that hand on my shoulder gripped me. The prompt billy had jumped.

“No,” I heard her say, “it is not an inconvenience. I had intended coming. When I last saw you I was not entirely frank.”

“And you will be so now, Miss Faille?” I heard the inspector interject, and interject, moreover, in a tone so different from that in which he had spoken to me that I wondered could he be a ventriloquist. But, then, beauty is a great emollient.

“I told you,” the girl was saying, “that I had no theory. That was untrue. But though I did have one, you will, perhaps, appreciate why I did not mention it. You know that Mr. Mar was—well, that he admired me.”

“He would have been blind if he had not,” that man threw in.

“But what you do not know,” the girl resumed, “is that I cared for him also. Oh, very, very much more than he knew—far more than I let him imagine. I was even guilty of trying to get him to think that I was interested elsewhere, when I was not—not in the very least, believe me.”

I could not see her tears, but it seemed to me I heard them. Yet presently, with a tremor in that voice of silk, the tale continued, and, though I could not see, I could fancy her two hands crushed together.

“Well, that last afternoon, when he took me home—”

“Permit me,” the inspector interrupted. “The other man—the one whom you seemed to favor—have you seen him since?”

“No, no—nor shall I ever again.”

“Do you know where he is?”

“No, nor do I want to.”

“What is he like?”

“Tall and dark, with regular features.”

At this the policeman beside me turned. He was looking me over.

Meanwhile, that voice which I have compared to silk became like a thread snapped swiftly. There was silence in the outer room—yet a silence that was punctuated soon by little sobs, by little, herculean efforts to arrest them.

“I wish I were dead!” she at last cried out. “It was I who killed him.”

“Miss Faille!” the inspector protested.

“Yes. At first I thought he had gone away to try me, to see if in his absence I would not give some sign to show—to show—And now! Is it not clear that, since you have those things of his, he must have killed himself, and that it was I who drove him to it?”

After the logic of that again for a moment there was silence. Then, with the customary combination of platitude and imagination, the inspector went at it:

“You see, Miss Faille, in matters of this kind the obvious is very misleading. The person from whom we got this watch and cigarette case has been hiding in Great Jones Street. I have sent to the place, and I find that he took lodgings there shortly after Mar’s disappearance. I find, too, that, except at night, and except to-day, when we got him, always he remained locked in his room.”

Once more there was a sob, the effort to subdue it, another little cry:

“He must have—Oh, he must have found Kenneth, and robbed him. Don’t you think so?”

“If he did, he found him before he was lost. But everything is possible. It is possible, for instance, that the man whom you seemed to favor, but who doubtless knew that in reality you preferred Mar, did away with him for that very reason, and then, that the crime might be attributed to a footpad, pocketed his valuables. That is usual, but what is usual, also, once the crime committed, he lost his nerve, and ran to cover.”

“What a Solomon!” I thought.

“Here!” I heard the inspector call. “Bring the suspect in here.”

In a moment I was before them—before the inspector, rather, for Janet’s back was toward me.

Slowly she turned; her deep eyes widened, her mouth half opened, closed, opened again; with a little bleat, she started to me, while, from over her shoulder, she called:

“This is Kenneth Mar!”

I would have laughed. I knew that what she said was true; knew that she was, also; knew, too, that I had hidden away for the very reason she stated, in order that some sign of hers might show whether she cared for me or for another.

I would have laughed, I say. But I was only just in time to catch her. She had fainted.

It was from sheer joy, she later told me. Yet even now I scarcely dare believe it.

The Top of the Heap

“Blind obedience and the truth. That’s what I want from you. Nothing else.”

Mr. Beamish, as he spoke, glared imperially. There are men whom it is more agreeable to avoid than to meet. Mr. Beamish had succeeded in becoming one of them. He was fat, and quite as fascinating as vulgarity and a French tailor could make him. What a French tailor can accomplish in that line exceeds the powers of prose. Yet, though fat, he was forceful, and if vulgar, valiant.

It was his son whom he addressed. The room, large, oblong, furnished in red, tropically hot on this mid-May noon, had the tawdriness of a Paris hotel written all over it. Through an open window the sun lurched. Beyond were the Tuileries. From below came the cries of the hawkers that are never still, “Le Matin! Demandez Le Matin!”

“Now disobey me if you dare⸺”

The boy made a face. He was rather good looking, and quite athletic.

“Disobey you! Disobey a father who is a phenomenon, a father with thirty million and three chins! What do you take me for? But how do you know she won’t object?”

“Because she does what her mamma wishes.”

“But I don’t see why her mamma should wish anything of the kind, or, for that matter, you either.”

“You don’t, eh? I am decently fixed, am I not? I did the fixing myself, didn’t I? What did I do it for? Why do you suppose that after mining in Montana I monkeyed with Morgan, roiled Rockefeller, and got ahead of Gates? For the fun of it? There is no fun in a job like that. To donate libraries? That is Carnegie’s patent. I want to splurge. In that new house of mine on Fifth Avenue I want to give cotillons and dinner dances—cotillons with automobiles and Russian sables for favors, dinner dances with government bonds for boutonnières. I want to be top of the heap.”

“Noble ambition.”

“And why not? Supposing I am self-made. I am as rich as Crœsus, whoever he may be, and just as good as the rest of them. The trouble is that in New York I don’t know anybody—except from 10 to 3. Out of Wall Street I am seven-eighths offered and nothing bid. But here it is different. On this side people who have position don’t seem to be as much afraid of losing it as they are at home. You have noticed that yourself, haven’t you?”

The young man yawned and nodded.

“Anyway,” Mr. Beamish resumed, “that’s been the case with the Finsburys. They are bankrupt, it is true, but they are not bounders, and provided I produce enough they are willing that you should marry their daughter and take her back to New York. There all you will have to do is to fill my house with the smart set. And they’ll come, too; they’ll come on a run when they find a duke’s daughter is there to receive them.”

“But what if I don’t like the girl?”

Mr. Beamish stood up and reached for a hat. “You have got to like her,” he answered shortly. “Come. It’s time for business. Ring the bell, and see if the auto is ready.”

The auto was. And presently, after a series of touf toufs, a whizz up the Champs Élysées, a bolt into the Avenue Marceau, father and son were let into the drawing-room of an appartement meublé, a miniature salon, cream and gold, and tenderly pink, where loomed a dowager, robust and rancid, flanking a tall, large-mouthed, small-eyed girl.

“Duchess, this is my son Harry,” Mr. Beamish began, and, plucking at his collar, and finding it moist, mopped himself abundantly.

The duchess assumed an expression of great amiability. “My daughter, the Lady Angelica,” she announced, with a wave of her fan, and with another, she added: “I am so sorry Finsbury is not in. But he has a perfect mania for going to the dentist’s, and that, I think, shows so much conscientiousness. Do sit down.”

The girl had moved to a sofa. Harry took a seat at her side. Mr. Beamish and the duchess ranged themselves opposite.

“Warm day,” said the fat man. At once he and his hostess lost themselves in cognate reflections.

“Do you like Paris?” Harry asked of the girl, who just raised her eyes to his. “I prefer London. But New York is good enough for me. You have never been there, have you?”

The Lady Angelica flushed, her eyes flickered, her lips half parted, then, as though by a sheer effort of will, her mouth shut tight. What she meant by the mummery Harry could not tell. But he took it for British reserve.

“Yes,” Harry continued, indifferently, “New York is a mighty nice place. We make a specialty of tall houses, high winds, beautiful manners, ready-made clothes, and pretty girls. It is all due to the climate, I believe. Did I understand you to say that you had been there?”

“My daughter,” the duchess overloudly interrupted “has not traveled much; she⸺”

Harry turned. His father was contemplating a Cupid on the ceiling. The duchess seemed to have one eye on him, the other on Angelica.

“She is only recently out of the schoolroom, you know, and⸺ Come here, Posey!”

Suddenly from somewhere, presumably from under the sofa, there filtered the cry of a cat.

“Come here, Posey, Posey, Posey.” And the duchess, leaning forward, snapped her fingers enticingly.

Mr. Beamish stood up. Harry also was rising; the girl, too. Previously flushed; now she was pale.

“They seem to have forgotten to give poor little Posey his breakfast,” the duchess added, in smiling explanation. “But you are not going, are you? Finsbury will be so sorry. Yet, why not dine with us to-morrow, just a plain family dinner at 8, and afterward my little girl can show you her water colors. She fairly dotes on water colors, and that, I think, shows such a pure mind.”

“To-Morrow, I am afraid,” Harry interjected, but his father managed to kick him.

“He will be proud to come. But how about to-day? Couldn’t you both lunch with us at Paillard’s? My auto can take you there and back in a jiffy.”

“That is my brother’s stepdaughter,” the duchess remarked to Harry, who was examining a photograph on the mantel. “Do you think she resembles Lady Essex? So many do.”

Harry moved closer to the picture. The duchess seized the opportunity to whisper to Mr. Beamish behind her fan. In a moment Harry turned.

“We shall love to,” the duchess resumed. “Lunching at Paillard’s will be quite an escapade. But we shan’t trouble you to bring us back. Our brougham can fetch us. And you won’t mind waiting a moment, while we put on our hats? Angelica!”

Trailing her daughter behind her, the duchess sailed from the room. Father and son were alone.

“Nice girl,” Mr. Beamish remarked, as the door closed.

“A peach. And so chatty.”

“Now see that you make up to her at luncheon. There is nothing like catching a girl on the fly.”

“Give me a hundred thousand a year, and catch her yourself, then. Matrimony, with a pretty girl at the other end, must be jolly good fun. But with her! Cæsar’s ghost! It would be medicine. That’s the truth.”

“It is, is it? Well, I want obedience also. You may take your medicine or your walking-stick. Just say which, and be quick.”

Harry glared about the room. Through its cream, and gold, and tender pink, the future surged. Divested of its garland of millions that future looked quite bleak.

Mr. Beamish stamped a foot.

“Which?”

“Medicine,” the boy answered, savagely. “I’ll be shot, though, if I don’t take it in capsules.”

“Don’t be slangy,” retorted the plutocrat, in whose phraseology capsules had no definite meaning.

“Scat!” cried Harry. “There’s that beastly cat again.”

From beyond there filtered anew a shrill meow. But immediately a door opened. The duchess, trailing her daughter, reappeared, and, presently, during an interchange of uplifting intellectualities, the street was reached, the auto hummed into the Champs Elysées, bowled down the avenue, and drew up at Paillard’s.

The canopied terrace was filled with people of manifest distinction, with horizontales and femmes du monde, exotics and cercleux, diplomats, and rastas. From a hall adjoining there issued the murmur of harps, the kiss of flutes, the caress of clinging measures. In the air was the savor of pine apples, the smell of orris, the odor of food and flowers, of pretty women and smart men, the atmosphere of what the French call High Life, and pronounce Hig Leaf. Mr. Beamish inhaled it voluptuously. Preceded by two maîtres d’hôtel, he led his guests to a table.

“Do you chauffe?” Harry asked Angelica, when all were seated.

“Do you, Mr. Harry?” the duchess inquired, in her stead. “I have not let my little girl learn yet, but she is passionately fond of collecting postage stamps, and that, I think, shows so much adaptability. But automobiling is very jolly, is it not?”

“It beats bridge,” Harry answered. “Wouldn’t you like to learn,” he continued, turning to the girl.

The Lady Angelica could not speak; her mouth was full of melon.

“That is the King of the Belgians,” said the duchess, indicating a voluminously bearded old party, who was being helped to a chair near by. “And is not that Mr. Astor, over there? We used to think,” she continued, expansively, “that he might marry among us. But his daughter will. Our young men have such a fondness for your pretty compatriots, and that, I think, shows so much entente cordiale. No, Mr. Beamish, no champagne; a drop of Eau de Vals if you will. After Paget, and Essex, and Craven and Curzon, then Marlborough, and, recently, Manchester, not to speak of my brother, who married a New Yorker, a Mrs. Morningside, of Morningside Park, a widow, with a daughter, such a dear, too, who, I fancy, will marry among us also. You know my brother, do you not, Mr. Beamish? But fair exchange, I often think, is not snobbery; is it, Mr. Harry? And does it not seem to you as though some of you young Americans should begin now, and lay siege to our lovely English girls. Thank you, a bit of the wing, nothing else.”

Harry turned anew to the Lady Angelica. “How would you like to be besieged by an American?” he asked, seductively.

The girl flushed. Apparently, she was about to reply, but British reserve may have prevented. She flushed afresh and looked away.

With superior tact the duchess intervened. “Tell me, Mr. Harry, is not that your ambassador over there?”

Harry turned. As he did so he heard a little plaintive cry. He turned again.

“The large, handsome man near the entrance,” the duchess insistently continued, and actually pointed with her fan.

Harry was forced to turn once more. The cry was repeated, but less plaintively, in a note louder and more shrill.

Again Harry turned. Others were turning, too. The King wheeled in his chair. A cocotte near him put her glasses up.

Angelica’s face was hid by a fan. Her thin frame shook. She seemed convulsed with laughter, with a churchlike desire to conceal it, too. Mr. Beamish was examining his fork as though it were a great curiosity.

In hasty astonishment an omnibus began ferreting under the table. With the same superior tact the duchess waved him away.

“Ce n’est rien,” she announced. “Une petite Angora, voilà tout. Angelica, you ought not to have brought her. Mr. Harry, would you be good enough, that is, my man out there”—as she spoke she motioned at the street—“would you mind fetching him? I will send Posey home by him. Poor, dear, little thing, it is the smell of ris de veau. She just dotes on ris de veau.”

“And that,” said Harry, in open mimic of the duchess, “shows, I think, such a candid nature.”

He got from his seat and made for the entrance. But in the street he discovered that he must have misunderstood the lady. The man he fancied hers spoke no human tongue. He bothered for a moment or two with another servant, but the latter turned out to be the King’s.

Harry started to go back. As he did so, he beheld the duchess entering a cab that stood a trifle beyond. Angelica was at her heels. Mr. Beamish was helping them both.

Harry hurried forward. “You are not going to take Posey home, are you?” he asked, a hand on the door. “Why, give her to me. I'll do it myself. Where is she?”

He looked from mother to daughter. Both were seated now. The girl had her veil down, but through it, at the question, he could see her mouth contract, then it opened, and from it issued a distinct meow.

Mr. Beamish slammed the door. “Allez,” he bellowed.

Quite flabbergasted, Harry fell back. His astonishment was not unnatural. Not until that moment had it occurred to him that the cat and the girl were one. Then, also, he had never heard a girl meow before. Yet, girls have, and will. Not often, of course, but semi-occasionally, in certain clinics—which Harry had never visited—and in certain treatises—which he had never read. To this inexperience and illiteracy his surprise was due.

“So—so, that is Posey?” he stuttered. “So that is Posey, is it?” he repeated instantly, in a voice more assured. “Well, you may marry that tomcat yourself. For I shan’t,” he added, defiantly. “Not for a million a month. Not for the top of the heap.”

But he addressed the Champs Élysées. His words were lost in the roar of the wide, white street. Mr. Beamish had swung into an automobile, and, in derision, perhaps, was touf-toufing away.

The machine floated on and up toward the Arc, through the glittering haze, through the swarm of glittering traps. Harry watched it go. As it fled a fantasy of finance, felines, and felonies formed and fluttered before him.

Then suddenly the vision of plutocracy and caterwauls faded away. A diminutive groom, impertinent yet correct, had, from the box of a brougham, swung, an inch from his toes. But it was not the boy, nor yet the brougham, nor even an obese coachman, who held the reins, that had vaporized his thoughts. Within the carriage a girl sat staring straight into his face.

As his eyes mingled with her own she turned. He could see her profile. He could see, too, that he had seen it before. But where? In dream? In the Louvre? In the picture of Psyche made by Gérard? Neither the lady or her tiger gave him time to determine. A door was being opened, and she was stepping out.

Then, in the perfection of the ravishment of a frock such as perhaps Doucet alone in all the world can produce, he beheld a waist that would fit in a garter, the figure of a willis in a ballad, the incandescence of beauty beautifully bedraped.

But what was she saying? Was it language of Olympus, or the tongue of France, in which she was deigning to address the groom? Yet manifestly the latter understood. He was tipping his hat. And immediately, too, Harry was enlightened. In those accents which certain sections of Fifth Avenue share with Mayfair there fell from lips of silk the perfectly plain and entirely intelligible Anglo-Saxon order: “Follow me.”

At once, under the chaperonage of the brougham, of the enormous coachman and diminutive groom, up the wide avenue she strolled.

The majority of women walk badly. It was a pleasure to watch this young person, and that pleasure Harry proceeded to enjoy. When she had stepped from the carriage, he had enveloped her with that look which strips from neck to knee. But she had not condescended to notice it, and now, her head erect, her nose in the air, her body unswayed, she passed along, disdainful, indifferent, and serene.

These airs affected him but mediocrally. It occurred to him that she was probably taking that promenade which succeeds the morning canter, and precedes the divertissements of the five o’clock, and in those divertissements he determined to participate. How he was to manage it he did not bother himself to ask. Once he passed her, but, of course, she did not look his way. He dropped behind, yet in the dropping there was not so much as the quiver of an eyelid to betoken a consciousness of his impertinence.

Women admire the brave when they do not prefer the audacious. Harry recognized the beauty of the truth of that axiom, even though he omitted to formulate it. He wanted to be devilish. He longed to. Yet how, barring downright caddishness, is it possible to be devilish with a young person who not only offers no encouragement, but who, in addition to the chaperonage of a brougham, is chaperoning herself with airs of profound contempt?

Reflections of this order are not propitious to enterprise. Only the unexpected is. Then, precisely as it always happens in life, and sometimes in fiction, the unexpected occurred. The Rue de la Boëtie—seductive and significant name!—had been reached, and through the torrent of traps which of a May afternoon pours that way, the girl was attempting to cross the avenue.

Midway on that avenue is a refuge. Before she could land there a tricycle swooped suddenly. It was within an inch of her. But athletics serve one in some stead. Before that inch could be covered Harry grabbed her, lifted her off her feet, pulled her bodily back. She was in his arms, and he, with calm effrontery, was smiling in her face.

“Are you an heiress?” he asked. “If so, you have got to marry me. You nearly had us both run over. After telling me to follow you, too⸺”

“I told you nothing of the kind. I never spoke to you in my life.”

Furiously she shook herself free, and angrily looked about her. But in the torrent the brougham must have been submerged. It was nowhere in sight.

“And now that you don’t seem to be able to take care of yourself,” Harry continued, “and, what’s more, as you seem to have no one to do it for you, I propose to take you home.”

“You will take yourself off,” the girl retorted, with the same show of splendid anger. “I never saw you before. I never want to see you again.” And her eyes, that were porcelain blue, flashed mightily.

“That’s just it,” Harry dulcetly interjected. “If you were not so uncharitable you would help me. I am a poor orphan, and I need assistance.”

“What you need is a policeman,” the girl threw back. “Now go find one, and let me alone.”

Caress a panther, and it will not necessarily rend you. The girl had shown her teeth. They were royal. But now from her voice the anger had gone. From her eyes the flash had subsided. Harry noted the change, and construed it properly. Château qui parle et femme qui écoute. From impudent he became resolute.

“Where are you stopping?” he asked.

At the question he stared deep into her eyes. She was fragrant as only a girl can be who has accounts all along the Rue de la Paix, and whose face is a wondering rose. As he stared at her she turned and looked much as the shipwrecked are rumored to do when in search of a sail. But in the seething maelstrom of the avenue, only tearing tilburys, scudding Stanhopes, and fleeting phaetons were discernible. The brougham was nowhere in sight, and helplessly she sighed and smiled.

“Across the way, at the Albe,” she answered at last, the point of her tongue just visible.

“Hurry, then, here’s a chance.” And without further preliminaries, yet with two fingers on her elbow, Harry propelled her through a channel which a sergeant-de-ville had conveniently engineered.

“You know,” he added, when ultimately the opposite shore was reached, “that when they run you down here they fine you, too. That is the reason of my solicitude.”

“Then your solicitude may cease. This is my hotel. If you presume to follow me any further, there will be somebody to show you the door.”

“Why, I can see it from here, and a very fine door it is. Would you wish me to examine it more in detail?”

But at this he raised his hat. A cab had rattled up, and a gray-bearded Englishman, who had got from the cab, was addressing the girl.

“You are just in time,” she exclaimed. “Lord Chudleigh, let me introduce a gentleman—whom I do not know.” And, with an expression that succeeded in being both diabolic and demure, she passed into the porte cochére.

Harry’s eyes accompanied her. Then, with a look of entire sweetness, he turned:

“Yes, there’s the devil of it. I haven’t the honor of knowing her, either. A locomotive was pouncing upon her a moment ago, and I took the liberty of saving her life. My name is Beamish,” he added, modestly.

“Hello! No relation to Josiah T.?”

“Unfortunately, his son.”

“Hello! Why unfortunately?”

“Oh, for a hundred reasons. I’ll skip two or three. He wants me to marry. Wants, did I say? He is holding me up.”

“That’s Josiah T. all over. He wants what he wants more than all others that want it, too. But, never mind. I’ll have a talk with him. One good turn deserves another. Meanwhile, you might come in and give us all the facts in your melancholy case. My daughter must be expecting them. Yes?”

“Why, you are a brick,” Harry exclaimed. “I had an idea, though, that your daughter was an American.”

“Yes? This way.”

Then, presently, Harry found himself au premier, in a canary-colored salon, staring again at the prettiest little girl in the world. She seemed but indifferently surprised to see him and but indifferently interested in the rather delayed introduction which ensued.

“Yes,” added Lord Chudleigh, when that ceremony had been effected. “You might give him some tea. And some tears, too, Maud. Unless he marries somebody or other he will be cut off with a million. Yes. I'll be back directly.”

“He is a brick,” Harry announced, as the door closed. “I just told him so. Now I may add that you are an angel.”

“And I may remark that you are very presuming.”

The girl was seated in a low chair. Her hat was gone, her gloves, too. She was playing with her fingers, the sunlight shuttling her hair, an image of Caprice retouched by Doucet. “And so you are to be married, are you?”

“I hope I am,” Harry, with sudden rapture, replied. “I would marry to-morrow if you would have me. Marry to-morrow!” he interrupted himself to exclaim: “I would marry right now.”

“Nonsense, you are to do as you are told. Who is the lady?”

“An escaped lunatic.”

The girl nodded, with curious sympathy. “You poor thing,” she murmured. “No wonder I thought you needed protection. And you are such a dear,” she added, absently. “I do think it a shame.”

Harry moved closer. “Am I a dear?” he asked, in a little innocent voice. “Tell me that I am.”

“You are a very enterprising young man, that’s what you are,” she cried, releasing a hand he had caught. “Can’t you behave?”

But already Harry had retreated. From without there had come the sound of familiar voices, punctuated by an equally familiar wail.

“As I am a sinner,” he gasped; “there’s that tomcat!”

“Don’t be ridiculous. It is only some relatives of mine. By the way, didn’t I see you this afternoon helping them into a cab?”

Harry, unnerved, unmanned, undone, was too abject for reply. The door had opened, and before him a horrible trio; the duchess, her daughter, and his father, stood.

“Hello!” and through a lateral entrance a bearded face emerged.

“Yes, Chudleigh, it is I,” the duchess announced. “The butler fell dead, and while he was being removed Angelica suggested coming here, and that, I think, showed such a sweet disposition.”

“Seraphic! But where did you pick up Beamish?”

“Oho,” said the fat man, “I stopped in for tea at your sister’s, and when the butler dropped dead, as the duke was at the dentist’s⸺”

“And if that isn’t Mr. Harry,” the duchess interrupted. “Angelica, did you see Mr. Harry?”

Harry, at the moment, was crossing the room.

“How did you get here?” Mr. Beamish, in a hurried whisper, hoarsely inquired of him, and as hoarsely continued: “Don’t you know that—er—that little fascination of our friend is but a slight nervous affection, which only shows itself when she is excited, and which, anyway, matrimony will cure?”

“When who is excited?” Maud had surged, a hand extended. “Mr. Beamish, since every one has forgotten to introduce us, I am Miss Morningside.”

“We were talking, Miss Morningside,” the plutocrat answered, with a bow, which he executed as though it were a feat, “we were talking of your charming connection, the Lady Angelica, and I was asking this young man if he knew that she had consented to marry me. Yes, Me. We settled it just before the butler⸺”

But the sentence was never completed. Harry exploded:

“Great Cæsar!” he cried. “I don’t wonder the poor devil dropped dead. But isn’t that too jolly?” he added, turning to Maud. “We shall be connections, too.”

“What? What’s all this about matrimony?” Lord Chudleigh called out. “I say, Beamish, you mustn’t ballyrag that boy into marrying any one of your choosing. Give him his head.”

“Thank you, Lord Chudleigh,” Harry called back. “But I wish you would give me your daughter instead.”

“His stepdaughter,” the duchess severely corrected. “Before her mother married my brother she had lost her first husband, and that, I think, showed so much savoir faire.”

Apparently, Lord Chudleigh did too. “What?” he exclaimed. “Give you Maud?”

“He saved my life,” the young woman serenely suggested.

“Hello! So he did! So he did! Pulled you out from under a runaway baby carriage, I believe. Beamish, what do you say?”

“What do I say?” answered the stock rigger, who, with Wall street agility, had calculated to an eighth the value which this new vista of smartness unrolled, and who, in one swift, rapt vision beheld in his house a duke’s daughter handing out grand pianos and polo ponies by way of cotillon favors, and an earl’s stepdaughter distributing diamond collars and four-in-hands. “What do I say? Why, it rather strikes me that we’ll corner the market; that we’ll be top of the heap.”

“And that,” said the duchess, “shows, I think⸺”

Yet what it showed to the duchess no one seemed to heed. A maître d’hôtel, preceding a footman who was weighed down with tea things, had entered the salon, and was supervising their arrangement in a corner of the room.

During the progress of these solemnities Harry, who had been standing in the embrasure of a window with the prettiest little girl in the world, edged over to his father again.

“Did I understand you to say that that little fascination of the Lady Angelica only manifests itself when she is excited?”

“Well, what of it?”

“Miss Morningside and I have been talking it over, and we have decided on a wedding present for her, which, we think, may be of use.”

Mr. Beamish sniffed with sudden suspicion. “You are getting devilish thoughtful of others. What is it?”

“A nice little cage!”

“And it is thoughtful of us, isn’t it?” Harry remarked, as a trifle overhurriedly, perhaps, he returned to where Miss Morningside stood.

“Yes, indeed; but let us think of ourselves,” that young woman answered, whereupon her hand was openly squeezed.

“Hello!” cried Lord Chudleigh. “What’s all this? Maud, come out of that window and pour the tea.”

“Yes,” said Mr. Beamish, “we don’t want any more waiters falling dead. One is enough on a day like this. Isn’t it?” he added, turning to Angelica.

And the duke’s daughter, looking down at the carpet, blushed, as she answered:

“Meow.”

The Verdict

“I don’t know where to begin.”

“Then begin at the end.”

The advice that Ten Eyck Jones gave Philip Rochester was entirely professional. Rochester was a man of what is snobbishly known as position. So was Jones, but his position was that of “bestseller.” Hence the professional quality of the advice. In life, as in letters, there is nothing like getting to the point.

Rochester, indicating a chair, dropped into another.

The chair that he indicated stood next to a table, which, heaped with costly futilities, had a cover that extended to the floor. The room itself—large, wide, furnished gravely with infinite taste, and lighted by two shaded lamps—was somber and, at the moment, soundless. The windows, high and draped, gave on one of the quietest streets in the metropolitan bedlam.

Jones, seating himself, got out a cigarette-case and looked about for a match, wondering, as he did so, what was up.

Fifteen minutes earlier, as he was rising from dinner at his club, Rochester had telephoned, begging him to come at once; and it was in response to that hurry call from a man whose college pal he had been that the novelist was then with the millionaire. That something was wrong with his friend Jones had already noted, though the shaded lamps did not reveal the fact that Rochester’s face was ashen.

“You tell me to begin at the end,” Rochester resumed. “I will. Nina is dead.”

Jones sat back. In the surprise of the announcement his cigarette-case slipped from him.

Nina was—or now, more exactly, had been—Rochester’s wife. Only the day before Jones had seen her on Fifth Avenue; yet, as always, in seeing her, he omitted to admire. She was amazingly pretty, but behind her cameo features he had divined the shrew.

Rochester half raised a hand, glanced at it, let it fall. Still under thirty, he had an ascetic face and dense, black hair. As usual with him, he was dressed in a threadbare fashion which, for a man of large means, is eminently correct.

Jones’s appearance was less fastidious. Though a novelist, he did not look it. He looked like a man of the world to whom much is absurd and nothing important. None the less, the surprise of the announcement shook him a little. In an effort to rally, he leaned over, groped for his cigarette-case, and, not finding it, straightened.

Rochester, whom the mummery perhaps perplexed, motioned.

“It was in this room, shortly before dinner. She had just entered the house. I was standing where you are seated. She came in, looked at me, gasped, half circled, crumpled. I sent for a physician—not hers, for the life of me I could not remember his name—but for any one. In relatively no time an imbecile named Folsom appeared. He said it might be her heart.”

“Good Lord!” exclaimed Jones, who, however indifferent to the lady, was a human being and found but that.

“But,” Rochester continued, “Folsom said that as he had not previously attended her he would have to notify the authorities. That is why I telephoned. I suppose the coroner may be here at any moment.”

Jones sat up.

“Phil, you have my deepest sympathy. If there were words of consolation, I would express them. There are none.”

As Jones spoke, he considered the picture—Nina Rochester strolling in and falling dead. It was as extraordinary as his own fiction, which, however, is not saying much.

“But,” he added, “don’t you see, there will have to be a postmortem?”

Bleakly Rochester nodded.

“That is why I asked you to come. I may need bail.”

Jones blinked. Bail! Was there anything behind all this, he wondered?

“Let me ask you,” he said, “did Mrs. Rochester complain at all?”

“Of her heart?” Rochester “Oh, constantly.”

As he spoke, he stood up and turned a switch. Abruptly the somber room was brilliant, and Jones saw that his friend had gone dead-white.

But the answer satisfied him. He was about to say as much when a servant appeared announcing the coroner and the coroner’s physician. Presently the two entered, one thin and vicious as a snake, the other fat, with a fabulous nose.

“Mr. Rochester?” the thin man began, addressing Jones. He waved at his companion. “Dr. Mordecai.”

The novelist got up.

“My name is Ten Eyck Jones.”

“The writer?” the coroner threw out. “I have been reading one of your stories.”

“You must have been very idle,” Jones negligently replied. Indicating his friend, he added: “This is Mr. Rochester.”

Already, and with but a glance, the coroner had taken the latter in. Already, the house, the appointments, the relaxing atmosphere of wealth had impressed him. Usually in a case that promised to be sensational—and this case certainly was promising—hot and heavy he went at it; but at the moment the ambient influences restrained. There was time enough, he thought, and he patted his chin.

“Dr. Folsom reports—”

“Quite so,” Rochester interrupted. “When he was here, I was too overcome to be entirely coherent. It is very natural that he should have reported a death to which Dr. Barker, my wife’s physician, whose name at the time I could not get, would have certified readily. Dr. Barker knew that Mrs. Rochester’s heart was weak. He had warned her about it. None the less, latterly she had been working practically night and day for a relief fund. It was too much for her. She overdid it. Probably you have charities of your own, Mr. Coroner. In that case, and in her name, I shall be glad to give you a thousand dollars for them.”

Instantly, but in French, Jones intervened.

“Don’t be a fool!”

The coroner’s eyes had narrowed.

“Ts that a bribe, sir?”

Quite as quickly Rochester took it up.

“You probably think that I don’t want an autopsy; and if so, you are right. I would like to spare the feelings of my dead wife’s family as much as possible. At the same time, if you have so much as the shadow of the peradventure of a doubt, then, if only for my own sake, I must insist on a postmortem.”

The coroner, swallowing something that did not taste like a thousand dollars, shifted.

“Let me see the body,” he said.

“This way,” Rochester replied.

II

The next moment Jones was alone. Professionally, if metaphorically, he cocked an eye. There was something queer here, something behind the scenes. What was it?

For a year and a day he had seen little of Rochester, who, for a while, had been visiting in Massachusetts. From there he had written to Jones, among other things, about a Puritan girl whom he said he was to marry. Subsequently he had shown up in town, but as one does when one has been hit, hard hit, hit on the head. He had become moody, remote, inaccessible.

Afterward, without further allusion to the Puritan maiden, Rochester’s marriage to Nina Varian had occurred. Whether it had been a success, no one save himself and his bride could have told; and now her heart had interfered. Suddenly it had stopped, and, discarding her flesh like a raiment, she had gone—in a jiffy, like that!

It was certainly odd, Jones reflected, and the oddity of it was heightened by Rochester’s demeanor, in which there was no sign of grief, or of anything, except perhaps of funk—the funk of a man too trained to betray it. Only in his curious pallor and in his equally curious bribe had it been revealed.

In an effort to clarify the situation Jones once more felt for his cigarette-case. Remembering that it had slipped from him, he bent over and groped behind the table-cover that reached nearly to the floor.

But now he had it—or no, he had something else. He drew it out and found himself looking at a six-shooter, which among the costly futilities of the room was incongruous as a pike in a tank of goldfish. Unsummoned, an empty remark of Rochester’s returned to him, charged now with significance:

“I was standing where you are seated.”

Strangling an oath, he threw the pistol back under the table, and, fumbling again, discovered the case. Then, straightening, he opened the case, took a cigarette, and was looking for a match when the three men reappeared.

“You tell me this lady was interested in some charity?” the coroner was saying.

Rochester nodded.

“Yes, and that reminds me—”

He pressed a button, sat down at the table opposite Jones, got a checkbook from a drawer, and began to write.

“I have made it to bearer,” he added as he finished, and handed it over.

Greasily the fat physician coughed and rubbed his fabulous nose; but the coroner, folding the paper, said:

“I will have a word with Barker, and then I will authorize Folsom to certify accordingly.”

At the door, in answer to the pressed button, a servant stood.

“Show these gentlemen out,” Rochester said:

“Well?” Jones put in when they had gone.

Rochester stood up, crossed the room, recrossed it, closed the door.

“Well, that’s over!”

With quick sympathy Jones eyed him.

“It must be a relief.”

Rochester mopped his face.

“Yes, for her family it will be. I am glad to have spared them that. They are very decent people. Besides, what I said was the absolute truth, though I did not tell all of it.”

Jones twisted.

“So I rather supposed. Do you care to tell me?”

With an intake of the breath, Rochester sketched a gesture.

“Yes, but beforehand tell me something. Do you think murder is ever justified?”

The sudden query was like the point of a rapier, and Jones backed from before it. Yet immediately, and in spite, too, of the six-shooter on the floor, he felt that whatever else may have happened, the possibility which the question evoked was absurd. Even Bluebeards no longer slaughter their wives. They perhaps find it simpler to love them.

That view—the optimism of which he later revised—steadied him. Lightly he was about to reply that he had killed any number of people in cold ink; but, judging the lightness ill-timed, instead he asked for a match.

Before Rochester could supply him, the servant entered.

“Mrs. Varian, sir.”

Rochester turned to Jones.

“That’s her mother, poor soul!”

Jones, at once on his feet, stretched a hand.

“I’ll look in again, Phil.”

He was as good as his word. On the morrow he returned to the house, and again the day after, but fruitlessly. Rochester was invisible. “He is suffering from aftershock,” Jones concluded, and, apart from attending the funeral and sending the usual flowers, he desisted from further effort.

Later a note came, thanking him, saying that Rochester was leaving town, and Jones wondered if he were en route for Massachusetts and the Puritan girl; but that amourette, he decided, had clearly been ended. Even otherwise, Rochester was too recently a widower to renew it.

Yet what was behind that widowerhood Jones could not picture. All that he could see was the pistol.

III

It was then October. June had come and was going before Jones saw Rochester again.

It was in his own workshop—a room containing no other evidence of the life known as literary except a vast table, upon which was a thin sheaf of copy. Upon the manuscript was a stiletto, long, wicked, brilliant, which, one adventurous night in Madrid, he had found—in his back. Long since he had recovered from its quick acquisition. Now he used it as a paperweight.

It was otherwise serviceable. It inspired. Engraved on the glittering blade was a promise—“Penetrabo.”

“I have been away,” Rochester very needlessly explained, after Jones had greeted him. “I have been to Caracas, to Rio, to Montevideo. I have been trying to get away from myself. The task is not humanly possible. I failed.”

Amicably Jones looked him over. He was less abominably dressed than before, and tan had covered the pallor of his face. Otherwise, too, he had changed, and not unbecomingly. His hair, formerly blue-black, had an eighteenth-century powdered effect. It was white.

“I’ll have a cigar, if you’ve got one,” resumed Rochester, seating himself. “And something else,” he added as Jones shoved a box at him.

“Anything you wish, Phil.”

Rochester, lighting a cigar, considered him.

“I want you to do what only a novelist can. I want you to double your personality, to put yourself in my place and tell me how, given the circumstances, you would have me act if I were a character in one of your stories.” Rochester paused and flicked his ashes. “God knows I have tried to find the way,” he continued; “but I cannot. Fate is against me!”

“Fate has nothing against any of us, Phil, except, indeed, such things as we may have against ourselves.”

Rochester shook himself. The idea was too massive for immediate digestion. Divining which, Jones, with ready sympathy, tacked.

“Tell me what is troubling you. It began in Massachusetts, did it not?”

At the clairvoyance of that, Rochester stared; but at once memory raised a latch.

“Yes, I wrote you from there. That was before my marriage. I had met somebody. I wrote you of it; but did I tell you her name? It was Priscilla. It does not picture her. No name could, except perhaps some one of those names that Poe gave to his heroines. She seemed a-tiptoe on the threshold of the beyond. When I first saw her, I thanked her. She asked me why. ‘Because,’ I said, ‘you have shown me an angel.’ ”

“I must use that!” Jones professionally reflected.

“Do you remember Euphorion?” Rochester immediately asked. “That Greek who, in Periclean days, painted only the mouth? He alone could have portrayed hers. It was ideal. So, too, were her eyes. In the lumber-room of verse is a line that runs: ‘Beauty, like a murmuring sound, had passed into her face.’ That line seemed made for her. It accompanied and announced her. I can hear it now, as I can hear her voice. The echo of both used to haunt me. There were days without number and nights without end when I thought the echo would drive me mad. On one occasion it did; but that was long afterward.”

Rochester puffed, but vainly. Relighting the cigar, he resumed:

“At the time she represented the goal in that eternal steeplechase after happiness in which, shirted and capped in the colors of hope, we all take part. Does it not seem to you that few of us ever get there? We either fall by the way or miss it by a nose. It was my misfortune to be thrown at the last hurdle. A furlong more, and the cup was mine—or at least I thought so; but I was jockeyed out of it.” Suddenly shifting, he as suddenly asked: “Do you think murder is ever justified?”

“You put that question before, Phil,” Jones answered.

“Again and again I have put it. But, tell me, do you?”

Professionally, if pontifically, Jones took it up.

“The theory of crime is human and relatively modern. Formerly people did as they liked. Subsequently they devised rules for their own behavior. Those who broke the rules were treated as malefactors. The theory of crime is therefore human. As for murder, while usual and legitimate in Neozoic times, today it properly belongs to the domain of mental pathology.”

With deepening gloom Rochester considered it. Then, and rather fiercely, he threw out:

“If you were wholly in love with a girl who was equally in love with you, and you were jockeyed out of it, how would you feel? How would you act? Would you be content to analyze the situation from the standpoint of history and therapeutics?”

Jones glanced at the stiletto.

“Few of us can tell in advance how we should act in any emergency. We may think we know, but that is because we don’t realize that we are apt to change our ideas about everything—except the high opinion which we have of ourselves.”

Rochester, entangled at once in the coils of that aphorism, resigned himself to it.

“Well, in any event, it was haphazard, in a village street, that I met her, and it was Nina who introduced me. The circumstances were such that Nina could not very well do otherwise, but she effected it as if saying:

“ ‘Here, off with your hat, and trot along with you!’

“Nina and I were both visiting at the same house. At the moment we were going on to luncheon at another house, and I thought she was just in a hurry—which she usually was. Then she marched me off. Meanwhile, after thanking Priscilla—a proceeding which Nina characterized as being in very poor taste—I could not but remark the contrast between them. You would have said that they came of alien races, from different zones. Priscilla Mather, with her Puritan face, suggested a church; Nina Varian, with her Fifth Avenue atmosphere, resembled a bazaar. One was all soul, the other all life.”

One was a lily, the other an orchid, thought Jones, who cared no more for orchids than he had for the late Mrs. Rochester.

“Well?” he proddingly threw out.

“Well, there you have the cast of the drama—myself and these two girls. They were the leads. For minor characters throw in a deacon and a plumber.”

“A plumber!” Jones exclaimed.

“Well, why not? Everybody can’t be a bestseller.”

“The Lord forbid!” Jones fervently protested, while mentally foreseeing that in this moving picture the plumber was of course the villain.

“The deacon,” Rochester resumed, “was Priscilla’s father, a thin-lipped psalm-singer in a duster. The plumber—but I will get to him presently. It was from Nina that I learned of him; but not until later. At the time I knew nothing except that I was young, that Priscilla was young, that we were both in the festival of life, and of a life filled to the brim with hosannas. Throughout the green afternoons and sudden dusks that I passed with her I had that sense of exhilaration which no grape has ever produced, and of which only those in love with love are conscious. To employ a homely expression, I felt as if I could jump out of my skin. Perhaps I was a little insane, as a healthy and happy child will sometimes become. I can remember that I would laugh for no reason, and yet what better reason could there be? But the laughter ceased, the exhilaration passed, the hosannas died in my throat. I had thought paradise so neighborly. The bitterest lesson of life is that always it lies just beyond!”

Rochester paused, opened and closed a hand.

“Between us no word had been said. It was her eyes that spoke. Mine had asked and hers had answered. No word had been said, yet our hearts had met. That is the ideal. Ours was the rapture of kisses without the contact of lips. We knew, and that knowledge transcended speech. We knew, and that knowledge exceeded bliss. In silence and the communion of spirit divinely we were betrothed—or at least I thought so. It was then, when happiness had reached its apogee, that, precisely as the lightning strikes and rescales the sky, it was then that happiness blinded and vanished.”

IV

At this point Jones lost the thread for a moment. He was thinking of the eternal story, told first perhaps in Babylon and retold ever since—the story of lovers irreparably parted at the beginning and inevitably united at the end. It is a famous story. However old, it is always new, and Jones wondered if he could not retell it, with Priscilla and Rochester—under other names—for leads.

Yet the manifest bribe to the coroner, and the antecedent object on the floor—these things blocked him. In considering them he must have missed something, for when he caught up with Rochester again the latter was telling of Boston, where he had gone for a ring, and where he had run into Nina.

“When she told me,” he was saying, “I experienced the curious and by no means enviable sensation of falling from an inordinate height. I had a sense of struggle with the intangible, in which my brain seemed to tip.”

“When she told you what?” inquired Jones, getting back at it.

“About Priscilla. It appeared that for a year she had been secretly married. Nina had stood up with her, and she told me of it—only, as she assured me, and as I realized, for my good. Yes, I realized that; but the goodness of it was that of the surgeon’s knife. God, how it hurt!”

“And what,” Jones asked, “did you say to the young woman when you saw her again?”

“I did not see her again—at least, not for a long time. I couldn’t see her. Yet I did, and constantly. She haunted me.”

Jones nodded.

“I can understand that. But why was she so—er—well, clandestine?”

“Because of her father, who would not hear of the plumber.”

“O-ho!” Jones exclaimed. “It was the plumber, was it, whom she married?”

“Well, you see, from the way Nina put it, he was not an ordinary plumber; he was what you might call a wholesaler. It is true that—”

“At the same time,” Jones interrupted, “the fact could hardly console you.”

“What could? I tried to forget—not to remember, rather—but with grief no one can argue. To banish it there is nothing but time and silence.”

“And someone else,” Jones maliciously cut in.

Rochester, exhaling smoke, looked through it at him.

“As you say. Nina became my wife. As such, and more particularly since she is no longer here, I cannot decently say anything against her. But that you may understand the situation, I can, and without discredit to her, admit that she suffered from an affliction which, probably congenital, was therefore not in the least her fault. She simply could not help it.”

“You are referring to her heart?”

“Well, yes, her heart. Now in that novel of yours—‘In Silk and Scarlet,’ isn’t it—how was it that you defined jealousy?”

“Jealousy!” Jones blankly repeated. “I am sure I don’t know; but wait a second. ‘The barometer of the affections’—was that it?”

“No. You called it inflammation of the mind, and that, poor woman, is precisely what she had. Nothing whatever, a chance remark, a momentary delay, the call of the telephone, anything, no matter what, was ground for suspicions which, believe me, were unfathomable. To argue with her was as profitable as talking at a phonograph. Once wound up, nothing could stop her.”

Except a bullet, Jones with sudden insight reflected.

“It is possible,” Rochester continued, “that she cared for me; but it is the misfortune of the jealous that they must love as though they hated, and the quintessence of it all she distilled into scenes that made life so unendurable that I took to going out. Where? Anywhere. Wherever I knew she would not be. And then, one day, I saw her.”

Appreciatively Jones gestured.

“From what you have told me, it was inevitable that Mrs. Rochester should have followed you.”

“I am not speaking of her. It was Priscilla that I saw.”

“And the plumber?”

“No; she was alone. It was on Fifth Avenue.”

“But you asked after him?”

“Yes, I did. I approached, raised my hat, and said: ‘It is so long since I have seen you. I hope you are well. And how is your husband?’—words simple enough, as you will admit, but before them she backed and wilted. Actually I could see circles forming under her eyes. Shall I ever forget the look in them? It was the imploring look of a terrorized child. With that look she shrank from me and gasped: My husband?’

“I hastened to reassure her. ‘Forgive me,’ I said, ‘I know it is a secret; but it is one I have never mentioned, one which I never thought I should mention, one which I never thought could be.’

“ ‘My husband?’ she tremblingly repeated.

“ ‘I learned of it the day after I last saw you,’ I continued. ‘Pray do not be alarmed. It was Mrs. Rochester who told me. She has not told any one else, nor shall I.’

“With a gesture infinitely pathetic she half raised a hand. ‘But I have no husband!’

“In view of what had gone before, that seemed a bit needless, and I took it up. ‘You have perhaps forgotten that my wife was your bridesmaid. She told me in confidence that you married a’—plumber, I was about to say, but somehow it seemed incongruous, and for it I substituted—‘a man to whom your father objected.’

“I had spoken very gently, but at each word she winced. It was as if I were striking her. Meanwhile her under lip had been quivering. I could see her bite it. She closed her eyes and threw her head back. I thought she was going to faint. As I realized afterward, she was reabsorbing her tears. But in a moment she looked at me, tried to speak, yet visibly she could not. Instead, she gave me a hand, and with the other she motioned at a taxi. She moved toward it and got in. I would have followed, but she closed the door, lifted her two hands, and, her lip still quivering, murmured:

“ ‘May God forgive her, Philip! It is all untrue. I had intended to be yours.’

“ ‘Where to, lady?’ the chauffeur asked.

“She must have replied, for she sank back, the motor veered, it was off, and I was alone in the crowd.”

Rather dramatic, Jones professionally reflected.

Rochester motioned.

“When people go mad, they are said to see red. Perhaps they do. What I saw was divorce. I saw, too, how it could be hastened; for I saw something else—a pistol, which I knew would be compelling, and which was then at the house. I hurried home. Nina was not there. I got the pistol and waited. Finally I heard her at the door, heard the servant open it, heard her step as she entered the room where I stood.

“How I looked, pistol in hand, I cannot say; but at sight of it and of me she stopped, her eyes widened, her mouth parted, she was going to scream. She must have seen that I knew. Then at once I came out with it.

“ ‘You lied to me! You told me Priscilla was married. You invented it to get me for yourself. Take that!’

“With the ridiculous noise of a firecracker, the pistol went off. Pointblank I had fired. She half circled and tumbled over on her face. I threw the pistol under the table and rang. When the servant came I sent for a physician. You know the rest.”

Jones, who had been surveying the ceiling, looked down. Before him, on the table, was the knife with the promise—“Penetrabo.” But beneath the surface of this drama he could not penetrate. The tale of it startled him into a belief in miracles. Only a procession of them could have preserved Rochester from the chair, and what deepened the marvel was the connivance of the physicians, whose examinations, however perfunctory, must have disclosed the truth.

For a moment he eyed the knife, then the assassin.

“I must say that you handled the coroner very adroitly! That relief-fund story which you advanced was, I take it, entirely imaginary. Even so, unless you bribed Folsom also—”

“I bribed no one,” Rochester protested. “Why should I? I did not want an autopsy. Who would? When Nina fell, I thought she had fainted. I had no idea she was dead. Do you suppose I had any intention of killing her? I hadn’t the slightest. All I wanted was to alarm her into leaving me and getting a divorce.”

“You certainly got one—with a bullet. That is very primitive, Phil!”

At that Rochester started. He stared at the novelist, who, knife in hand, looked rather primitive himself. Relentlessly the latter continued:

“It would call it Neozoic, only there were no firearms then.”

“But—” began Rochester, staring still, and broke off.

“But what?”

Impotently Rochester gestured.

“Why, nothing—nothing whatever; only I seem to have dropped a thread.”

“A thread!” Jones threw at him. “Is that the way you refer to your wife? It is true I never admired her, but then—”

“Look here!” Rochester protested. “You are all at sea. In telling you that I fired pointblank, I seem to have omitted to dot the i’s. It was a blank cartridge that I fired. In a brief summary such as I have given, one can’t think of every detail. Besides, I thought you already had it. It is no palliation, I admit, yet—”

Jones had been twisting the knife. Now the device on it prompted.

“You mean that she died of fright?”

“Certainly I do.”

V

In sheer relief, Jones sat back.

“But,” Rochester resumed, “none the less, I killed her.”

Aridly, across the novelist’s face there passed a smile.

“Though I am not imaginative enough to believe in fate, I am sufficiently commonplace to believe in an evil conscience. It was that that killed her.”

Rochester shook his head.

“No, it was I.”

Jones, knife in hand, turned on his friend.

“You are ridiculous, that’s what you are. The essence of crime is the intent, and in the absence of intention, though you were tried for it, as you might have been, you would be acquitted. But I appreciate now as I never did before the attitude of the physicians and the coroner. Knowing nothing of your pistol and less of her conscience, finding no evidence of violence, and having no reason to suspect anything else, they swallowed what you told them. It was adroit and, in view of the circumstances, excusable. On the other hand, if you had made a soiled breast of it, while you might have needed bail, not for a moment would you have been in jeopardy.”

“You’re a novelist!” retorted Rochester, who perhaps knew better—or worse.

Jones glanced at the knife.

“Now what are you to do? You tell me that you have been trying to get away from yourself and failed.”

Rochester, suffocating a sigh, took it up.

“Remorse prevented me.”

“Remorse?” Jones angrily repeated. “Rubbish! You failed because you thought of nothing but your precious self. To get away from it, you’ve got to think not of yourself, but of others. As for your remorse, it is medieval. Penitents used to expiate it in prayer. The most commendable form of prayer is a good deed. By the same token, the most important word in the dictionary is duty. You have one to perform—don’t you realize it?”

Uncertainly Rochester nodded.

“I had thought of the front.”

“The front! What earthly use could you be in that red galley?”

“I had thought, too, of joining the Trappists.”

“The Trappists! When you can have the world for monastery!”

Uneasily, in the spaciousness of that, Rochester squirmed.

“No!” Jones cried at him. “You have another duty. Have you forgotten Priscilla?”

“Forgotten her! Did Dante in his inferno forget Beatrice?”

“Don’t run into excesses,” retorted Jones, to whom the bard was sacred. “There has been but one Dante, and, except in the heaven of the cantos, no Beatrice; but Priscilla exists, and on earth—and the plumber does not. Go to her! There is your duty.”

The vista allured, yet before the witchery of it Rochester lowered his eyes.

“To do that, I would have to tell her, and—but you don’t know her—never could she forgive!”

Angrily Jones again turned on him.

“No, I don’t know her, but I would not be worth my syndicate if I did not know women, and you can take it from me that in the heart of a woman who loves always there is forgiveness. Always, do you hear me?”

“Yes,” Rochester moodily answered. “I hear you, but I doubt it.”

“I dare say; but that is because you have yet to learn that all love is pity.”

“If I could think that!” Rochester, with lifted eyes, exclaimed. “If I could think—”

Jones, brandishing the knife, cut him short.

“Don’t think—act! Action is thought in motion. You have asked me what, in your circumstances, I would have a character in fiction do. Ordinarily it would cost you one fifty to discover. Here it is, free—I would have him stride, booted and spurred, into the palace of all delights, the palace of adventure, of love and ambition, and if ever, in the high halls there, a fantom surged, I would have him exorcise the apparition, not with vain regrets, but with the joy of giving. You are not a pauper, Phil. If you think you have done evil, then efface it with good. Meanwhile—”

The knife clattered on the table. Jones stood up.

“Meanwhile there is that hurdle-race. Your description of it might have been worse. In any event it is too good for you, and I will annex it for copy purposes. But the race remains. You now know the course better than before. Go it again. Dress yourself once more in the colors of hope. Put on anew its magic shirt and cap. Off with you! Take the hurdles as if there were nothing there, and at the goal, if you win the cup, don’t thank fortune—there is no such thing—or your stars, for you have none. Thank Priscilla—it is hers to withhold or to bestow.”

Rochester, who during the tirade had listened as a prisoner at the bar listens to his attorney, flushed beneath his tan.

“By the Lord, you’re right! I will go to her. I’ll tell her all. It will be for her to condemn or acquit.”

Jones smiled.

“And when she decides the case, you might wire me.”

A week later the wire came. Lacedaemonian in brevity, apart from the address and the signature, it contained just four words:

Join me. Wedding tomorrow.

“Well,” Jones professionally reflected, as he told his servant to pack, “some day I’ll make a novel out of it all, and I’ll call it—let me see—oh, yes, I’ll call it ‘The Verdict.’ ”

Their Only Way

That night, when the last guest had gone, Ketletas, approaching his wife, put an arm about her. With her hair done up with opals and her dress looped with diamonds, in the brilliant room she shone. But undulantly she backed and smiled and said—and civilly enough: “Would you mind not mussing me?”

Ketletas strangled an oath. Still young, good natured, good looking, though not unreasonably so, a man of means and of what is amusingly termed position, before marriage he had been rather run after. So, too, had she. An heiress and a beauty, men in droves had knocked at her heart, or at least at what they thought was her heart, for while necessarily she had one, she was unware of it. Dormant and unaroused, it had never spoken. The men who knocked got for answer an uplift of her delicate chin, the level look of steady eyes and a smile not disdainful but aloof—a smile such as that with which she had just gratified her husband, whom she had accepted, de guerre lasse, because even in these liberal days spinsterhood has its restrictions, yet mainly because, for an heiress and a beauty, marriage is the conventional thing and to be accepted as such.

Conventional she intended the marriage to be. She told him so. It was as though she had told him that truffles were intended merely to be looked at. He did not believe her. He did not believe either that she understood what she was talking about. Even otherwise he felt that he could change her views. But marriage effected no change in this girl who remained fair and frigid as a polar noon.

Apart from that she was a joy in the house and at the dinners and dances that she gave, she became recognised as one of the most charming hostesses in New York, where charming hostesses abound.

It was after one of these dances that she asked Ketletas not to muss her. Ordinarily, and particularly in the drawing-room, he might not have attempted to. But it was always the same thing. Before him were truffles, odorant, delicious, yet not to be touched.

Mad as he was about her, the fact had long since envenomed. Now, strangling an oath, he felt that he could kiss her and kill her, but kiss her first. Either proceeding being hazardous, he caught at an unoffending gilt chair and smashed it to bits. It was a pretty if somewhat conventional act.

Helen backed and bubbled.

But Ketletas, his face flushed, threw at her: “One might as well ask alms of a statue as affection from you.”

Helen laughed again. “Some statues have not any.”

“Have not what?”

“Arms you said, didn’t you? There’s the Venus de Milo.”

“Damn the Venus de Milo,” thought Ketletas. But—convinced that there must be some scandal about the lady—he got out: “Anyway, somebody won her.”

“By breaking chairs?” Helen cut in and so tantalisingly that instantly she backed still farther. Again he was approaching her, and with a look in his eyes that even she knew rather well.

But in backing she had reached the wall. There there was a button. She touched it. Ketletas, who heard it ring, stopped short, speculatively.

At that, Helen looked him over, and inhumanly pretty she looked. “Don’t be tiresome,” she lightly admonished. For a second she paused, then added: “You have not seemed quite yourself lately. Why not see somebody? Yes, why not see Cally?”

She turned. A servant had entered. Indicating the wreckage she told the man to remove it.

Ketletas, turning also, walked to the end of the room. The end reached, he turned again. The servant was there, but Helen had gone.

Pursuit was idle. Before he could reach her, she would, he knew, be in her room, her women about her. Moreover the outburst with the chair had already mortified this man who, however primitive, was at least a gentleman.

Yet what could he do? he futilely wondered. The existence that he led was impossible. But at the moment, unable to conjecture any remedy for it, Helen’s mockery occurred to him and he thought of Cally—Cagliostro for short, as grateful patients sometimes called him—a man with whom he had chummed at Harvard, and gloomingly he wished himself back there. But that too being impossible he went on and up to bed, which is always a sane proceeding.

In bed, though he had ridden the whole afternoon and danced the whole evening, sleep delayed, but Cally returned. From him, his thought drifted to Gautier’s “Avatar,” a story in which a man in love with a woman who is not in love with him consults a physician and with such surprising results that ever since they have been manna to needy novelists. But that detail is negligible. Ketletas did not know of it, nor would it have interested if he had known. What preoccupied him was the story of this physician who, being an occultist, knew things that Lothario never imagined. But, for such knowledge, occultism is not always obligatory. Common sense is quite as serviceable and common sense was a commodity that Cally dispensed.

Ketletas sat up. “I’ll see him tomorrow,” he told himself. Then he lay back, sleep claimed him, and he dreamed of a regenerate Helen living only his behests to obey.

“Dreams are true while they last,” he found himself remarking to Cally when, on the morrow, he at last had speech with him. “What a nuisance it is that we cannot live in dream.”

Cally nodded. Tall, saturnine, remarkably well-dressed, he was seated before an enormous table on which there was nothing but a riding-crop and a cigar box.

The latter he opened. “What’s wrong with you now?”

Ketletas dropped in a chair. “I suppose a chap may tell his physician anything. Mayn’t he?”

“Unfortunately for the physician, most chaps do,” replied Cally who, as he spoke, helped himself to a cigar. “By the way, do you know I have not seen you in the Park lately?”

Ketletas sat back. “Well, latterly, I have taken to riding in the afternoon. I am going today. Will you join me?”

Cally, occupied in lighting the cigar, shook his head. “What have you got up your sleeve?”

Ketletas ran his long thin fingers through his thick bright hair. “It’s about my wife. She don’t care for me and I can’t make her. Last night she made me so furious that I nearly pulled the house down.”

Cally puffed and eyed him. “A very seductive method. Just the way to appeal to a woman, particularly a woman like Mrs. Ketletas.”

“But you don’t realise the confounded injustice of it.”

“Where a woman is concerned I don’t need to. To a woman there is something much superior to justice, and that is pity. Pity she can give. In return what she wants is sympathy and understanding—not an individual who irritates her at every angle of life, and that, I suppose, is what you have been doing.”

Ketletas leaned forward. “Yes, but previously, I—”

Cally waved at him. “Then it was previously that your mistakes began. Given tact, opportunity, propinquity and the desire, and any man, who is a man, can win any woman. These things, all of them, you have, except tact. Try and acquire a little. Meanwhile—”

The physician paused and puffed and threw out: “Mrs. Ketletas, I take it, is entirely convinced that you care for her?”

“Convinced! Why, good Lord! Since I first saw her I have never looked at another woman.”

Cally wreathed himself with smoke. “Then look at one, look hard and see that Mrs. Ketletas sees you at it. In cases of this kind there is nothing like jealousy on the part of the woman, particularly when complicated by indifference on the part of the man. Indifference is very winning. But men generally swear and stamp about. That is so human and therefore so artless that it heightens a lady in her own esteem and fortifies her in her attitude. Yet when the man is serene, smiling and apparently occupied elsewhere, she will say to herself, if not to him: ‘What is the meaning of this?’ And that is the psychological moment. That is the time to walk in.”

“Perhaps,” Ketletas sighed. “But not with a woman like my wife. You don’t know her as I do.”

With magnificent disdain Cally strewed his ashes on the floor. “It may be that I know her better. Mrs. Ketletas is a young and sensitive woman, and a woman who is young and sensitive resembles nothing so much as a violin. In the hands of an artist, a violin becomes a harmonious thing. In the hands of an artisan, it is merely discordant. Necessarily there are violins so wretched that no artist would touch them. But given a Cremona and a virtuoso and what duos the conjunction will produce! A young and sensitive woman is a Cremona in flesh and blood. The harmonies of which she is capable depend on the maestria of the man by whom she is approached. Now fancy yourself a virtuoso and your wife a violin. If you are to make her care for you, you must treat her as an artist should. Have a cigar?”

“But I am not an artist,” the exasperated Ketletas exclaimed. “I am a plain, everyday sort of chap.”

Appreciatively Cally nodded. “Very good then, I’ll sing another tune. Now tell me, when you are not occupied in pulling the house down, do you ever take tea with Mrs. Ketletas? For if so I can give you something to put in her cup—when she is not looking, you know.”

“Rubbish!” Ketletas snorted. “There are no love-philters any more.”

Cally threw away his cigar. “No, but instead there are pathogenic bacilli.”

Ketletas stared.

Again Cally nodded. “Do you happen to count Condillac among your acquaintances?” he asked.

Ketletas shook his head.

“Condillac,” Cally resumed, “was a philosopher. He undertook to analyze the human mind. For the purpose he imagined an adult capable of experiencing every emotion and of appreciating any idea, but having none whatever, and into the mind of this person he proposed to introduce the understanding of things, singly, one after the other. Theoretically the project was luminous. Practically it was impossible. He had no such person to play with. Moreover being, not a scientist, but a philosopher, he could not create one.”

“Well, what of it?” Ketletas, now very bored, inquired.

Cally took from the table the crop and waved it. “What he could not do I can accomplish. With certain bacilli I can give anybody a fever that will empty their mind of everything—temporarily that is, but meanwhile it will be as wax. Wax to receive, marble to retain. Do you get it?”

Ketletas, a bit dazzled, blinked. “I think I am afraid to.”

With a smile, a trifle self-satisfied, Cally shook the crop. “There is nothing to fear, faint heart. Nothing. On the contrary. By means of the bacilli, Mrs. Ketletas’ mind could be made a blank. Then, little by little, her education could proceed. Little by little she would become what you wish. Little by little your ideas, and yours only, would be implanted in her. I could tell you how to do it and you would find the occupation ideal. For you would be fashioning a nature in consonance with your own, molding a heart in your own heart’s image.”

“But,” Ketletas protested, “she might die of the fever.”

Cally laughed. “People never dic of fever. They die of idiots, of apothecaries, of imbeciles who call themselves M. D.’s. But of fever—never!”

“I never heard such rot.”

Cally put down the crop. “It is a bountiful Providence that has enabled us to despise whatever we do not understand. But to get back to our muttons, or rather to my bacilli. At some time or other every man has cause, or thinks he has cause, to complain of his wife. Against the best of women, the best of husbands will, at sometime or other, have a grievance. That is the law of matrimony. From that law my bacilli can exempt you. What do you say?”

Ketletas sprang to his feet. “I say that if I cannot win my wife by fair means, I won’t win her by foul. Damn it, Cally, you are more devilish than the old wizard in Gautier’s ‘Avatar.’ ”

Cally caressed his chin. “Since you wish to be complimentary, you might call me, not more devilish, but more modern. Flatter me, you know.”

“It amounts to the same thing,” Ketletas, making for the door, threw back. “I’ll disinfect myself of you in the Park.”

Cally saw him go and, as it happened, saw to him later. For in the Park Ketletas’ horse when going full tilt, shied widely and slipped, and Ketletas who, at the moment, was inattentively intent on his wife, came a crumpler.

Carted to his house and put on a lounge in the drawing-room, it was there that Cally, summoned by Helen, saw to him.

Quickly but methodically the physician examined, diagnosed and pronounced: “Fracture of the skull.”

Helen twisted her hands. “Will he die?”

Darkly Cally surveyed her. “Call your men. Have him put to bed. I’ll attend to the rest.”

He was as good as his word. But later, as he was leaving, Helen, intercepting him, timorously repeated that question.

“Will he die?”

Cally who was fumbling with a glove, balefully turned on her. “It is not your fault, if he doesn’t. He told me today how happy you make him! The fracture is the result.”

With that lie for knife, there and then he operated on her. Beneath it she shrank and shriveled. One hand went to her head, the other to her throat.

But Cally had not finished. “In exchange for the confidence, I told him to pay no attention to you and to interest himself elsewhere. But he could not, he is too honest. Then I offered to make you plastic, the servant of his will. It would have necessitated a preliminary illness on your part, and that I was prepared to induce. Another man—less honest—would have accepted. He reviled me and went off—to that!”

Helen’s head was bent. From her eyes two great tears fell perpendicularly without touching the cheek. Cally, his glove in the air, watched them. Then, with a shrug, he was gone.

Thereafter for a while it was as though Ketletas were dead, drowned rather, sunk into depths where nothing can follow, into those deepest depths where life is without movement, without impulse, without sensation of any kind. But ultimately, death, loosening its hold, retreated; life beckoned, calling him from where he lay, and imperceptibly, little by little, after infinite hesitations, relapses, retrievals, drifting upward from those depths he awoke to the light of day.

The first thing that he saw was Helen—or else a vision.

In a delicious torpor he closed his eyes. But had he dreamed it? When he again awoke, beside him was a strapping nurse, flanked by Cally who told him that he was better.

Ketletas did not need to be told. It was long though before he was up, longer still before he was about. But finally he was both, and one day, when he was feeling rather fit, a great event occurred, for he heard someone coming and, turning, rebeheld the vision.

At the entrance she hesitated, looked at him, moved to where he stood and, though her face spoke for her, she too was speaking, and at once he was drinking words that made his mouth champagne.

“I have been wrong,” he heard her saying. “But for your accident, but for something too that Cally told me, something else that I discovered, I might not have known it ever.” How good it tasted!

“Since then,” she added. “I have had so long to think it over. Can you forgive me?” And what vintage was there that could compare with that!

In the intoxication of it, tactlessly he took her hand. But that hand, instead of drawing away, drew him nearer, until actually his arms were about her, and there was no protest at being mussed.

So do miracles occur.

The marvel of it she increased. “Can you forgive me?” she repeated. “Oh,” she ran on, “that night you broke the chair, do you remember? You looked so wretched that I should have asked you then. But afterward, if you had tried any of Cally’s methods I never could have. You found a better way. You made me sorry for you. I could not have told you that before. I did not know it. I did not know what love was, either. It was you that taught me, and you found the only way to do it, for love, real love, all love is pity.”

She looked up at him. “Don’t you think so?”

“No, I don’t,” thought Ketletas. But he did not say it. He said nothing. He did better. Drawing her closer, he kissed her and he kissed her. That there are other ways of answering a lady, he knew. But that was his way, his only way, and it did not seem to him that it could be improved.

White Gloves

I

“You are the most beautiful thing in the world!”

Elaine, who had been looking down, looked up. She was a pretty girl, but not beautiful, or at least not extravagantly so. She had fair hair, candid eyes, cameo features, a complexion of cream, which occasionally had claret in it, and an air of having no nonsense—or, at any rate, very little nonsense—about her.

“Indeed you are!”

Ruis Ixar smiled as he spoke, displaying the gleam of white teeth, a gleam that contrasted curiously with his eyes, which were dark and melancholy, and with his skin, which was strikingly, almost unnaturally, brown. Otherwise, save for that detail, save, too, for a slight affectation in his attire, he was a good-looking young man dressed completely in white—in white serge, white shoes, white gloves.

Though the time was high noon of a midsummer day and the place a New England village, those gloves he retained. They perhaps indicated the foreigner that his name proclaimed.

A little before he had drifted—from no one knew whence—into this somnolent Massachusetts hamlet, and had settled himself at the inn, a low, two-storied building that faced the village church. Barring the inn and the post-office, the church was the only public building in this place, which, though not far from a great city, is one of the quietest I have ever known. Its name, an Indian one which it is unnecessary to give, means, in English, “place of peace.” Peaceful it was and doubtless still is, with that peace which comes of the absence of trade, the rarity of passers-by.

Peaceful, also, was the church, which was generally empty, somnolent like the village, yet, unlike it, refreshingly cool. For that reason, unless it were for another, hour after hour Ruis Ixar loitered in the dim aisles where, on week-days, the silence was stirred only by chimes that, in minor keys, sobbed, rather than announced, the flight of time. But it may be that their melancholy appealed to this young man, fusing, as it must have, with the melancholy which was his.

The pastor, a gentle soul, wondered at the unusual and persistent worshiper, and imagined that he had perhaps a crime on his conscience—a reflection for which presently he rebuked himself; for clearly, the donations that the young man put in the plate at each service betokened a grateful heart.

That idea aiding, acquaintanceship ensued, in the course of which the pastor found occasion to introduce the young man to certain people—among others, to Colonel Doremus and his daughter, Elaine.

Colonel Doremus was a large, stout man, slightly lame, who drank now and then, though not to excess. His daughter you have already met. The colonel’s home stood near the church, which latter, after the introduction, saw Ixar no more.

It was otherwise with the colonel’s home. There, hour after hour, the young man sat with the girl as he had sat in the aisles; sat, too, though less protractedly, with her father. To both of them, as was but natural, he told of himself—told that, born of Spanish parentage in Santiago de Cuba, he had been educated in England, from which country he had recently returned.

“And why not?” thought the colonel, who, rising from a seat on the porch, limped indoors and helped himself from a decanter.

But the young man was obviously a gentleman. The colonel limped back, and asked him to stop and dine.

There are men who can refuse a favor with greater grace than others can grant one. At the invitation, Ruis Ixar contemplated his gloved hands. Then, with that grace, he declined.

This occurred the day after the introduction. On subsequent occasions the invitation was renewed. Always the result was the same.

The colonel, who had been in Spain, though not in Cuba, was not surprised. Castilians, he was aware, never extend invitations, and, he reflected, perhaps did not accept them either. But the point was obscure. With a libation, he dismissed it.

Yet, though Ruis Ixar would not break bread with the colonel, he came to his house, as he had gone to the church, and gradually entered the thoughts of Elaine. Imperceptibly she began to await his coming; and on one occasion when he came, imperceptibly the claret deepened in the cream of her skin. There was no claret to deepen in his. Beneath its dark veil, it was ashen.

“He never got that coat of tan in England,” the colonel told himself. “His face looks as though it had been frozen at the north pole and then baked at the equator.

“How long is it since you were at Santiago?” he asked.

“Six weeks,” the young man answered. “After the gray London sky to which I had been so long accustomed, the ferocity of the Caribbean sun burned me to the bone—to the marrow. I fell ill, and came north to recover.”

“And why not?” thought the colonel, who, as usual, limped away.

It was on this occasion that the girl’s color deepened, for it was then that the young man’s remark about beautiful things cropped out.

“Will you give me a picture of yourself?” he added.

The girl parried.

“Will you give me yours?”

But Ixar had none. There are people who have a physical dread of the camera. He said he was one of them.

“Nonsense!” retorted Elaine, who had a way and a will of her own. “The operation is quite painless, and in Boston there is such a good man. We might motor in. It is barely twenty miles, only—”

“Only what?”

“Our chauffeur has injured himself.”

But at this Ixar, with a zeal which he afterward regretted, announced that he could run a machine. Elaine suggested that they should go at once; and shortly, with the open car for chaperon, the two young people flew off.

Presently the photographer’s studio was reached, photographs in assorted sizes were taken, and, through the summer afternoon, the two flew back.

II

At the inn, a few days later, the pictures appeared. From them Ixar selected two—one small, one large—which, after dinner, he took to Elaine.

But, as it so happened, the girl, or her father, had guests that evening. Ixar left the pictures at the door and returned to his room.

There, on the mantel, beside a box of pigments and paints, he put one of the remaining photographs. It was a head, nearly life-sized, that showed back, almost as from a mirror, the contour of his features and the melancholy of his eyes.

For a while, a trifle sadly, he studied it. Then he took a book and read. An hour passed, and another. It was getting late.

Ixar stood up, moved to the window and began singing a measure, sweet and slow, a song of far-away lands. As he sang, he could see the road over which he had motored with Elaine, and which stretched on and on until lost in the engulfing city.

At thought of the girl, and oppressed by the utter loneliness that was his, he got out of the window, hung by the sill, and, dropping a few feet to the ground, went up the road to her house.

Save for a light in one curtained window, it was dark. But behind the curtains he divined Elaine. He kissed his hand at them. Abruptly they parted. A fiery face appeared. It was the colonel’s. Ixar sank into the shadows and away.

After luncheon, the next day, he returned there, and was promptly thanked by Elaine for the photographs which he had left for her.

“The big one is excellent,” the girl resumed. “So, too, is the little one. Before they came, I had been writing a letter. I had been telling about you in it, and how nice it is to have some one to talk to here; and afterward I enclosed your picture—the little one. Of course I said to return it. The letter was to my brother.” She paused, then idly added: “I posted it last evening. It must have reached him by this time.”

Idly, also, Ixar remarked:

“I did not know you had a brother.”

“Well, he is my half-brother. My mother was a widow when she married my father, and he and Herbert never quite hit it off.”

As the girl spoke, she thought of a family legend, the story of her father attempting to punish his stepson and of the boy tearing the whip from him, lashing him with it, and throwing it in his face.

A silence ensued. During it, Ixar, lifting his voice, sang, as he had sung the night before, a song of far-away lands.

“Aloha nui, palalaha—”

As the song began, the girl made a little gesture. As it concluded, she sat looking surprised at him.

“Why,” she exclaimed, “I was thinking of Honolulu, and at once you begin on a Hawaiian air. That must be telepathy, isn’t it?”

Ixar turned his dark eyes upon her.

“How do you know what the song is?”

“Because it is an air one can’t forget. I heard my brother sing it. He has been in Honolulu. He has been there twice. The government sent him. You may have heard of him—Herbert Duncan. He is in Boston now. Why, what’s the matter?

Well she might ask. Had a dog run suddenly out and as suddenly and vicious bit Ixar on the leg, he could not have started more. For a moment his mouth twitched. It was impossible for him to turn pale, and yet, he appeared to.

“What is it?” Elaine repeated.

“The—The—” he at last began, but he did not seem to be able to get any further.

Sympathetically the girl nodded.

“You told us that at Santiago—”

“Yes. I was ill there. I have not quite recovered. I think I had best go back to the inn and lie down.”

“You won’t have anything?” Elaine asked, thinking as she spoke of her father’s decanter. “Can’t I get you—”

Ixar had risen. He thanked the girl. In thanking he looked at her—and what a look! Afterward it was to haunt her. A moment, and he had gone.

Elaine watched him go. She knew he cared for her, but concerning herself she was uncertain. Sometimes she thought she did care, sometimes she thought she did not. It was all very curious and delightful, and it had been more to clarify her own ideas than with any other object that she had written concerning him and sent his picture to her brother.

Now, as she sat musing on the porch, a motor flew up. It had but one occupant, a man, at sight of whom she exclaimed delightedly:

“Herbert! I was just thinking of you.”

Without alighting, he called to her. He had a shrewd, ugly, attractive face and a look of bulldog tenacity. As she hurried to him, he called again.

“Where is this man—what’s his name—Ixar?”

With candid eyes the girl surveyed her brother.

“Where is he? At the inn, I suppose. Why? Why do you ask? Won’t you get out?”

From a pocket he had taken a paper, which he gave her.

“I haven’t time. Here is a letter.”

“But, Herbert—” she expostulated, for already the machine was starting.

From over his shoulder he added:

“Later! I may return.”

The machine shot on, and she looked at the letter, which she had fancied was for her. It was for her father; and she thought it odd, for the two barely spoke.

Perplexed, she entered the house, where she found the colonel seated, conveniently near a sideboard.

“Here is a letter for you,” she announced. “Herbert brought it.”

“Herbert?” the old man growled.

He did not seem to believe her, but he took the letter and opened it. Then he opened his mouth, stared at the letter, stared from it at the girl, let it fall, and, his mouth still agape, got from his chair and steadied himself against the sideboard, where, with hands that shook, he helped himself to liquor.

Elaine ran to him.

“What is it?”

But now his head had begun to shake; it was as though he were palsied.

“Father, what is it?” Elaine repeated.

Her hand on his arm, anxiously she was looking at him. With a hand that still trembled, he pointed to the letter on the floor.

Elaine bent, reached for it, took it up, looked at it, and gave one low cry. Her father was just in time to catch her. She had fainted.

III

Ar first, on leaving the house, Ixar had walked slowly enough. Presently, when out of sight of it, he began to run. He ran, too, as he entered the inn, ran up the stair and into his room, where hurriedly he began to pack, and then abruptly desisted. The chimes across the way were sobbing out the time. It was just three thirty, and there was no train, he knew, for fully two hours.

He moved to the window, thinking, as he did so, that after all he could walk. But now, along the road, at full speed, a motor was approaching. It had one occupant, who, looking up, stopped the machine before the inn, jumped out, and called to him.

“Baxter!”

Ixar wheeled like a rat surprised. In search of a hiding-place he wheeled again. If he had only a weapon, he thought! He had no time to think more. There was a sound of steps that confused him. They were on the stair, in the hall, at the door, which then opened, and Elaine’s brother appeared. Producing a pistol, Herbert Duncan said, and negligently enough:

“This is rather shabby of you—don’t you think so?”

As he spoke, his eyes took in the room—the bed, the chair, the table; the trunk half packed; the picture and paints on the mantel.

A second only. With an uplift of the chin, again he turned to Ixar.

“In Honolulu, when the truth was known, you broke your word, and got away before you could be taken. At the time I hardly fancied that you would turn up here, and in a double masquerade—the masquerade of an assumed name, the masquerade of a painted skin—presume to approach my sister!”

Ixar, his back against the wall, like an animal at bay, showed his teeth.

“Dr. Duncan, I did not know! I swear to you—”

“Gammon! You knew about yourself. And now she knows. Or at least I may assume so. On learning from her that you were here, I wrote her father a letter concerning you which I have just left at his house. But, if I can prevent it, no one else shall know. If I can prevent it, she shall not be bespattered!”

With a look which the damned may have, Ixar bowed his head.

“I was going. I will go.”

Duncan nodded.

“Indeed you will. But you broke your word before. You’ll not get another chance. Instead of coming here personally, I could have notified the authorities. Because of my sister, I did not. Now there is but one way out of it, and you have got to take it!”

Ixar raised his eyes. The anguish in them was infinite.

“You have got to!” Duncan continued. Significantly, with his bulldog air, he added: “Afterward the coroner shall have the facts, but I will see to it that they are buried with you.” For a moment he paused, then threw out: “I have two pistols. One I will leave with you. With the other I will station myself outside. If you attempt to escape, I shoot. It is now a quarter to four. You have fifteen minutes. At four, if you are not—” Again he paused. “If you are not—”

A gesture completed the sentence.

Ixar sank on the chair. Turning his face from this man who arrogated to himself the triple functions of judge, jury, and executioner, he muttered dully:

“I will be.”

With befitting gravity, Duncan bowed.

“Then commend yourself to God.”

At once, placing the pistol on the table and fingering another in his pocket, he backed to the door and went along the hall, down the stair, and across the street, where, his eyes on Ixar’s window, he waited.

Obviously, he lacked the right to do as he had said he would. What is more notable, he had no intention of doing it. But it had been necessary to threaten, and the threat would, he felt, prove effective.

Meanwhile the minutes limped. At last, slowly, mournfully, the bells rang out.

Simultaneously, with the ridiculous noise of a punctured tire, there came, from the room opposite, the crack of a pistol.

With an intake of the breath, Duncan nodded. The man had kept his word—or at least had tried. For might he not have failed? Might it not be that he was but wounded?

In this uncertainty, he reentered the inn, went up the stair and down the hall to the door. It was locked.

“Baxter!” he called.

There was no answer—the sound merely of some one moving or turning or perhaps writhing there.

“Baxter!” he called again.

But now the silence was complete.

Duncan shook at the knob. The lock rattled. He put himself against the door and shoved. With a squeak, it yielded, but within there was something that resisted.

He shoved again. With a crash this time it opened, disclosing a table, overturned, that had been placed against it. It was the table that had crashed. The room itself was empty, or, more exactly, deserted. Ixar had got from the window, into the motor, and away.

In an instant, when Duncan reached the window, he could see him speeding along, headed for the engulfing city.

Immediately he told himself that he could telephone, that he could commandeer the colonel’s car.

With the double motive, he turned. On the mantel before him were the photograph and the paints and pigments. From among the latter he caught up a crayon, and, with hurried, impatient hand, scrawled across the picture:

Baxter, alias Ixar, leper.